<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../TAN-2021/schemas/TAN-T.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../TAN-2021/schemas/tan.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TAN-T xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns" TAN-version="2021" id="tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:cpg2462:eng:ward">
  <head>
    <name xml:lang="eng">Benedicta Ward's English translation of the Apophthegmata patrum, alphabetical collection,
      Evagrius</name>
    <master-location href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Arithmeticus/TAN-Evagrius/master/cpg2462/cpg2462.eng.1975.ward.xml"/>
    <license which="by_4.0" licensor="kalvesmaki"/>
    <work which="apophthegmata"/>
    <vocabulary>
      <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-key:evagrius</IRI>
      <name>General keywords associated with the TAN collection for Evagrius of Pontus</name>
      <location href="../TAN-voc/evagrius.TAN-voc.xml" accessed-when="2022-01-07"/>
    </vocabulary>
    
    <source which="ward 1984"/>
    <adjustments/>
    <vocabulary-key>
      <person xml:id="kalvesmaki" which="Joel Kalvesmaki"/>
    </vocabulary-key>
    
    <file-resp who="kalvesmaki"/>
    <resp roles="editor" who="kalvesmaki"/>
    <change when="2024-10-27" who="kalvesmaki">Started file</change>
    <to-do/>
  </head>
  
  <body xml:lang="eng">
    <!-- page 63 -->
    <div n="1" type="chapter">Abba Evagrius said, 'Sit in your cell, collecting your thoughts.
    Remember the day of your death. See then what the death of your
    body will be; let your spirit be heavy, take pains, condemn the
    vanity of the world, so as to be able to live always in the peace you 
    have in view without weakening. Remember also what happens in 
    hell and think about the state of the souls down there, their painful
    silence, their most bitter groanings, their fear, their strife, their
    waiting. Think of their grief without end and the tears their souls 
    shed eternally. But keep the day of resurrection and of presentation
    to God in remembrance also. Imagine the fearful and terrible
    judgement. Consider the fate kept for sinners, their shame before the face
    of God and the angels and archangels and all men, that is to say, the
    punishments, the eternal fire, worms that rest not, the darkness,
    gnashing of teeth, fear and supplications. Consider also the good
    things in store for the righteous: confidence in the face of God the 
    Father and His Son, the angels and archangels and all the people of 
    the saints, the kingdom of heaven, and the gifts of that realm, joy
    and beatitude.
    'Keep in mind the remembrance of these two realities. Weep for
    the judgement of sinners, afflict yourself for fear lest you too feel
    those pains. But rejoice and be glad at the lot of the righteous. Strive
    to obtain those joys but be a stranger to those pains. Whether you
    be inside or outside your cell, be careful that the remembrance of
    these things never leaves you, so that, thanks to their remembrance,
    you may at least flee wrong and harmful thoughts.'</div>
    <div n="2" type="chapter">He also said, 'Restrain yourself from affection towards many
    people, for fear lest your spirit be distracted, so that your interior
    peace may not be disturbed.</div>
    <div n="3" type="chapter">He also said, 'It is a great thing to pray without distraction but
    to chant psalms without distraction is even greater.'</div>
    <div n="4" type="chapter">He also said, 'Always keep your death in mind and do not
    forget the eternal judgement, then there will be no fault in your
    soul.</div>
    <div n="5" type="chapter">He also said, 'Take away temptations and no-one will be
    saved.</div>
    <div n="6" type="chapter">He also said that one of the Fathers used to say, 'Eat a little 
      without irregularity; if charity is joined to this, it leads the monk 
    rapidly to the threshhold of apatheia.'</div>
    <div n="7" type="chapter">One day at the Cells, there was an assembly about some matter
    or other and Abba Evagrius held forth. Then the priest said to him,
    'Abba, we know that if you were living in your own country you
    would probably be a bishop and a great leader; but at present you
    sit here as a stranger.' He was filled with compunction, but was not
    at all upset and bending his head he replied, 'I have spoken once and
    will not answer, twice but I will proceed no further.'</div>

  </body>
  
</TAN-T>