<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../TAN-2021/schemas/TAN-TEI.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../TAN-2021/schemas/tan.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" TAN-version="2021" id="tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:Evagrius_Reflections_Dysinger">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <head xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns">
    <name xml:lang="eng">English translation of Reflections (Skemmata) by Dysinger</name>
    <master-location href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Arithmeticus/TAN-Evagrius/master/cpg2433/cpg2433.eng.1991.dysinger.xml"/>
    <license which="by_4.0" licensor="kalvesmaki"/>
    <work which="Skemmata"/>
    <vocabulary>
      <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-key:evagrius</IRI>
      <name>General keywords associated with the TAN collection for Evagrius of Pontus</name>
      <location href="../TAN-voc/evagrius.TAN-voc.xml" accessed-when="2022-01-07"/>
    </vocabulary>
    
    <source which="Dysinger_1990"/>
    <adjustments>
      <normalization>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-small-caps-off</IRI>
        <name>Small caps removed.</name>
      </normalization>
      <normalization>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-color-off</IRI>
        <name>Color removed.</name>
      </normalization>
      <normalization>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-italics-off</IRI>
        <name>Italics removed.</name>
      </normalization>
      <normalization>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-xrefs-off</IRI>
        <name>Translator's references to other primary sources removed.</name>
      </normalization>
      <normalization>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:l-sep-off</IRI>
        <name>left separator, U+2028, removed</name>
      </normalization>
      <normalization which="no reference markers"/>
      
    </adjustments>
    <vocabulary-key>
      <person xml:id="kalvesmaki" which="Joel Kalvesmaki"/>
    </vocabulary-key>
    
    <file-resp who="kalvesmaki"/>
    <resp roles="editor" who="kalvesmaki"/>
    
    <change when="2024-08-09" who="kalvesmaki">Typos repaired.</change>
    <change when="2022-01-23" who="kalvesmaki">Started file</change>
    <to-do/>
  </head>
  <text>
    <body xml:lang="en">
      <div type="section" n="1">
        <ab>The CHRIST[:]
          
          as Christ, has essential knowledge; while
          
          as creator [he has] the logoi [inner meanings] of the ages; and
          
          as incorporeal [he has] the logoi of incorporeal [being]s.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="2">
        <ab>If any would see the state of the[ir] nous, let them deprive themsel[ves] of all concepts (noemata)[:]
          
          and then they will see themsel[ves] like a sapphire or the color of heaven; (Exod. 24:10)
          
          but this cannot be accomplished without apatheia, [dispassion] since it requires the cooperation of God who breathes into them the kindred light.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="3">
        <ab>Apatheia is [the] quiet state of the reasoning soul composed of gentleness and
          temperance.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="4">
        <ab>The state of the nous is the noetic (intelligible) height like the color of heaven, upon
          which the light of the holy Trinity comes at the time of prayer.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="5">
        <ab>Christ is [the] reasoning nature who has [with]in himself what is symbolized by the dove
          descending upon him. </ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="6">
        <ab>A censer is the pure nous at the time of prayer: it has no matters associated with the
          senses joined to it. </ab>
        <ab>According to virtue we will be one on the eighth day; while according to knowledge [we
          will be one] on the last day.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="7">
        <ab>The kiss of the nous is a blameworthy thing, an impassioned thought (noema) of a
          sensible concern. And thus the Savior said to the disciples, <quote>Greet no one along the
            way</quote> of virtue.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="8">
        <ab>Irascibility (thumos) is a power of the soul destructive of [tempting-]thoughts
          (logismoi).</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="9">
        <ab>Like a [guard-]dog [lit. dog-like] is the contemplative nous: through the movements of
          irascibility it hunts down all impassioned [tempting-]thoughts.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="10">
        <ab>Like a [guard-]dog [lit. dog-like] is the ascetical nous, hunting down unjust
          [tempting-]thoughts.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="11">
        <ab>Instruction is [the] denial of impiety and worldly desires.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="12">
        <ab>Fear is betrayal of the thoughts that come to [our] assistance.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="13">
        <ab>A Demonic [tempting-]thought is the image of the sensing man, constituted according to
          reason through which the nous that has fallen [lit. moved] through passion secretly says
          or does something lawlessly to an idol that is has [allowed] to creep in.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="14">
        <ab>The anchorite is one who, in the world erected according to reason, dwells justly and
          piously.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="15">
        <ab>An ascetical person is one who makes appropriate use of the gifts from God.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="16">
        <ab>The ascetical nous is one that always receives the thoughts of this world with
          apatheia.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="17">
        <ab>There are four ways by which the nous receives thoughts. The first way is through the
          eyes; the second, through hearing; the third, through memory; the fourth, through
          temperament [krasis]. Through the eyes it receives only forms of thoughts. Through
          hearing, [it receives] both forms and unformed [thoughts]; the mind [logos] signifying
          matters both sensed and contemplated. Memory and temperament [krasis] follow upon hearing,
          each forming the nous or not forming it in imitation of hearing.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="18">
        <ab>In bodies there [can be] both equality of essence and difference of essence. While in
          incorporeal [beings] there is only equality of essence, in [forms of] knowledge there is
          only difference of essence.</ab>
        <ab>For none of the contemplations is the same except contemplation of the stars. In the
          Trinity, [there is] only equality of essence [consubstantiality], for there are no
          different underlying objects as in [other] contemplations. Nor does [the Trinity] consist
          of many essences as bodies do.</ab>
        <ab>And by “essences” I mean those that contribute to the composition of a designation that
          indicates the being of the subject; but not as in the case of incorporeal [beings],
          although we [may] speak of them as equal in essence [consubstantial] in their
          receptiveness to the same knowledge.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="19">
        <ab>Since the nous receives [tempting] thoughts from the five senses, one should ponder from
          which [they are received] with greatest difficulty. And it is evident that it is by means
          of hearing, since <quote>a depressing word disturbs the heart of a man</quote>, according
          to the proverb.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="20">
        <ab>The nous occupied in ascetical practice is in the thoughts of this world. When occupied
          with knowledge it is employed in contemplation. When it [attains] to prayer, it is in
          formlessness, which is called the “place of God”. Then it will see the equality of
          essence and the difference of essence in bodies, in contemplations, and in God. </ab>
        <ab>That which concerns God clearly pertains to what is impossible, since essential
          knowledge is obscure and change does not pertain to essential knowledge.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="21">
        <ab>Some temptations lead to pleasures, others to sadness [depression], still others to
          bodily pain for human beings.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="22">
        <ab>The mind sometimes moves from one thought to another thought, sometimes from one
          contemplation to another contemplation, and then from contemplation to thoughts. But there
          are also [times] when it moves from an imageless state to thoughts or to contemplations
          and [then] back again from these to the imageless state. This happens to it at the time of
          prayer. </ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="23">
        <ab>The mind is unable to see the ‘place of God’ in itself unless it has been raised higher
          than all thoughts of practical matters. And it will not be raised higher unless it has put
          aside all the passions that bind it to perceptible objects through thoughts. And passion
          will be put aside through the virtues, and simple thoughts through spiritual
          contemplation. And this will happen when the light has been manifested to it.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="24">
        <ab>Demonic thoughts blind the left eye of the soul, which is given over to contemplation of
          things that have come to be.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="25">
        <ab>From holy David we have exactly learned what the ‘place of God’ is, for he says: In
          peace is His place established and his dwelling on Zion (Ps 75:3). The ‘place of God’ is
          therefore the reasoning soul, and his dwelling [is] the luminous nous that has renounced
          the desires of the world and been taught to behold the logoi of the earth.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="26">
        <ab>Prayer is a state of the nous destructive of every earthly thought.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="27">
        <ab>Prayer is the state of the nous [illuminated] by the sole light of the Blessed
          Trinity.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="28">
        <ab>A petition is a conversation of the nous with God requesting supplication, encompassing
          help or requesting good things.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="29">
        <ab>A vow is a willing promise of good things.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="30">
        <ab>An intercession is an invocation presented to God for the salvation of others by one who
          is greater.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="31">
        <ab>Hades is a lightless region filled with eternal darkness and gloom.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="32">
        <ab>The gnostic is a salaried day-laborer.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="33">
        <ab>The ascetic is a day-laborer, awaiting his payment.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="34">
        <ab>The nous is the temple of the Holy Trinity</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="35">
        <ab>The incarnate nous is the contemplator of all the ages.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="36">
        <ab>The impure nous is one that delays over a blameworthy passion [arising from] through
          perceptible things.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="37">
        <ab>Desire is the power of the soul that destroys anger.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="38">
        <ab>The ascetic is one who lives piously and justly [as a free citizen] in the world erected
          according to reason (dianoia).</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="39">
        <ab>The contemplative is one who shapes the sensible world according to [his] reason
          (dianoia) solely on account of its knowledge.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="40">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some accompany us as living beings [animals], others as
          human beings. [Accompanying us] as living beings are those that arise from desires and
          anger; [Accompanying us] as human beings are those arising from sadness [depression],
          vainglory, and pride; while the ones arising from acedia are a blend [of vices that
          accompany us both] as living beings and human beings.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="41">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some lead, while others follow. Those of pride* lead, those
          of anger (thumos) follow.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="42">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts that lead, some are likewise in front while others follow.
          The ones in front arise from gluttony, while those that follow arise from lust.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="43">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts that follow after the first ones, some lead and some follow.
          Those that lead are from sadness [depression], while the ones that follow are from anger.
          Thus, as Proverbs says, <quote>a sad word give rises to anger</quote>.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="44">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some are immaterial, others have some matter [i.e. objects],
          and still others have abundant matter [ie. objects]. The immaterial are those from the
          first pride; those from lust have some matter [ie. objects]; and those from vainglory have
          abundant matter [ie. objects].</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="45">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some cause harm over time, others by assent. The latter
          [harm] by the committing of sin. Those that only [harm] over time are natural. And those
          that [harm] both over time and by the committing [of sin] are those against nature: the
          demonic and those that propose vice.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="46">
        <ab>To thoughts that are good, two [tempting-]thoughts are opposed: the demonic and those
          proposing vice. To evil [thoughts] three [are opposed]: from nature, from proposing
          uprightness, and from an angel.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="47">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some have external matter [ie. objects] , while those of
          lust [have matter [ie. objects] ] from the body.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="48">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some arise from the fallen [lit. ‘moved’] soul, while others
          arise externally by means of demons.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="49">
        <ab>Of the unclean [tempting-]thoughts: some depict God as unjust, others as prejudiced,
          others as impotent, and still others as without mercy. [Depicting God as] unjust are those
          arising from lust and vainglory; as prejudiced, the [tempting-]thoughts originating from
          the second pride; as impotent, those arising from the first pride; and as unmerciful, the
          rest.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="50">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some [remain and] accompany us as monks; others [with us as]
          men of the world.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="51">
        <ab>EVERY [tempting-]thought is followed by pleasure except the [tempting-]thought of deep
          sorrow [depression].</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="52">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some are preceded by fantasies of their own [items of]
          knowledge, others by [items of] knowledge.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="53">
        <ab>The first of all [tempting-]thought[s] is love of self; after it [come] the eight.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="54">
        <ab>Some [tempting-]thoughts arise from requesting [seeking]; others arise from the common
          struggle.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="55">
        <ab>Some thought form [imprint] the mind [dianoia]; others do not form it. [The ones that]
          form it are things that arise from sight; [the ones that] do not form it are such things
          arising from the other senses that [remain and] accompany us.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="56">
        <ab>Of the [tempting-]thoughts, some are according to nature, while others are contrary to
          nature. And contrary to nature are those [arising] from desire and anger; while according
          to nature are those [arising] from father, mother, wife, and children.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="57">
        <ab>Among the [tempting-]thoughts, only the [tempting-]thoughts of vainglory and pride
          [remain and] accompany us after conquest of the other [tempting-]thoughts. </ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="58">
        <ab>To cause injury [mislead] is common to all thoughts. </ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="59">
        <ab>Of the fallen passions, some are moved by memory, others by the senses, still other by
          demons.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="60">
        <ab>All the impure [tempting-]thoughts are from desire or from anger or from deep sadness
          [depression] chain the nous.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="61">
        <ab>Only the [tempting-]thoughts of deep sadness [depression] are destructive of all the
          [tempting-]thoughts.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="section" n="62">
        <ab>The thoughts arising from sensation are five; those from memory are ten. Of these, five
          are pure if they are accomplished well; five are impure if they are accomplished badly.
          From angels there are five spiritual [concepts]; there are five from demons. Of these,
          those from [?a]vision are five: from [1] good and [2] evil memory; [3] from an angel; [4]
          from sight, and [5] from demons. Of these, two are evil: [1] from evil memory; and [2]
          from demons imitating a vision. There are three pure [thoughts]; but the imageless are
          twenty-eight.</ab>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>