<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../SERVER/release/1/dev/schemas/TAN-TEI.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../SERVER/release/1/dev/schemas/TAN-TEI.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI TAN-version="1" id="tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:Evagrius_Kephalaia_Gnostika_eng_Dysinger_S2.TAN-TEI.001"
  xmlns:tan="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ἑξακόσια προγνωστικὰ προβλήματα</title>
        <author>Evagrius Ponticus</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>translated by</resp>
          <persName><forename>Luke</forename>
            <surname>Dysinger</surname>, O.S.B.</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <biblStruct type="website">
            <monogr>
              <title>St. Evagrius Ponticus (345-399)</title>
              <author>
                <name>Evagrius Ponticus</name>
              </author>
              <editor>Fr. <forename>Luke</forename>
                <surname>Dysinger</surname>, O.S.B. </editor>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>Valyermo, California</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Fr. Luke Dysinger, O.S.B.</publisher>
                <date>1990</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Assembled 2011-2012 by <persName>Joel Kalvesmaki</persName>, based on public-domain
          material found on the website of the translator.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Unnecessary spacing and reduplication silently corrected.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Transcription does not reflect the translator's original orthography (small caps not
            reflected); color; italics; indentation. It also does not distinguish author's
            metanarrative from the translation.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <list>
        <item>
          <date when="2012-05-12">12 May 2012</date> Updated by Joel Kalvesmaki</item>
      </list>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <head xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns">
    <name xml:lang="eng">Dysinger's translation of the Kephalaia Gnostika, Syriac S2</name>
      <rights-excluding-sources rights-holder="kalvesmaki">
      <IRI>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en_US</IRI>
      <name>Exclusive of rights held and licenses offered by rightsholders of the source or sources
        listed below, this data file, insofar as it constitutes an independent work, is licensed
        under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</name>
    </rights-excluding-sources>
    <source>
      <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:external_Evagrius_Kephalaia_Gnostika_eng_Dysinger_S2</IRI>
      <name>Dysinger's online translation</name>
      <location when-accessed="2013-04-13"
        >http://www.ldysinger.com/Evagrius/02_Gno-Keph/00a_start.htm</location>
    </source>
    <declarations>
      <work>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:cpg2432</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">The Kephalaia Gnostika, written by Evagrius Ponticus</name>
      </work>
      <version>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:cpg2432#S2-eng-Dysinger</IRI>
        <name>Dysinger's English translation of S2</name>
      </version>
      <div-type xml:id="title">
        <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Title_(publishing)</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">title</name>
      </div-type>
      <div-type xml:id="century">
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:div-type-century</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">century</name>
      </div-type>
      <div-type xml:id="chapter">
        <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Chapter_(books)</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">chapter</name>
        <name xml:lang="grc">κεφάλαιον</name>
      </div-type>
      <div-type xml:id="epilogue">
        <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Epilogue</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">epilogue</name>
      </div-type>
      <recommended-tokenization which="general-1"/>
      <filter>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-small-caps-off</IRI>
          <name>Small caps removed.</name>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-color-off</IRI>
          <name>Color removed.</name>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-italics-off</IRI>
          <name>Italics removed.</name>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-xrefs-off</IRI>
          <name>Translator's references to other primary sources removed.</name>
        </normalization>
      </filter>
    </declarations>
    <agent xml:id="kalvesmaki" roles="editor">
      <IRI>http://viaf.org/viaf/299582703</IRI>             <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:self</IRI>
      <name xml:lang="eng">Joel Kalvesmaki</name>
    </agent>
    <role xml:id="editor">
      <IRI>http://schema.org/editor</IRI>
      <name xml:lang="eng">Editor</name>
    </role>
    <change when="2014-10-30" who="kalvesmaki">Started TAN-TEI file.</change>
    <comment when="2014-10-30" who="kalvesmaki">From the source: Translation by Luke Dysinger,
      O.S.B. (translation in public domain) Note that the the majority of the Greek text below is
      Frankenberg’s retroversion from the [UNRELIABLE!] Syriac S1 MS. This text, should be used with
      extreme caution: it is NOT the basis for this English translation, which relies principally
      on: [1] Guillaumont’s Syriac S2 version, [2] his French translation of S2, and [3] assorted
      Greek fragments.[1] [1] The complete text of Evagrius’ Kephalaia Gnostica survives only in
      Syriac and Armenian translations with extant Greek fragments and parallels available for only
      about one-sixth of the complete text. The majority of these fragments are reproduced in the
      Greek text above, BUT the Greek text above largely consists of a retroversion into Greek of
      Frankenberg’s 1912 edition of the UNRELIABLE Syriac text (which includes a commentary by the
      seventh-century anti-Origenist abbot, Babai the Great). Guillaumont designated this the S1
      version of the Kephalaia Gnostica: it contains no evidence of the controversial Origenist
      doctrine condemned by councils from the sixth century onwards. The problematic nature of this
      S1 version was clarified in 1958, when Antoine Guillaumont published the critical edition of a
      new Syriac version based on a manuscript tradition he designated S2. This version exists in
      only a single manuscript. Although known in antiquity, it had been denounced by ancient Syriac
      authors as the work of heretical forgers who were alleged to have intentionally altered texts
      by ‘the blessed abbot Evagrius’ in order to justify their own teachings. The surviving Greek
      fragments of the Kephalaia Gnostica uniformly attest to the priority of the S2 version,
      revealing the more widespread S1 tradition to be a drastic re-editing of Evagrius’ text ,in
      which all passages suggestive of controversial Origenist doctrine had either been eliminated
      or modified. This (expurgated) S1 version appeared very quickly, possibly anticipating by
      several decades the anathemas of 543 and 553. The Syriac manuscript evidence places it no
      later than the first third of the sixth century; and an Armenian translation of S1 may have
      been made sometime in the fifth century, that is within a century of Evagrius’ death in 399.
      The existence of both expurgated and unexpurgated versions of Evagrius’ works during the sixth
      century reflects an uneasy attitude of reverence for his writings combined with anxiety
      concerning their orthodoxy which is well-attested elsewhere in the monastic literature of the
      period. The Syriac and Greek Versions used here include the following: the critical edition of
      Syriac S1 and S2 texts ed. and trans. by A. Guillaumont, Les six Centuries des ‘Kephalaia
      Gnostica’ d’Évagre le Pontique, Patrologia Orientalis 28.1, Nº 134 (Paris, 1958). Syriac S1
      text with commentary by Babai the Great and Greek retroversion, ed. and trans. by by W.
      Frankenberg, Evagrius Ponticus, Abhandlungen der königlichen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften
      zu Göttingen, Phil.-hist. Klasse, Neue Folge, vol. 13, no. 2. (Berlin, 1912), pp. 8-471.
      Principal Greek fragments ed. by: 1) I. Hausherr, ‘Nouveaux fragments grecs d’Evagre le
      Pontique’,Orientalia Christiana Periodica 5 (1939), pp. 229-233; 2) Muyldermans, ‘À Travers la
      Tradition Manuscrite d’ Èvagre le Pontique’, Bibliothèque du Muséon 3 (Louvain: Istas, 1933),
      pp. 74, 85, 89, 93; 3) Muyldermans, ‘Evagriana. Extrait de la revue Le Muséon, vol. 42,
      augmenté de nouveaux fragments grecs inédits’ (Paris, 1931), pp. 38-44; 4) Géhin, ‘Evagriana
      d’un Manuscrit Basilien, (Vaticanus Gr. 2028; olim Basilianus 67)’, Le Muséon 109 (1996), pp.
      59-85. </comment>
  </head>
  <text>
    <body xml:lang="eng">
      <div type="century" n="I">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p n="S2">I,1. To the first good there is no opposition, because He is essentially [good];
            thus there is no opposition as regards essence,.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p n="S2">I,2. The opposition is in the qualities, and the qualities are in the creatures;
            opposition therefore is in the creatures.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p n="S2">I,3. Every reasoning nature is in its essence knowledge-seeking; and our God is
            Himself knowable: indivisibly He comes to be in those whom He has caused to be, like
            earthly science; but different from this in the substantial [nature of His] being
            is.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p n="S2">I,4. All that exists is either susceptible to opposition or is constituted of
            opposition. But those who are susceptible to opposition are not all yoked to those
            constituted of opposition.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p n="S2">I,5. Principles do not engender and are not engendered, but the intermediate
            engenders and is engendered.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p n="S2">I,6. In comparison, we are one thing but that which is in us is another thing,
            and that in which we are is another; but taken together [they] are that in which we are
            and that in which it is that we are.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p n="S2">I,7. When those that are together are raised, the number will also be raised,
            and when this is raised, that which is in us and that in which we are will be one.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p n="S2">I,8. When that in which we should be has been separated, he will engender that
            in which we are; but when that which is in us is mixed, he will raise that which will be
            raised with the number.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p n="S2">I,9. When we are in that which is, we see that which is, but when [we are] in
            that which is not, we engender that which is not. But when those in which we are will be
            raised, again it will not be that which is not.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p n="S2">I,10. Among the demons, certain oppose the practice of the commandments, others
            oppose thoughts of nature, and others oppose words [logoi]about divinity because the
            knowledge of our salvation is constituted from these three.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p n="S2">I,11. All those who now possess spiritual bodies reign over the worlds that have
            been made; and those who are joined to praktike bodies or to opposites, will exercise
            their reign over worlds yet to come. {See Sch In Ps 1 on praktike bodies and
            judgment}</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p n="S2">I,12. One ["unique"] is he who is without intermediaries, and he thus also, by
            means of mediations, is in all. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p n="S2">I,13. Among the logikoi, some possess spiritual contemplation and praktike, but
            others hindrance and judgment.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p n="S2">I,14. For each one of the arts, you see in it about the one who made it; but the
            knowledge of him who is, you will find in all things if our Lord made everything with
            wisdom. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p n="S2">I,15. When the four will be raised, also the five will be raised, but when the
            five will be raised, the four will not be raised with them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p n="S2">I,16. That which has been separated from the five will not be separated from the
            four, but that which has been separated from the four is delivered also from the
            five.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p n="S2">I,17. When that which is in us will be changed, those [things] in which we are
            will be changed, and this often to the extent that, that which is will no longer be
            named with modes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p n="S2">I,18. The goal of the praktike and of suffering is the heritage of the saints,
            but that which is opposed to the first is the cause of the second; and the end of this
            is the heritage of those who are opposed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p n="S2">I,19. Knowledge that is in the four is the knowledge of thoughts of creatures,
            but the knowledge of the One is the knowledge of him who alone is.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p n="S2">I,20. When only thoughts of all that which was made by accident remain in us,
            then only he who is known will be known only by him who knows. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p n="S2">I,21. Among the good and evil ones who are considered without necessity, certain
            [ones] are found in the soul and others outside it; but [as for] those who are said
            naturally to be evil, it is impossible that they would be outside it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p n="S2">I,22. The bodies of demons have color and form but they escape our senses,
            because the mixture is not the mixture of bodies that our senses apprehend. For when
            they wish to appear as persons, they transform themselves into the complete image of our
            body, while not showing us their bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p n="S2">I,23. The thoughts [logoi] of things on earth are the good [things] of the
            earth; but if the holy angels know them, according to the word of Teqoa, the angels of
            God eat the goods of the earth. But it is said, Man eats the bread of angels. Thus
            knowledge of the thoughts[logoi] of that which is in the earth is also known by certain
            men.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p n="S2">I,24. If the sprout is in the seed with power, also perfection is in the
            receptive one with power. But if this is so, it is not the same as the seed and that
            which is in it, nor the sprout and that which is in the grain. But the seed of that
            which is held by the sprout and the sprout of this seed are the same. For although the
            seed becomes the sprout, the seed of that which is in the sprout has not yet received
            the sprout. But when it is liberated from sprout and seed, it will have the sprout of
            the first seed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p n="S2">I,25. There are those who would sift us with temptations, either questioning the
            thoughtful part of the soul, or striving to seize the feeling part, either of the body
            or the surroundings of the body.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p n="S2">I,26. If the human body is a part of this world, but the form of this world is
            passing [away], it is also evident that the form of the body will pass [away].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p n="S2">I,27. Five are the principal contemplations under which all contemplation is
            placed. It is said that the first is contemplation of the adorable and holy Trinity; the
            second and third are the contemplation of incorporeal beings and of bodies; the fourth
            and the fifth are the contemplation of judgment and of providence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p n="S2">I,28. Among the many ways, there are three ways of salvation that together
            obtain to destroy sins; but two of them obtain alone that they might deliver from
            passions, and the virtue of the third is that it will be the cause of glory. However,
            glory accompanies the first, psalmody the second, and exaltation the third.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p n="S2">I,29. Also as with bodies go colors, forms, and numbers, thus also among the
            four elements matter is destroyed; for with them it possesses this, that it did not
            exist and it was made.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p n="S2">I,30. Only fire is distinct from the four elements, because of that which is
            living in it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p n="S2">I,31. As it is among the sons of Israel and among the lands of the land of Judah
            and in the cities of Jerusalem, thus also the sign of the symbols of thoughts is the
            portion of the Lord.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p n="S2">I,32. Those who have seen something of that which is in the natures have seen
            only their common appearance; for only the just have received their spiritual knowledge.
            But one who disputes this is like him who said, I was acquainted with Abraham when he
            traveled with two wives. He spoke the truth but he did not see the two covenants and did
            not understand those who are born from them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <p n="S2">I,33. Just as each of the arts needs a sharpened sense that conforms to its
            matter, so also the intellect needs a sharpened spiritual sense to distinguish spiritual
            things.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <p n="S2">I,34. The sense, naturally by itself, senses sensory things, but the mind [nous]
            always stands and waits [to ascertain] which spiritual contemplation gives it
            vision.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S2">I,35. Just as light, while enabling us to see everything, [itself] needs no
            light to be seen; so God, while making all things visible, needs no light by which to be
            known, for he, essentially,is light. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p n="S2">I,36. The organ of sense is not the same thing as sensation nor is the sensor
            the [same as the thing] sensed. For sense is the power by which we lay hold of matters;
            the sense organ is the member in which the sense resides; the sensor is the living being
            that possesses the senses; the[thing] sensed is what is apprehended by the senses. But
            it is not thus with the nous, for it was deprived of one of the four.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p n="S2">I,37. Spiritual "sensation" is apatheia of the reasoning soul, produced by the
            grace of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p n="S2">I,38. We say various things about sleep while awake; but [it is] during sleep
            that we experience the proof. In the same in regard to all the things we hear about God
            while outside of him: we will experience the proof of them [once we are]within him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S2">I,39. We had the seeds of virtue [within us]when we were made [in the beginning]
            - not [the seeds] of vice. For if we were not receptive of something would we have
            [within us] all its power? And since we have no power to cease existing, we do not have
            [within us] the power of the non-existant: that is if the powers are qualities and the
            non-existant not is not a quality.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p n="S2">I,40. There was [a time] when evil did not exist, and there will be [a time]
            when it no longer exists; but there was never [a time] when virtue did not exist and
            there will never be [a time]when it does not exist: for the seeds of virtue are
            indestructible. And I am convinced by the rich man [almost but not completely given over
            to every evil] who was condemned to hell because of his evil, and who felt compassion
            for his brothers . For to have pity is a very beautiful seed of virtue.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p n="S2">I,41. if death is subsequent to life, and sickness subsequent to health, it is
            evident that vice is subsequent to virtue. Death and sickness of the soul are evil, and
            virtue is more ancient than the intermediary.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <p n="S2">I,42. IT is said that God is [present] where he acts, and where he acts most,
            there he is most present; And since He acts most in the reasoning and holy natures, it
            is therefore in the celestial powers that he is most present.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p n="S2">I,43. God is in every place and he is not in a place; he is in every place for
            he is in all that exists by his manifold wisdom.. He is not in a place because he is not
            [one] among other[beings].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p n="S2">I,44. If the kingdom of the heavens is known by what is contained and that which
            contains,torment will also be known by the opposite of these things.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p n="S2">I,45. There is nothing among incorporeal[beings] that has power in bodies; for
            our soul[nous?] is incorporeal.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p n="S2">I,46. Everything in power in bodies is naturally in them in act, as well; they
            are connatural with those from whom they come. But the nous is free of [both] form and
            matter.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p n="S2">I,47. Nothing in power in the soul is able to leave it through action and then
            to subsist independently, for [the soul] was by its nature made to exist in bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p n="S2">I,48. Everything attached to bodies accompanies those by whom they are
            engendered, but nothing of this is attached to the soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p n="S2">I,49. The Monad is not moved in itself: rather, it is moved by the receptivity
            of the nous which through inattentiveness turns its face away, and which through this
            deprivation begets ignorance.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p n="S2">I,50. Everything that exists, exists for the knowledge of God; but among beings
            some are first and some are second. Knowledge is older than first beings; and the
            movement is older than second beings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p n="S2">I,51. THE movement is the cause of evil but virtue is destructive of evil.
            However, virtue is the daughter of names and modes, and the cause of these is the
            movement.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p n="S2">I,52. When the knowledge of those who are first in their administration and who
            are second by their creation will be in the principles, then only those who are first in
            their administration will receive the knowledge of the Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p n="S2">I,53. Demons who fight against the nous are called birds; those who trouble
            indignation [are called] animals; those who move desire [are called] beasts.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p n="S2">I,54. Limitless is the fullness of those who are first in their administration
            is without limit, but for emptiness limits have been set. And while second beings are
            coextensive with emptiness, they rest when the fullness causes the receptive to approach
            immaterial knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S2">I,55. Only those who are first in their creation will be delivered from the
            corruption [inherent]in action; but none among beings [will be delivered] from the
            corruption [inherent] in power.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p n="S2">I,56. The good are the cause of knowledge and torment, but the evil only of
            torment.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p n="S2">I,57. Men fear Sheol, while demons fear the abyss; but there exist [beings] even
            more cruel, such as the indescribable [or mute?] serpents.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p n="S2">I,58. one [kind of] death has birth as its first cause; another is from the
            saints against those who do not live justly; and the mother of the third is forgiveness.
            And if "mortal" [means] one who is by nature made to be freed from the body to which he
            is joined, than "immortal" must [mean] one who is not naturally made for that. For all
            who have been joined to bodies will necessarily be liberated from them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S2">I,59. Just as light and shadow are accidents of air, so virtue and vice, as well
            as knowledge and ignorance, are united with the rational soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p n="S2">I,60. If today they have received the wise steward in their homes, it is clear
            that yesterday they sat and modified their bills. However, he was called wise because he
            gave more than he was receiving.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p n="S2">I,61. There are no second beings receptive of knowledge, nor any first beings
            who were first in a place.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p n="S2">I,62. Knowledge is said to be in a place when one who isreceptive of it is
            united to one the second beings, which is accurately and principally said to be in a
            place.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p n="S2">I,63. Whether the logikoi exist always or do not exist depends on the will of
            the Creator; but whether they are immortal or mortal depends on their own will, as does
            [the question] whether they are joined or not joined to one thing or another.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p n="S2">I,64. The true life of the logikoi is their natural activity, while their death
            is an activity against nature. But if such death is so mortal as to naturally extinguish
            true life, who among beings is immortal? For every reasoning nature is susceptible to
            opposition.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p n="S2">I,65. In the knowledge of those who are second by to their creation various
            worlds are constituted and indescribable battles take place. But in the Unity nothing
            like this occurs: it is unspeakable peace, and there are only the naked noes that
            constantly quench their insatiability, if according to the word of our Savior, the
            Father judges no one, but he has given all judgment to Christ. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p n="S2">I,66. Virtues are said to be in front of us, on the side where we have the
            senses; while behind us are the vices, on the side where we do not have senses. For we
            are commanded to flee fornication and pursue hospitality. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p n="S2">I,67. Who can know the structure of the world and the activity of the elements?
            And who can understand the composition of this organ of the soul? And who can
            investigate how one is joined to the other, in what their empire consists, and how they
            participate with one another in such a way that the praktike becomes a chariot for the
            reasoning soul, which strives to attain the knowledge of God?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p n="S2">I,68. In angels nous and fire predominate, but in human beings epithumia and
            earth, and among demons thumos and air. It is said that the third approaches
            intermediaries through the nostrils, while the first [approach] the second through the
            mouth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p n="S2">I,69. One who excells in knowledge has one after him, while one who excels in
            ignorance has none.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <p n="S2">I,70. With God is said to be: first, the one who knows the Holy Trinity; and
            next after him one who contemplates the logoi concerning the intelligible [beings];
            third, then, is one who also sees the incorporeal beings; and then fourth is one who
            understands the contemplation of the ages; while one who has attained apatheia of his
            soul is justly to be accounted fifth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p n="S2">I,71. The end of natural knowledge is the holy Unity, but ignorance has no end;
            for as it is said,there is no limit to his greatness. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p n="S2">I,72. The Lord takes pity on those to whom he gives spiritual knowledge if the
            just walk in the light, but the foolish in darkness. . But the Lord also pities the
            foolish, in that he does not torment him immediately, but rather impels him from evil
            towards virtue.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p n="S2">I,73. The life of man consists of holy knowledge but the mercy of God is the
            contemplation of beings. Many of the wise of this world have promised us knowledge,
            but‘the mercies of God are better than life. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p n="S2">I,74. The light of the nous is divided into three:</p>
          <p>knowledge of the adorable and holy Trinity;</p>
          <p>and the incorporeal nature that created by it;</p>
          <p>and the contemplation of beings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p n="S2">I,75. If "the crown of justice" is holy knowledge, and the gold, moreover, that
            contains the stones denotes the worlds that have been or will be, the contemplation of
            corporeal and incorporeal nature is therefore the crown that is placed by the "just
            judge" upon the head of those who fight. .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S2">I,76. It is not to the knowledge hidden in objects that ignorance is opposed,
            but rather to the knowledge of the intelligible forms of the objects. For ignorance is
            not naturally made so as to exist in corporeal nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p n="S2">I,77. The second nature is the sign of the body,</p>
          <p>and the first [nature is] the [sign] of the soul.</p>
          <p>And the [sign of the] nous is</p>
          <p>the Christ who is united to the knowledge of the Unity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p n="S2">I,78. The first renunciation is voluntary abandonment of the objects of this
            world for the sake of the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S2">I,79. The second renunciation is the laying aside of vice, which happens through
            divine grace and human diligence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p n="S2">I,80. the third renunciation is separation from ignorance, which naturally
            becomes apparent to people according to state they have attained.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p n="S2">I,81. While the glory and light of the nous is knowledge, the glory and light of
            the soul isapatheia.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p n="S2">I,82. That which sensible death normally does in us, "the just judgment of God"
            willsimilarly accomplish for the other logikoiwhen "he is ready to judge the living and
            the dead" and to "render to each according to his works." </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p n="S2">I,83. If the Gihon is the Egyptian river that surrounds the whole land of
            [Ethiopia] Cush, from which Israel was commanded by one of the prophets not to drink, we
            also know the three other sources and the river from which the four sources are
            separated.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p n="S2">I,84. Knowledge and ignorance are united in the nous, while epithumia is
            receptive of self-control and luxury, and love and hate normally occur to thumos. But
            the first accompanies first[beings], and the second, second [beings].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p n="S2">I,85. The nous wanders when impassioned, and is uncontrolled when it attains the
            elements of its epithumia desire, but ceases from distraction when it becomes impassible
            and attains the company of incorporeal [beings] who fulfil all its spiritual
            desires.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <p n="S2">I,86. Love is the excellent state of the reasoning soul, for in it one cannot
            love anything among corruptible things more than the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p n="S2">I,87. All beings exist for the knowledge of God, but everything that exists for
            another is less than that for which it exists. Because of this, the knowledge of God is
            superior to all.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p n="S2">I,88. Natural knowledge is true understanding of those who were created for
            knowledge of the Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p n="S2">I,89. All reasoning nature was naturally made in order to exist and to know: and
            God is essential knowledge. And while opposed to reasoning nature there is
            non-existence, and[opposed] to knowledge there is evil and ignorance, there is in these
            no opposition to God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p n="S2">I,90. If this is the day called "Friday", on which our Savior was crucified,
            then all who died are a symbol of his grave; for with them [also] died the righteousness
            of God that will live again on the third day and will be raised clothed with a spiritual
            body - if today and tomorrow he accomplishes miracles and the third day it is finished.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="epilogue" n="">
          <p n="S2">The End of the First [Century]</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="II">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p n="S2">II,1. The mirror of the goodness of God, of his power and his wisdom, [these
            are] the things that in the beginning were nothing [and have] become something.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p n="S2">II,2. In second natural contemplation we see "the manifold wisdom" of Christ, he
            who served in the creation of the worlds; but in the knowledge that concerns the
            logikoi, we have been instructed on the subject of its substance.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p n="S2">II,3. The first of all (forms of) knowledge is the knowledge of the Monad and of
            the Unity, and more ancient than all natural contemplation is spiritual knowledge; the
            former, indeed, comes forth before the Creator, and it appears with the nature that has
            accompanied it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p n="S2">II,4. While the transformations are numerous, we have received knowledge of only
            four: the first, the second, the last and that which precedes it. The first, it is said,
            is the passage from vice to virtue; the second is that from apatheia to second natural
            contemplation; the third, is (the passage) from the former to the knowledge that
            concerns thelogikoi; and the fourth is the passage of all to knowledge of Blessed
            Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p n="S2">II,5. The body of what is, is the contemplation of beings; and the soul of what
            is, is knowledge of the Unity. He who knows the soul is called soul of that which is,
            and those who know the bodies are named body of that soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p n="S2">II,6. The praktike soul which, by the grace of God, has triumphed and has
            departed from the body will be in the regions of knowledge which the wings of its
            apatheia provide it. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p n="S2">II,7. For the soul of heirs, after death, these[wings] will [prove to] have been
            of assistance to it either for virtue or for vice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p n="S2">II,8. The wealth of the soul is knowledge, and its poverty ignorance; but if
            ignorance is deprivation of knowledge, wealth precedes poverty, and the health of the
            soul [precedes] its sickness. [Letter 42, Frb 596 I.7-9]</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p n="S2">II,9. Who knows the activity of the commandments? Who understands the powers of
            the soul, and how the former heal the latter and urge them on to the contemplation of
            things which exist?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p n="S2">II,10. Desirable are things that approach us through the senses, but [even] more
            desirable is their contemplation. But, because the senses do not attain knowledge due to
            our infirmity, the latter is considered superior to the former that is not attained.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p n="S2">II,11. With regard to everything composed of the four elements, things near or
            distant, it is possible for us to perceive some likeness. But only ournous is
            incomprehensible to us, as well as God, its author. Indeed, it is not possible for us to
            understand what is a nature susceptible of the Blessed Trinity, nor to understand the
            Unity, essential knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p n="S2">II,12. The right hand of the Lord is also calledhand, but his hand is not also
            referred to as right. And his hand receives increase and diminution, but it does not
            [thereby] attain as well to the right.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p n="S2">II,13. The first contemplation of nature suffices for the creation of reasoning
            nature, and the second also suffices for its conversion.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p n="S2">II,14. Thοse who live in equal bodies are not in the same knowledge, but rather
            the same world that is theirs. While those who are in the same knowledge are in equality
            of body and in the same world.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p n="S2">II,15. When reasoning nature receives the contemplation that concerns it, then
            all the power of the nous will also be healthy.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p n="S2">II,16. Such is the contemplation of all that has been made and will be, that the
            nature that is receptive of it will be able to receive also the knowledge of the
            Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p n="S2">II,17. Accompanying the knowledge that concerns the logikoi are the destruction
            of worlds, the dissolution of bodies, and the abolition of names; while [there] remains
            the equality of knowledge according to the equality of substances.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p n="S2">II,18. Just as the nature of bodies is hidden by qualities that remain in them
            and make them ceaselessly pass one into the other, so also reasoning nature is hidden by
            virtue and knowledge, or by vice and ignorance. And to say that one of these second
            things is made naturally with the logikoi is unjust, because it is with thesustasis of
            the nature that it has appeared.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p n="S2">II,19. The knowledge concerning the logikoi is more ancient than duality, and
            the knowing nature[more ancient] that all natures. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p n="S2">II,20. Second natural contemplation was immaterial in the beginning; [but] in
            the end, the Creator has revealed the nature of the logikoi by means of matter .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p n="S2">II,21. Everything that has been made proclaims the richly-varied wisdom of God;
            but there is none at all among them that provides information concerning His nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p n="S2">II,22. Just as the Word has known the nature of the Father, so the reasoning
            nature [has known] that of the Christ.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p n="S2">II,23. The image of the essence of God also knows the contemplation of things
            that are; but he who knows the contemplation of beings - he is not absolutely one who is
            the image of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p n="S2">II,24. There is only one who has acquired common names with the others.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p n="S2">II,25. Just as the body is called grain of the ear to come, so also this present
            world will be called grain of that which will come after it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p n="S2">II,26. If the wheat carries the symbol of virtue andthe straw the symbol of vice
            , the symbol of the world to come is amber [succinum] which will attract the straw to
            it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p n="S2">II,27. The nous, when it considers the intelligibles, sometimes receives their
            vision separately, and sometimes also becomes a seer of objects.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p n="S2">II,28. The sensible eye, when it looks some visible thing, does not see the
            totality: but the intelligible eye either has not seen, or else when it sees immediately
            surrounds all the sides of what it sees.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p n="S2">II,29. Just as fire potentially possesses its body, so also the nous potentially
            posseses the soul, when it is entirely mixed with the light of the Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p n="S2">II,30. The holy powers know the thoughts [prob. τὰ νοητά, the intellections cf.
            2.45] of all those over whom they have also been made guardians; but it is
            not[necessarily] over those whose thoughts [intellections]they know that they have
            received absolute guardianship.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p n="S2">II,31. Men live three lives: the first, the second and the third. The first and
            the second lives are received by those who belong to the first nature; but the third
            life by those who belong to the second nature. And it is said that the first life comes
            from what is, but that the second and the third come from what is not.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p n="S2">II,32. Just as it is not material [things] that feed bodies, but rather their
            power; so it is not objects that make the soul grow, but rather their contemplation
            .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <p n="S2">II,33. Among the objects of material knowledge, some are primary, and the others
            secondary. The first in power are corruptible, and and those [which are] second are so
            in power and in act.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <p n="S2">II,34. Just as the magnesium stone by its natural power attracts iron to it, in
            the same way holy knowledge naturally attracts to itself the pure nous.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S2">II,35. The nous also possesses five spiritual senses, with which it senses the
            substances presented to it. Vision shows it simple, intelligible objects; through
            hearing it receives the logoi that concern them; the fragrance that is a stranger to
            deceit delights the nose, and the mouth receives the flavor of the latter; by means of
            touching it it is confirmed by grasping the exact demonstration of objects. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p n="S2">II,36. It is not to all seers of intelligible objects that has been confided the
            true logos which concerns them; and it is not (only?) to those to whom there have been
            confided their logoi that they see them that see also their objects. But it is those who
            have obtained these two distinctions who are called first -born of their brothers. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p n="S2">II,37. There is one among all the beings who is without a name and whose place
            is not known [cf. Let to Mel. Frank p. 618, l. 6-7.) </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p n="S2">II,38. What is the nature of the days before the Passion, and what is the
            knowledge of Holy Pentecost?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S2">II,39. The five are related to the fifty, and the former are preparations for
            the knowledge of the latter.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p n="S2">II,40. The four are related to the forty, and the former is the contemplation of
            the forty.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p n="S2">II,41. There is one who, without the four and the five, knows the forty and the
            fifty.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <p n="S2">II,42. Who comes to the holy Pasch, and who knows the Holy Pentecost?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p n="S2">II,43. There is one who was left [behind] there; but he will also be found
            there. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p n="S2">II,44. Not all the saints eat the bread, but all drink of the chalice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p n="S2">II,45. The organs of sense and the nous both partake of sensible [things]; but
            the nous alone has intellection of the intelligible, and it thus becomes a seer of
            objects and of logoi.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p n="S2">II,46. The art apart from the artisan contains his work; and the wisdom of God
            contains all. And just as one breaks [the artist's] work who separates art from artisan
            by speaking, so also one who in his thought separates wisdom from God destroys all.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p n="S2">II,47. The Trinity is not reckoned among the contemplation of sensible or
            intelligible [things], and still less is it counted among objects: because the former is
            one quality and the latter are creatures; whereas the Blessed Trinity alone is essential
            knowledge. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p n="S2">II,48. The nous, if it advances in its own path, meets the holy powers; but if
            it [advances] in that of the organon of the soul, it falls on demons.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p n="S2">II,49. He who is first to take the ear of grain is the first of those who have
            the grain; and he who takes the second ear is the first of those who have the first ear;
            and he who takes the third ear is the first of those who have the second ear; and so on
            with all the others, until the one who abandons [both] the last ear and first - he who
            ultimately lacks the power of the grain.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p n="S2">II,50. When those who give birth will have ceased to give birth, then also the
            guardians of the house will tremble; then also the two heads will decorate with rose and
            linen. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p n="S2">II,51. The chariot of knowledge - (these are) fire and air; but the chariot of
            the ignorance - air and water.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p n="S2">II,52. Among demons, one kind are called the knowers of intelligible [things]
            and the others have also received the knowledge of the intelligible.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p n="S2">II,53. There is only one who is is adorable, he who solely has the sole
            [-begotten].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p n="S2">II,54. Knowledge - it is not in the regions of ignorance that it advances, but
            in the regions of knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S2">II,55. Some have attracted ignorance to themselves by their will, and others
            involuntarily. The second are called captives, and first are named captors: the captors
            have come, and they have taken captives. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p n="S2">II,56. The nous teaches the soul, and the soul the body; and only the "man of
            God" knows the man of knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p n="S2">II,57. We have learned that there are three high altars: of which the third is
            simple and the two (others) are composite. The wisdom which concerns the second altar
            makes known the wisdom of the third, and that which concerns the first altar is prior to
            that which is in the second.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p n="S2">II,58. To those who now dwell in the width have been given the three altars; but
            for those who (reside) in the length and in the depth, it is in the world to come that
            they will be given.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S2">II,59. "The just judgement" of our Christ, is known by the fact of the
            transformation of bodies, of regions and of worlds; his forbearance, (makes known) those
            who struggle against virtue, and his mercy, especially those who are objects of his
            providence, without their being deserving. [p85]</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p n="S2">II,60. The table of the Christ is God, and the tableof those who are exalted is
            the incorporeal and corporal nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p n="S2">II,61. The contemplation of the incorporeals which we knew in the beginning
            without matter, we now know linked to matter; but that which concerns bodies we have
            never seen without matter.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p n="S2">II,62. When the noes receive the contemplation that concerns them, then the
            entire nature of the body will also be withdrawn; and thus the contemplation that
            concerns it will become immaterial.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p n="S2">II,63. Among (different kinds of) knowledge, the one will never become material,
            and the other never immaterial; but that which is material will also be able to become
            immaterial.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p n="S2">II,64. Among the beings some have been produced before the judgement,</p>
          <p>and others after the judgement.</p>
          <p>And as regards the subject of the first [beings], no one has provided information,</p>
          <p>but as regards the subject of the second [beings], he who has been on Horeb has given
            an account.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p n="S2">II,65. By those who have attained to the perfect achievement of evil it is
            possible for us to understand the multitude of worlds that have been produced; indeed,
            it is not possible that we could accomplish all in one stroke in ignorance, because this
            is not (possible), not at all in knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p n="S2">II,66. The genesis of bodies - it is not the genesis of the logikoi which it
            makes known: rather it introduces the nature of names; and the composition of the former
            demonstrates the difference in rank of the latter.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p n="S2">II,67. Inseparable will become the separate when they will receive the
            contemplation of things that have separated them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p n="S2">II,68. It is said that those on high possess light bodies, and those below
            possess heavy [bodies]: and above the former are others who are lighter than they; while
            below the latter are those heavier than they.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p n="S2">II,69. It is not the first distinction of the logikoiand the genesis of bodies
            that the Holy Spirit has made know to us; but it is, rather, the present distinction
            between the logikoi and the transformation of bodies that He has revealed us.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <p n="S2">II,70. If God has done everything with wisdom, there is nothing created which
            does not bear, each in its particular way, the imprint ("symbol") of lights.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p n="S2">II,71. The contemplation of incorporeals remains in the non-descended; as for
            that which concerns bodies, it appears partly capable of descent and partly incapable of
            descent.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p n="S2">II,72. If the knowledge of those who are not expelled in one stroke is primary,
            it is evident that light bodies preceed heavy ones.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p n="S2">II,73. Just as He Who, by His Word has given us a revelation concerning matters
            of the world to come, it is not concerning the genesis of bodies and the incorporeals
            that He has made His exposition to us: similarly also, he who taught concerning the
            creation of this world - it is not the passage of bodies and the incorporeals that he
            has made known, but he exposes their distinction and their transformation. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p n="S2">II,74. Who has known the first distinction and who has seen the creation of
            bodies and these varied worlds, in which some holy powers have fed and which have
            exerted a blissful royalty?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p n="S2">II,75. As much as the judge has judged those to be judged, so much also has he
            made worlds; and he who knows the number of the judgements knows also the number of
            worlds.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S2">II,76. Just as varied [states?] orders distinguish the logikoi of one order from
            another, so also the places which suit the bodies and are joined to them[also
            distinguish the logikoi].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p n="S2">II,77. [In] the last judgement it is not the transformation of bodies that will
            be made manifest; rather, it will make known their destruction.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p n="S2">II,78. Each of the orders of celestial powers has been constituted either
            completely of superiors or completely of inferiors, or again of superiors and inferiors.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S2">II,79. That which advances to knowledge approaches the excellent change of
            bodies; but that which (advances) to ignorance advances to the bad change.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p n="S2">II,80. Varied is the contemplation of thisorganon of the soul;highly varied is
            that of theorgana of the celestial [beings], and more [varied still] than the latter is
            the contemplation which concerns the logikoi, because the former are habitations of
            Knowers, and the latter are susceptible of the Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p n="S2">II,81. Knowledge has engendered Knowledge, and it engenders the knowers at all
            times.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p n="S2">II,82. It is not the bodies of the spiritual powers , but only those of souls
            which are naturally suitable to feed the world that is similar to them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p n="S2">II,83. Just as the senses are changed by receiving different qualities, so too
            the nous is changed [by]constantly gazing at [richly-]diverse contemplations.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p n="S2">II,84. There was a time when the Lord wasjudge only of the living; but there
            will never be a time when he will judge only the dead; and there will be again a time
            when he will judge only theliving. (cf.Acts 10:42; 2Tim 4:1; 1Pe 4:5)</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p n="S2">II,85. If the living are receptive of increase and decrease, it is thus evident
            that these are they who are opposed to those who are dead [and] who [also]receive these
            same things. And if this is so, then there will again be new and varied bodies, and
            worlds will be created which are suitable to them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <p n="S2">II,86. Those who are outside - their bread is notshowbread, and their drink is
            full of flies; but those who are inside - their bread is showbread, and their drink is
            unspoiled. (cf. Ex 25:50; Heb. 9:2)</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p n="S2">II,87. Temporal is the movement of bodies, but timeless the transformation of
            the incorporeals.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p n="S2">II,88. The contemplation of this sensible world - it is not only to men that it
            is given as nourishment, but also to reasoning natures.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p n="S2">II,89. He who alone is seated at the right of the Father alone has knowledge of
            the right. (Ps. 109:1; Acts 2:33)</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p n="S2">II,90. They who have seen the light of the two luminaries, (?Mt. 17:3; Mk 8:4;
            Lk 9:30) are those who have seen the first and blessed light, which we will see in
            Christ, when by an excellent change we will rise before him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="epilogue" n="">
          <p n="S2">The End of the Second [Century]</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="III">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p n="S2">III,1. The Father alone knows the Christ, and the Son alone [knows] the Father,
            the latter as unique[?only-begotten?] in the Unity, and the former as Monad and Unity.
            (Mt.11:27) (for unique see also I,12; IV,16)</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p n="S2">III,2. The Christ is he who alone has within himself the Unity and has received
            the judgement of the logoi.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p n="S2">III,3. The Unity is what is now known only by Christ, he whose knowledge is
            essential</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p n="S2">III,4. It is proper to angels that they are nourished at all times by the
            contemplation of beings, to men that they are not [so nourished] at all times; and to
            demons that they are not [so nourished] at proper or improper times.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p n="S2">III,5. The noes of celestial powers are pure and full of knowledge, and their
            bodies are lights which shine on those who approach them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p n="S2">III,6. The naked nous is that which, by means of the contemplation which
            concerns it, is united to knowledge of the Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p n="S2">III,7. Each of the changes is established to feed the logikoi and those which
            feed [on it] attain to the excellent change; but those which do not feed [on it] attain
            to the bad change. .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p n="S2">III,8. The nous which possesses the last robe is that which knows only the
            contemplation of all the second beings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p n="S2">III,9. In the world to come the bodies of ignorance will be surpassed, and those
            which will follow the change will receive an increase of fire and air; and these that
            are below will concentrate henceforth on knowledge, if ‘the houses of the impious
            receive purification’ (Prv. 14:9) and that ’today and tomorrow’ the Christ ‘performs
            miracles and on the third day it is accomplished’. (Lk 13:32)</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p n="S2">III,10. The nous which is imperfect is that which again has need of the
            contemplation which is known by corporeal nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p n="S2">III,11. Corporeal nature has received the manifold wisdom (Eph. 3:10) of Christ;
            but of him it is not receptive. But incorporeal nature displays the wisdom of the Unity
            and is receptive of the Unity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p n="S2">III,12. The perfect nous is that which is able to easily receive essential
            knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p n="S2">III,13. we have known the wisdom of the Unity, united to the nature that is
            below it; but the Unity itself cannot be seen, linked to some of the beings; and because
            of this the incorporeal nous sees the Holy Trinity in those which are not bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p n="S2">III,14. The deficient soul is that whose power subject to passion inclines
            towards vain [things].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p n="S2">III,15. If the perfection of the nous is immaterial knowledge, as it is said,
            and if immaterial knowledge is solely the Trinity, it is evident that in perfection
            there will not remain anything of matter. And if that is so, the nous, forevermore naked
            will come to vision of theTrinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p n="S2">III,16. The perfect soul is one whose passible power acts according to
            nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p n="S2">III,17. These who have attained to immaterial contemplation, are also in the
            (same) state; but they are not those who are in the same state who are from now on also
            in immaterial contemplation. Indeed, it is possible that they are again in the
            contemplation that concerns the intelligibles, which also requires a naked nous , if it
            previously has also seen it nakedly.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p n="S2">III,18. Torment is the fiery suffering which purifies the passible part of the
            soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p n="S2">III,19. The first and second contemplations possess in common that they [both]
            have a naked vision, but especially this: that one is immaterial and the other
            material.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p n="S2">III,20. The change of the organa is the passage of bodies to bodies, according
            to the degree of the order of those who are joined to them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p n="S2">III,21. This is common to both second and third contemplations - that they are
            material: but especially this, that one has a naked nous and the same order; and the
            other is with bodies and in various orders.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p n="S2">III,22. The first movement of the logikoi is the separation of the nous from the
            Unity that is in it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p n="S2">III,23. This is common to all the worlds: that they are constituted of the four
            elements; but especially this - that each of them has a variation of quality.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p n="S2">III,24. The knowledge of the first nature is the spiritual contemplation which
            has served the Creator by making only the noes that are receptive of his nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p n="S2">III,25. The spiritual body and its opposite will not be (formed) of our members
            or our parts, but of a body. For the change is not a passage of members to members, but
            (the passage) of a an excellent or evil quality to an excellent or evil change. (1Cor
            15:42)</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p n="S2">III,26. The knowledge that concerns the second nature is the spiritual
            contemplation which has served the Christ by creating the nature of bodies and the
            worlds from it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p n="S2">III,27. First natural contemplation is naturally made for the separation of the
            nous, and so that it will not be separated. Indeed, that which is taught is separable,
            but that which appears in the nouswhich it know is sown to be inseperable.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p n="S2">III,28. The soul isthe nous which, through negligence, has fallen from the
            Unity; and through its carelessness, has descended to the rank of thepraktike.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p n="S2">III,29. The sign of the human state is the human body, and the sign of each
            state is the greatness of their forms, the colors, the qualites, the natural forces, the
            weakness, the time, the relative place, the increases, the modes, the life, the death,
            and what attaches to these things.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p n="S2">III,30. The nous is the seer of the Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p n="S2">III,31. It is possible to speak of the unity of thenous; but its nature cannot
            be described: because there is no knowledge of the quality of [something]composed of
            neither form nor matter</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p n="S2">III,32. The image of God is not that which is suceptible of His wisdom, for
            corporeal nature would thus be the image God. Rather that which has become susceptible
            of the Unity - this is the Image of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <p n="S2">III,33. The name of "immortality" makes known the natural unity of the nous and
            the fact that it is eternal makes known its ‘incorruptibility’. The first name - the
            knowledge of the Trinity accompanies it; and the second -the first contemplation of
            nature. (1Cor 15:53-54)</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <p n="S2">III,34. The ‘demon’ is the reasoning nature which, because of an abundance of
            thumos, has fallen from the service of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S2">III, 35. [Spiritual*] knowledge heals the nous, love [heals] thumos, and
            chastity epithumia. And the cause of the first is the second, and that of the second the
            third. [*Syriac lacks spiritual]</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p>The world is the natural sustasis that comprises the different and varied bodies of the
            logikoi, for the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p n="S2">III,37. "The stars are superior to one another by their glory" (1Cor 15:41) and
            not by bodies; but their greatness, their shapes, their distance from one another, and
            their courses are varied. The fact that some of them are united to the interior of the
            shadow of the earth, others outside of it, and others to the separating limit, provides
            information concerning their orders and concerning the government which has been
            confided to them by God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p n="S2">III,38. The judgment of God is the creation of the world, in which he provides a
            body, proportionately measured for each of the logikoi,</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S2">III,39. One part of fire is able to burn, while the other is incabable of
            burning: the part able to burn is that which burns sensible matter; incapable of burning
            is the part thatt consumes the trouble of the troubled. And the first does not burn all
            sensible matter, while the second is able to burn [up] the whole mass of trouble.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p n="S2">III,40. The ‘last trumpet’ (1Cor 15:52) is the commandment of the judge who has
            joined thelogikoi to good or bad bodies, after which there will be no bad bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p n="S2">III,41. Concerning the contemplation of beings and the knowledge of Trinity, we
            - [that is] we and the demons - provoke a great battle, one against the other: the
            latter through wanting to prevent us from knowing, and we, by striving to learn</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <p n="S2">III,42. Contemplation is spiritual knowledge of the things which have been and
            will be it is this that causes the nous to ascend to its first rank..</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p n="S2">III,43.; These who now apply themselves to approaching near[er] to knowledge
            possess in common the ‘water’ and the ‘scented oil’[i.e. chrism]; but human beings
            especially and abundantly possess ‘the oil’.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p n="S2">III,44. The intelligible ‘sun’ is the reasoning nature that contains within it
            it the first and blessed light. .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p n="S2">III,45. Just as one cannot say that one nous is older than a[nother] nous, so
            also spiritual bodies are not older that praktike bodies if the change causing the two
            organa is one ("unique").</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p n="S2">III,46. The judgement of angels is that knowledge concerning the soul’s
            infirmities which effected the ascent to health of those who had been injured.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p n="S2">III,47. One [‘unique’] is the change that is made ‘in the twinkling of an eye’
            (1Cor 15:52) which will affect each according to his degree as a result of judgement,
            and will establish the body of each according to the degree of his order. Indeed, should
            someone say that there is a change in the components apart from that which is common,
            that indicates that he is ignorant of the intellections of judgement.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p n="S2">III,48. The ‘change of the just’ is the passage from bodies that are praktike
            and seeing, into bodies which are seeing or very [clearly] seeing.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p n="S2">III,49. The nous will not be crowned with the crown of essential knowledge, if
            it has not cast far from it ignorance of the two struggles.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p n="S2">III,50. The change of sinners is the passage frompraktike or demonic bodies to
            [bodies] that are very heavy and darkened..</p>
          <p> [judgment] for the ungodly is the change from a body for asceticism to a darkened and
            gloomy one.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p n="S2">III,51. All the changes which are produced before ‘the world to come’ have
            joined some with excellent bodies, and others with bad bodies. But those which will be
            produced after that which comes will join them all to gnostic organa.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p n="S2">III,52. The intelligible ‘moon’ is the reasoning nature that is illuminated by
            ‘the sun of justice.’ </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p n="S2">III,53. Whoever has become receptive of the knowledge of God [but] who honors
            ignorance more than this knowledge - he is said to be evil. Now there is no corporeal
            nature receptive of knowledge. None of the bodies, can therefore properly be said to be
            bad.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p n="S2">III,54. ‘In the wink of an eye’ Cherubs have been appointed Cherubs, Gabriel,
            Gabriel, and human beings, human beings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S2">III,55. In the beginning the nous had [the]incorruptible God as teacher of
            immaterial intellections; but now it has received corruptible sensation as the teacher
            of material intellections.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p n="S2">III,56. Spiritual knowledge is the ‘wings’ of thenous; the [one] who knows is
            the nous of the wings. And if this is so, then objects bear the sign of ‘trees’, on
            which the nous abides, [in] which it is charmed by the leaves and [in] which it savors
            the fruits, by hastening every moment towards ‘the tree of life’ </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p n="S2">III,57. Just as those who teach letters to children trace them on tablets, so
            too the Christ, in teaching his wisdom to the logikoi, has traced it in corporeal
            nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p n="S2">III,58. He who has to see written things has need of the light; and he who has
            to learn the wisdom of beings has need of spiritual love.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S2">III,59. If all vice is naturally engendered by thelogistikon by the
            epithumetikon, or by thethumikon, and of these powers is possible for us to use them
            well or badly, it is evident, therefore, that it is by the use against nature of these
            parts that vices later happen to us. And if this is so, there has never been anything
            created by God that is evil.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p n="S2">III,60. The ‘sign of the East’ is the symbol of the saints, and the ‘sign of the
            West’ of the souls which are in Sheol. But the achievement of the return from ‘the race’
            by all is the Blessed Trinity. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p n="S2">III,61. Virtues cause the nous to see second natural contemplation; and the
            latter cause it to see first [natural contemplation]; and the first in its turn (makes
            it see) the Blessed Unity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p n="S2">III,62. The intelligible ‘star’s are reasoning natures to which it has been
            confided to illuminate those who are in the darkness.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p n="S2">III,63. He whose knowledge is is limited; his ignorance is also limited: and he
            whose ignorance is unlimited; his knowledge is also unlimited.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p n="S2">III,64. If among tasty things none is sweeter than honey and the honeycomb, and
            if the knowledge of God is said to be superior to these things, it is evident that there
            is nothing of all the things on earth that gives pleasure like the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p n="S2">III,65. Angels that will have had men as disciples on the earth will establish
            the former, in the world to come, as heirs of their government.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p n="S2">III,66. Just as the first trumpet has made known the genesis of bodies, so in
            the same way will ‘the last trumpet’ make known the destruction of bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p n="S2">III,67. All second natural contemplations bear the sign of milk, and the first
            that of honey; and it is there that the "land flows with milk and honey." </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p n="S2">III,68. Just as the first "rest" of God will make know the decrease of
            wickedness and the disappearance of thickened body, so also the second will make know
            the destruction of bodies, second beings, and the diminution of the ignorance.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p n="S2">III,69. From the contemplation of which the nouswas constituted, it is not
            possible that anything else be constituted, unless this is also receptive of the
            Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <p n="S2">III,70. It pertains to the naked nous to say what is its nature; and to this
            question now there is no reply, but at the end there will not be even the question.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p n="S2">III,71. Just as man, after receiving the [divine]inbreathing, "has become a
            living spirit", so also the nous, when it has received the blessed Trinity, will become
            living nous. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p n="S2">III,72. The inheritance of the Christ is knowledge of the Unity; and if all
            become coheirs of Christ, all will know the blessed Unity. But it is not possible for
            them to become his coheirs unless they have previously become his heirs. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p n="S2">III,73. If the day of the Lord comes like a thief in the night, no one of all
            those who are in the house knows at what time or on what day he steals from those who
            sleep. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p n="S2">III,74. Everything which pertains to corporeal nature and is called holy has
            been sanctified by the word of God ; and everything which is called holy among the
            logikoi is sanctified by the knowledge of God. But there are again some among the second
            who are sanctified by the word of God, like children, who are receptive of
            knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p n="S2">III,75. What is impure becomes so as a result of use contrary to nature or as a
            result of wickedness. And everythng used contrary to nature which is considered polluted
            comes from corporeal nature; but what is polluted as a result of wickedness,that, it is
            said, arises from reasoning nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S2">III,76. When we are formed in the womb, we live the life of plants; as infants,
            (we live) the life of animals; and, as adult, we live either the life of angels or the
            life of demons. The cause of the first life is animate nature; that of the second is
            sensation, and that of the third is the fact that we are receptive of virtue or of
            vice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p n="S2">III,77. Those [by?] whom the Holy Spirit has told us of life and death, they
            also have proclaimed to us in advance the resurrection which is to come.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p n="S2">III,78. Angels and demons approach our world; but we do not approach their
            worlds. For, we are not able to unite the angels more [closely] to God, nor could we
            propose to make the demons more impure.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S2">III,79. Those who are now under the earth will carry away to an inordinate
            wickedness those who will now have made the things of earth - the poor wretches!</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p n="S2">III,80. Knowable are corporeal nature and incorporeal (nature); but only
            incorporeal nature is knowing. God is both knowing and knowable; but it is not as
            incorporeal nature that he knows, nor is it more as corporeal nature and incorporeal
            nature that he is known.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p n="S2">III,81. He who knows God has either knowledge of His nature or knowledge of His
            wisdom "which served him in making everything". </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p n="S2">III,82. blessed are they who by means of objects receive the demonstration of
            the grace of God; and blessed also those who by knowledge can undertake an examination
            of them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p n="S2">III,83. Faith is a voluntary good which guides us towards the blessedness to
            come.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p n="S2">III,84. All the second natural contemplation bears the sign of [the] stars; and
            stars are those to whom it has been confided to illuminate these who are in the
            night.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p n="S2">III,85. All those who are baptized in water receive the delectable odor; but he
            who baptizes -it is he who has the perfumed oil .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <p n="S2">III,86. Blessed is he who has not loved anything , of second natural
            contemplation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p n="S2">III,87. Blessed is he who has not hated anything of [the] first contemplation of
            natures, except their wickedness. (N.B.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p n="S2">III,88. Blessed is he who has attained infinite knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p n="S2">III,89. Just as our body which is begotten by our parents cannot in turn beget
            them, so also the soul, which is begotten by God, can not give Him knowledge in return.
            Indeed, "What return can I make to the Lord for all He has given me?" </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p n="S2">III,90. Demons do not cease slandering thegnostikos, even when he is not in
            fault, in order to attract his nous to them. Indeed a cloud attaches to the nous and
            chases the nous far from contemplation at the moment the demons resume[their role] as
            slanderers.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="epilogue" n="">
          <p n="S2">THE END of the THIRD [CENTURY]</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="IV">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p n="S2">IV,1. God has planted for Himself the logikoi; His wisdom has, in turn, grown in
            them by their reading every kind of scripture [ܟܬܒܵܐ]</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p n="S2">IV,2. "That which can be known of God " is in those who are first by their
            genesis; and what is not knowable of Him is in His Christ.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p n="S2">IV,3. That which is knowable of Christ is in those who are seconds by their
            genesis, and that which is not knowable of Him is in His Father.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p n="S2">IV,4. The heir of Christ is one who knows the intellections of all the beings
            subsequent to the first judgement.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p n="S2">IV,5. What is knowable been revealed to the knower, partly in the knower and
            partly in the non - knower.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p n="S2">IV,6. Of that which is knowable, one part is produced in the pure, and one part
            in those who are not pure. What is produced in the first is called spiritual knowledge;
            and what falls to the second goes by the name of natural contemplation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p n="S2">IV,7. He who has placed the ful[ly] manifold wisdom in beings - he also teaches
            those who want it the art of easily becoming a seer.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p n="S2">IV,8. The coheir of Christ is one who arrives in the Unity and delights in
            contemplation with the Christ.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p n="S2">IV,9. If the heir is one thing and the inheritance another, the Word is not that
            which inherits: rather the Christ (inherits) the Word which is the inheritance; because
            anyone who inherits is thus united to the inheritance; and the Word-God is free from (or
            "for"?) union.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p n="S2">IV,10. Among writers of true doctrines, some have plunged from the first
            contemplation of nature, others from the second, and still others are fallen from the
            blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p n="S2">IV,11. If God is known by means of corporeal nature and incorporeal (nature) ,
            and that the two contemplations of these (natures) vivify thelogikoi, it is very
            well-said that God "is known by the interior of the two living" </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p n="S2">IV,12. The intelligible circumcision is a voluntary distant removal of the
            passions that (are made) for the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p n="S2">IV,13. Those "who share in flesh and blood" are children ; now whoever is young
            is neither good nor bad. It is thus well said that men are intermediate between angels
            and demons.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p n="S2">IV,14 Just as the pledges which are in bodies are a small part of the body, so
            also the pledes which are in knowledge[s] are a certain part of the knowledge of
            beings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p n="S2">IV,15. If the whole world of men is a world of children, one day they will
            attain the age of adulthood befitting the just or the impious.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p n="S2">IV,16. The only-begotten is he before whom no other has been begotten, and after
            whom no (other) has been. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p n="S2">IV,17. It is said that "up" is where knowledge leads those who posess it, and
            "down" is where ignorance leads those who posess it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p n="S2">IV,18. The intelligible anointing is the spiritual knowledge of the holy Unity,
            2 and the Christ is he who is united to this knowledge. 3 And if this is so, the Christ
            is not the Word in the beginning,4 just as as he who is anointed is not God in the
            beginning. 5 Rather the latter [God] because of the former [anointed] is the Christ, and
            the former[anointed] because of the latter [God] is God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p n="S2">IV,19. One is a number of quantity, and quantity is linked to corporeal nature;
            number therefore pertains to second natural contemplation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p n="S2">IV,20. The first is only he before whom there are no others, and after whom the
            others come to be.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p n="S2">IV,21. The anointing either indicates knowledge of the Unity or [it] designates
            the contemplation of beings. And if Christ is anointed more than the others , it is
            evident that he is anointed with knowledge of the Unity. Because of this, he alone is
            said to be seated at the right of his Father ; the right which here, according to the
            rule of the gnostikoi, indicates the Monad and the Unity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p n="S2">IV,22 Just as those who offer symbolic sacrifices burn up through the virtues
            the bestial movements of the soul, so do those who sacrifice to demons destroy through
            the vices the natural activites of the soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p n="S2">IV,23. Moses and Elijah are not the Kingdom of God, if the latter is
            contemplation, and the former the saints. How is it therefore that our Savior, after
            promising to show the disciples the kingdom of God, shows them - having a spiritual body
            himself - - Moses and Elijah on the mountain?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p n="S2">IV,24. The firstborn from among the dead is he who is raised from the dead, and
            [is] the first to assume a spiritual body </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p n="S2">IV,25 Just as the light that shines in holy temples is the symbol of spiritual
            knowledge, so also that in the house of idols is the sign of untrue doctrines and logoi
            . The first is nourished by the oil of holy love, and the second it by the worldly love
            that loves the world and what is in it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p n="S2">IV,26. If on the third day the Christ "is accomplished" and on the preceding day
            the wood gathered in the desert is burned, it is evident that "today" is that which is
            called Friday, when "at the eleventh hour" the nations have been called by our Savior to
            eternal life</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p n="S2">IV,27. The symbol which has appeared to the Baptist of the one baptized - , is
            it that which is in the first contemplation, or the second, or in the third? And again
            is it possible that the Unity could be imprinted in a form as that [symbol], however
            there is here a danger which we make known openly openly; but you will correct this
            symbol among the gnostikoi</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p n="S2">IV,28. The intelligible unleavened loaves are the state of the reasoning soul
            which is constituted by pure virtues and true doctrines.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p n="S2">IV,29. Just as if the earth were destroyed night would no longer exist on the
            face of the firmament, so when vice will be removed ignorance will no longer exist among
            the logikoi. Ignorance is the shadow of evil, in which those who walk there, as in the
            night, are illuminated by the [lamp-] oil of Christ and see the stars, according to the
            knowledge that they are worthy of receiving; and - for them as well - the stars will
            fall for them, if they do not return promptly to the sun of justice. , </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p n="S2">IV,30. If the wealth of God, which is to come is the spiritual contemplation of
            worlds that will be, those who limit the kingdom of heaven to the palace and the banquet
            will be disconcerted.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p n="S2">IV,31. Just as the star hidden by the interposition of another star is higher
            than it, so one who is much more humble that another will be found, in the world to
            come, to be more exalted than he.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p n="S2">IV,32. The lobe of the liver is the first [tempting-] thought that is
            constituted by the concupiscible part of the soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <p n="S2">IV,33. The merciless at death are received by merciless demons; and those more
            merciless [are received] by [demons] who are themselves even less human. And if these
            latter acquire them, they then extract them unawares, from their bodies, so that in
            departing [from life] they encounter demons. Indeed, it is even said that God never
            desires that those who depart [life] be given over to such demons.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <p n="S2">IV,34. In the world to come, no one will escape the prison into which he will
            fall; because it is said: You will not depart from there, until what you pay the last
            penny," that is a minimum suffering.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S2">IV,35. If the gift of languages is a gift of the Spirit, and [if] the demons are
            deprived of this gift, then they do not speak in languages. But it is said that, as a
            result of study, they know the languages of men; and this is not surprising that they
            possess this through receptivity; because their sustasis is coextensive with the
            sustasis of the world. Someone has said that their languages also vary, like those of
            men. And there are those who say that there are even ancient languages among them, with
            the result that those who work against the Hebrews make use of the Hebrew language, and
            to Greeks there are those who speak in the Greek language, and so on for the rest.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p n="S2">IV,36. The intelligilble fat is the thickness which, on account of vices,
            descends upon thehegemonikon.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p n="S2">IV,37. Among animals, it is said that some draw breath from the outside, others
            from the inside, others from their surroundings, and yet others from every direction.
            And it is said that those that[draw breath] from the outside are men and all those with
            lungs; those that [draw breath from] the inside are fish and all those with large
            throats; those that breathe from their surroundings are bees [breathing] by the beating
            of their wings; and those who draw breath from every direction [are]the demons and all
            the logikoi posessing bodies of air.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p n="S2">IV,38. In the world to come, the irascible man will not be counted among the
            angels, nor will the[headship?] be confided to him. Indeed, he does not see that because
            of passion he readily loses his temper with those who are led by him, [and thus] he
            descends from vision and rejects those who are in danger. For these two things are
            foreign to the angelic order.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S2">IV,39. If in the worlds to come God shows his wealth to the logikoi, it is clear
            that He will do this in those who will be after Him who comes because before Him the
            logikoiwould not be able to receive His holy riches .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p n="S2">IV,40. The Key of the Kingdom of Heaven is the spiritual gift which partially
            reveals the intellections of the praktike and of the nature, and those of the logoi
            which concern God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p n="S2">IV,41 Before his coming the Christ showed to men an angelic body, and more
            recently He has not shown them the body He has now: rather, he has revealed [the body]
            which they should [?will]have.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <p n="S2">IV,42 The promise of the hundredfold is the contemplation of beings, and eternal
            life is the knowledge of the Blessed Trinity: This, then is eternal life; to know you,
            the only true God </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p n="S2">IV,43. If the Christ who has appeared to Jacob on the ladder designates natural
            contemplation, the appearance of the ladders provides information concerning the path of
            the praktike:but if it means the knowledge of the Unity, the ladder is the symbol of all
            worlds. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p n="S2">IV,44. The Sabbath is the rest of the reasoning soul, in which it is naturally
            made not to cross the limits of nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p n="S2">IV,45. It is not those who adore them, but rather those who sacrifice to them
            that the divine powers repel; and of this we have been clearly apprised in Judges, by
            Manoah. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p n="S2">IV,46. The four corners signify the four elements, the object which appeared
            means the dense world, and the different animals are symbols of the orders of men: and
            it is this which appeared to Peter on the roof. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p n="S2">IV,47. With those who approach obscure matters and want to write on them the
            demon of anger fights night and day, that [demon] which is accustomed to blind the
            thought and to deprive it of spiritual contemplation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p n="S2">IV,48. The intelligible turban is faith which is inflexible and not susceptible
            to fear. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p n="S2">IV,49. Among all pleasures, there is one coextensive with the sustasis of the
            nous: namely, the [pleasure] accompanying knowledge, for all will pass away in the world
            to come.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p n="S2">IV,50. There is a good love that is eternal: namely, that which true knowledge
            chooses for itself, and which is said to be inseparable from the nous.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p n="S2">IV,51. In second natural contemplation, it is said that some are leaders, and
            others ar submissive to leaders, of necessity. But, in the Unity there will not be those
            who are leaders, neither those who are submitted to leaders; but all will be gods.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p n="S2">IV,52. The intelligible blade is the knowledge of the Blessed Trinity. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p n="S2">IV,53. Knowledge diminishes and decreases among those who build the tower with
            viciousness and with false doctrines; they run aground on ignorance and confusion of
            ideas["intellections"], in the same way as those also who construct the tower. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p n="S2">IV,54. In all languages words make known names, and [so] objects are known. In
            this way the words of the Apostles offered in the Hebrew language were transformed into
            the names and the words of (other) languages; [and] because of this all peoples had
            knowledge of what was revealed. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S2">IV,55. The words [?names] of the virtues are virtues’; and he who hears the
            words but does not practice them. sees virtue [as] in [that] shadowwhich is the face of
            the soul. .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p n="S2">IV,56. The intelligible ephod is the state of the reasoning soul, in which a man
            customarily practices his virtues. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p n="S2">IV,57. The Christ has appeared as creator by the multiplication of loaves, by
            the wine of the[marital] union, and by eyes of the man born blind. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p n="S2">IV,58. God, when he created the logikoi, was not in anything; but, when he
            creates the corporal nature and worlds which arise from it, he is in his Christ.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S2">IV,59. If an essence is not said to be superior or inferior to an[other]
            essence, and that a demon has been designated by our Savior as worse that an[other]
            demon, it is evident that it is not by their essence that demons are bad. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p n="S2">IV,60. To those who blaspheme against the Creator and speak ill of this body of
            our soul: who will demonstrate the grace that they have received, [namely] while they
            are passible, to have been joined such an organon? They testify in favor of my words,
            who in hallucinations of dreams are terrified by demons and escape into wakefulness as
            [if] beside angels, when the body awakens abruptly.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p n="S2">IV,61. "Interpretation" is explanation of the commandments for the consolation
            of the simple.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p n="S2">IV,62. It is necessary for the nous to be instructed concerning incorporeal
            [beings], concerning bodies, or even simply to see objects: for there, indeed, is its
            life. But it will not see incorporeal[beings], if it be impure in its will, nor bodies,
            if it should be deprived of the organon that shows it sensible things. What, then, will
            they give to the dead soul for contemplation, those who despise the Creator and also
            malign our body here?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p n="S2">IV,63. The propitiatory is. spiritual knowledge, which conducts the soul of the
            praktikoi. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p n="S2">IV.64. If ancient Israel, of whom many were not[part] of Israel, accompanied
            him, is it also thus with the new Israel – that many among the Egyptians did not go out?
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p n="S2">IV,65. All reasoning nature is divided into three parts: over one reigns life,
            over the second (reign) death and life, and over the third (reigns) only death .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p n="S2">IV,66. The intelligible pectoral is the hidden knowledge of the mysteries of
            God. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p n="S2">IV.67. Objects which fall beneath the soul through the senses move it in order
            to make it receive their forms within it: for this is the "work" of the nous - to know,
            like the animals that breathe externally: and [the nous] falls into danger if it does
            not work, if, in the words of wise Solomon, the light of the Lord is the breath of men.
            .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p n="S2">IV,68. This body of the soul is the image of the house, and sense carries the
            sign of the windows, by which the nous regards and sees sensible things.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p n="S2">IV,69. The intelligible coat is the spiritual teaching that gathers wanderers.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <p n="S2">IV,70. it is not said to all: Flee from prison, my soul: but to those empowered
            by purity of soul, to give themselves over, apart from this body, to the contemplation
            of what has come to be.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p n="S2">IV,71. If one of the senses is missing, it deeply saddens those deprived of it:
            who [then] will be able to endure the deprivation of all, which will occur all at once
            and deprive him of the admiration for bodies?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p n="S2">IV,72. The intelligible trousers are the mortification of the concupiscible
            part, which been made for the knowledge of God. .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p n="S2">IV.73. One in whom the nous always attends to the Lord, in whom the thumikos is
            full of humility following the memory of God, and in whomepithumia is completely
            oriented toward the Lord - is it appropriate for him not to fear our adversaries who
            circle outside our bodies?.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p n="S2">IV,74. These among saints who have now been delivered of bodies and have mingled
            with the choir of angels, it is evident that the latter have come also to our world
            because of the [divine?]economy.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p n="S2">IV.75. The intelligible ephod is the soul’s justice, through which man is
            accustomed to win fame in works and in irreproachable teachings. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S2">IV,76. One who is passionate and who prays to quickly depart (the body)
            resembles the sick man who asks to the carpenter to quickly break up his bed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p n="S2">IV,77. Objects are outside of the nous, and the contemplation concerning them is
            constituted within it. But it is not thus with the holy Trinity, for it is solely
            essential knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p n="S2">IV,78. The Christ is inherited and he inherits; but the Father is only
            inherited.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S2">IV,79. The belt of the high priest is humility of the thumos, which strengthens
            the nous. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p n="S2">IV,80. It is not the Word of God who descended to Sheol and ascended to Heaven,
            but the Christ, who has the Word [with]in Him; indeed, the coarse body is not receptive
            of knowledge, and God is known.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p n="S2">IV,81. All contemplation by the sign of its intellection is immaterial and
            incorporeal; but material or immaterial, is said to be that which possesses or that does
            not possess objects which fall beneath it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p n="S2">IV,82. The refuge is the praktike body of the passible soul, which delivers it
            from the demons that surround it. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p n="S2">IV.83. He who, although impure, escapes from the body should reflect on whether
            perchance the parent of the one who was killed is not standing by the door and will not
            accuse him. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p n="S2">IV.84. Knowledge is not a quality of bodies, nor are colors qualities of the
            incorporeals; but knowledge is (a quality ) of the incorporeals, and color is
            accidentally (a quality) of bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p n="S2">IV.85. The demons prevail over the soul when the passions are multiplied, and
            they render man insensible by extinguishing the powers of his sense organs, for fear
            that by perceiving a nearby object he will make the nous ascend as from a deep well.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <p n="S2">IV,86. The nous that possesses a body does not see the incorporeals; and, when
            it will be incorporeal, it will not see the bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p n="S2">IV,87. All contemplation appears with an underlying object, except for the
            Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p n="S2">IV,88. Of the three altars of knowledge, two are circumscribed, while the third
            appears uncircumscribed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p n="S2">IV,89. Who will recount the grace of God? Who will scrutinize the logoi of
            providence and how the Christ leads the reasoning nature by [means of] varied worlds to
            the union of the Holy Unity?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p n="S2">IV,90. The knowledge of God requires not a soul[skilled in] dialectic, but one
            that sees: for while impure souls may become dialecticians, seeing is reserved to the
            pure.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="epilogue" n="">
          <p n="S2">The End of the Fourth Century</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="V">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p n="S2">V,1. Adam is the image of Christ, and that of the reasoning nature is Eve, on
            account of whom the Christ has left his Paradise.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p n="S2">V,2. The hearers of the sensible Church are separated from one another only by
            by [their]place[s]; but in the intelligible [Church], those who are opposed to one
            another [are separated] by [their]place and [their] bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p n="S2">V,3. Just as those who reside in this world catch a very small glimpse of the
            world to come, so those who are in the last world see something of the luminous rays of
            the Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p n="S2">V,4. An archangel is the reasoning essence to whom has been confided the logoi
            concerning providence and judgement and those of the worlds of angels.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p n="S2">V,5. Two among the worlds purify the passible part of the soul, one of them by
            praktike, and the other by cruel torment.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p n="S2">V,6. The contemplation of angels is named [the]celestial Jerusalem and the
            mountain of Zion: now if those who have believed in Christ have approached the mountain
            of Zion and the city of the living God, it is therefore in the contemplation of angels
            which have been and will be[come] those who have believed in Christ, that from which
            their fathers have come up from and gone down into Egypt.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p n="S2">V,7. An angel is the reasoning essence to whom have been confided the logoi that
            concern providence and judgement and those of the worlds of men.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p n="S2">V,8. Those who have cultivated their earth during the six years of praktike,
            these will feed orphans and widows not in the eighth year but in the seventh; for in the
            eighth year there are no orphans and widows.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p n="S2">V,9. Among men, some will feast with the angels, others will mingle with the
            brood of demons, and others will be tormented with impure men.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p n="S2">V,10. "The first-born" are reasoning natures that, in each of the worlds,
            approach the higher transformation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p n="S2">V,11. From the order of angels come the order of archangels and that of
            psychics; from that of psychics (will come that) of demons and of men; and from that of
            men will come anew that of angels and demons, if a demon is that which, because of an
            abundance of thumos, has fallen the praktike and has been joined to a darkened and
            extensive body.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p n="S2">V,12 The nous that is divested of the passions and sees the logoi of beings does
            not henceforth truly receive the eidola that (arrive) through the senses; but it is as
            if another world is created by its knowledge, attracting to it its thought and rejecting
            far from it the sensitive world.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p n="S2">V,13. The intelligible cloud is the reasoning nature which has been entrusted by
            God to give drink to those who sleep far from it. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p n="S2">V,14. Just as when the sun rises things which are elevated a little from the
            ground cast a shadow, so also to the nous which begins to approach the logoi of beings,
            objects appear obscurely.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p n="S2">V,15. The nous that is divested of the passions becomes completely like light,
            because it is illuminated by the contemplation of beings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p n="S2">V,16. The intelligible (large or storm-) cloud is spiritual contemplation which
            contains within it the logoi of providence and the judgement of those who are on
            earth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p n="S2">V,17. Just as waves when they rise cast a shadow, and then immediately appear
            again without shadow, so when the logoi of beings flee from the pure nous,they will
            immediately be known again.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p n="S2">V,18. Demons only imitate colors, forms and size, but the holy powers also know
            how to transform the nature of the body by disposing it for services that are necessary.
            And that happens among the composite [natures]; but of the incorporeal nature there are
            no such logoi, as someone has said.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p n="S2">V,19. The resurrection of the body is the passage from the bad quality to the
            superior quality.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p n="S2">V,20. The life vivifies first the living, then those who live and those who are
            dead; but at the end it will vivify also the dead.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p n="S2">V,21. IT is not in all worlds that you will find Egypt; but in the others you
            will see Jerusalem and the mountain of Sion.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p n="S2">V,22. The resurrection of soul is the return from order of passibility has the
            impassible state.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p n="S2">V,23. The multiform movement and the various passions of the reasoning beings
            (logikoi) have forced the logoi that concern providence to appear obscurely; and their
            various orders have rendered hidden the logoi that concern judgement.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p n="S2">V,24. The logoi which concern judgment are secondary, as has been said, in
            relation to the logoithat concern the movement and providence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p n="S2">V,25. The resurrection of the nous is the passage from ignorance to true
            knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p n="S2">V,26. just as it is not the same thing for us to see the light as to speak of
            the light, even so, to see God is not the same thing as to understand something
            concerning God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p n="S2">V,27. Thumos, when it is disturbed, blinds the one who sees, and epithumia, when
            it is moved irrationally, hides visible objects.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p n="S2">V,28. The intelligible sword is the spiritual saying that separates the body
            from the soul, or the vice and the ignorance.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p n="S2">V,29. Just as those who come into cities to see their beauty are amazed by
            looking at each work, so also the nous, when it approaches the logoi of beings, will be
            filled with spiritual desire and will not withdraw from admiration.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p n="S2">V,30. If the kingdom of heaven is the contemplation of beings, and if the
            former, according to the saying of Our Lord, is within us, and if our inner[self] is
            occupied by demons, it is therefore quite rightly said that it is said that Philistines
            occupy the Promised Land. .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p n="S2">V,31. The intelligible shield is practical knowledge that guards unharmed the
            passible part of the soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p n="S2">V,32. What is contained in the first cup resembles wine, that is the knowldge of
            incorporeal [beings]; and what (is contained) in the second bears the sign of water, I
            mean the contemplation of bodies. And it is there that the cup of these two has been
            mixed for us by Wisdom.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <p n="S2">V,33. The iniquitous treasurer {steward} cannot till the earth because he has
            forsaken the virtues of his soul; and the wretch, on the other hand, is ashamed to beg -
            he who is the teacher of others. And he teaches with anger these who are henceforth
            below him; he who has withdrawn{into his hermitage(?) condemned}now to remain among the
            quarrelsome.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <p n="S2">V,34. The intelligible helmet is spiritual knowledge that guards unharmed the
            intelligent part of the soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S2">V,35. If the bread of the reasoning nature is the contemplation of beings, and
            if we have received the order to eat the former by the sweat of our brow, it is evident
            that it is by the praktike that we ate the former.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p n="S2">V,36. Those who have inherited the Promised Land will slay with all their might
            the Philistines who are there, for fear that, when Joshua becomes old among them, he
            will not cease going out with their force, and so they not again become slaves of the
            Philistines.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p n="S2">V,37. The intelligible [fish-]hook is the spiritual teaching that draws the soul
            from the depth of vice towards virtue.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p n="S2">V,38. He who fights for apatheia will arm himself with the commandments, and he
            who (fights) for the truth will exterminate his enemies with knowledge. The defeat of
            the first occurs when he does what the law forbids and [defeat] of the second when he
            takes the lead in false teachings and opinions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S2">V,39. In pure thoughts [there] is imprinted a splendid sky to see and a spacious
            region where it appears how the logoi of beings and of the holy angels approach those
            who are worthy. And this vision that is imprinted - irritation causes it to be seen
            [only]obscurely, and anger when it flames up destroys it completely.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p n="S2">V,40. The intelligible mountain is spiritual contemplation placed at a great
            height which it is difficult to approach: when the nous has attained it, it will become
            a seer of all the objects lying below.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p n="S2">V,41. One in whose soul the intelligible world is completely imprinted abstains
            from all corruptible desire, and is henceforth ashamed of what formerly gave him
            pleasure, his logismoi reproaching him for his former insensitivity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <p n="S2">V,42. The world created in the mind seems difficult to see by day, the nous
            being distracted by the senses and by the sensible light that shines; but at night it
            can be seen, luminously imprinted at the time of prayer</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p n="S2">V,43. The intelligible path is the state of the reasoning soul, on which the
            nous as it advances will encounter objects and will understand their logoi.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p n="S2">V,44. If the anger of dragons is their wine and if the Nazarenes in accordance
            with the law abstain from wine, the law has therefore ordained that the Nazarines are to
            be without anger.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p n="S2">V,45. The nous is named head of the the soul, and virtues are signified by the
            word hair; when he will be deprived of it, the Nazarene will be separated from gnowledge
            and will be taken bound by his enemies .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p n="S2">V,46. The high priest is He who addresses supplications to God for all reasoning
            nature and separates some from evil, and others from ignorance.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p n="S2">V,47. We honor angels non because of their nature, but on account of their
            virtue; and we insult demons on account of the vice that is in them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p n="S2">V,48. Alone of all bodies, the Christ is adorable by us because he alone has
            within him the Word of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p n="S2">V,49. The new God is he who cannot make anything to exist, or he who is united
            to evil.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p n="S2">V,50. Only the Blessed Trinity is adorable in itself, by which, finally, the
            incorporeal and the corporeal nature in the beginning became something out of
            nothing.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p n="S2">V,51. One who sees the Creator according to the harmony of beings - it is not
            [God’s] nature that he knows, rather he knows His wisdom by which He has made
            everything: and I do not mean the essential wisdom, but that which appears in beings,
            that which is called natural contemplation by those who are expert in these things. And
            if this is so, what is the madness of those who say they know the nature of God!</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p n="S2">V,52. a pure nous has need of the logoi of bodies, a purer (nous) [needs] the
            logoi of incorporeals, and a (nous) purer than the latter [needs] the Blessed
            Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p n="S2">V,53. The spiritual sacrifice is the pure conscience that puts on the state of
            the nous as on an altar.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p n="S2">V,54. Just as it is more difficult for us to see thelogoi of the incorporeals
            that [to perceive] through the senses objects which approach us, so it is more difficult
            for us to know the logoi of bodies that to see the bodies themselves.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S2">V,55. The Blessed Trinity is not a thing that would be entangled into
            contemplation; Indeed, that occurs only to created beings. Thus one will call it holy
            essential knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p n="S2">V.56. One who is separated from objects, has not[necessarily] also fallen
            completely from the contemplation that concerns them; nor is one who lost contemplation,
            [necessarily] outside of objects. But it is not the same concerning the Blessed Trinity;
            indeed, we that it is solely essential knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p n="S2">V,57. Just as we now approach sensible objects through the senses, and
            eventually when we are purified we will also know their logoi; so we first see objects,
            and when we are further purified, we will also see the contemplation concerning them,
            after which it is possible henceforth to also know the Blessed Trinity</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p n="S2">V,58. The nous discerns sensations not as sensible, but as sensation; and
            sensation discerns sensible things not as objects but as sensible objects.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S2">V.59. Sensation does not discern sensation; rather it discerns only the
            sense-organs, not as sense-organs, but as sensible [objects]. The nous discerns
            sensation as sensation and the organs of sense as organs of sense.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p n="S2">V,60. The power of the nous that sees spiritual natures is one thing; that
            (power) which knows the contemplations which concern them is another. But(only) one is
            the power which knows and understands Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p n="S2">V.61. Whenever we consider material [things], we come to the memory of their
            contemplations; and when we receive their contemplation we again distance ourselves from
            material [things]. But this is not what happens in regard to the Blessed Trinity;
            because it is solely essential contemplation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p n="S2">V.62. The nature of the Trinity is not known through ascents or descents.
            Indeed, [since] there are no subjacent objects, its nature does not admit analysis: for
            elucidating the nature of bodies would finally make [that nature] consist of matter and
            form; and in elucidating the incorporeal natures, one would return it to natural (?
            common) contemplation and to those substance susceptible of opposition. But it is not
            possible to know the nature of the Blessedtrinity by this means.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p n="S2">V.63. Investigation brings us back to the beginning of objects, and
            properly-measured knowledge renders visible the wisdom of the Creator; but it is not
            [by] following these signs that we see the Blessed Trinity. For it is without beginning,
            nor do we say that the wisdom in these objects is God, if these beginnings accord in the
            contemplation of nature with things of which they are the beginnings. Indeed, such a
            wisdom is knowledge without substance, which appears only in objects.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p n="S2">V,64. Just as a mirror remains unstained by images that are observed there, so
            the impassible soul (remains without being stained) by things that are on earth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p n="S2">V,65. The praktikos is the servant of separation, and the gnostikos the
            assistant of wisdom.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p n="S2">V,66. the nous is not united to knowledge until it has united the passible part
            of its soul to its proper virtues.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p n="S2">V,67. If reasoning natures bear the sign of trees and if the latter grow in
            water, it is rightly said that knowledge is called the spiritual water which flows from
            the source of life. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p n="S2">V,68. The intelligible Philistine is he who is opposed to those who enter
            through inheritance into the Promised Land.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p n="S2">V,69. The Blessed Trinity is the sign of the blessed water, and the Tree of Life
            is the Christ who drinks there.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <p n="S2">V.70. Just as our body is said to be in a place, thenous is also (said to be) in
            a kind of knowledge; for this reason knowledge is accurately termed the place[of the
            nous’].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p n="S2">V,71. The intelligible hero is he who strives to go out with those who have
            entered the Promised Land..</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p n="S2">V.72. If the four sources came from only one river, one should say, "the world
            where there was only one river", so that the body also discerns the Paradise from which
            it will drink.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p n="S2">V.73. The nous marvels, when it sees objects, and it is not disturbed in
            contemplating them; instead it runs as if towards its family and friends.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p n="S2">V,74. The intelligible city is the spiritual contemplation which contains the
            spiritual natures.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p n="S2">V.75. The more the nous divests itself of the passions, the more it approaches
            objects; and, according to the level of its rank, it also receives knowledge. And [in]
            all the ranks in which it will stand it will know the contemplation proper [to that
            rank].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S2">V,76. Knowing Natures examine objects, and the knowledge of objects purifies the
            Knowers.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p n="S2">V,77. The intelligible gates are the virtues of the reasoning soul and praktike
            which have been constituted by the power of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p n="S2">V,78 Bodies of demons neither grow nor diminish and a strong stench accompanies
            them, by which they also put our passions into motion; and they are easily known by
            those who have received from the Lord the power to perceive this odor.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S2">V.79. Everything that falls under the nous’power to see the incorporeals is
            completely within its nature. But as for those who have seen by means of the other
            (power) that cannot be connatural to [thenous], if it is the same power that knows
            [both] the intellection of the incorporeals and the Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p n="S2">V,80. The intelligible deadbolt (or bar) is the free mastery of itself, which
            does not weaken because of goodness.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p n="S2">V,81. When the nous will have received essential knowledge, then it will also be
            called "God" , because it will also be able to found varied worlds.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p n="S2">V,82. The intelligible wall is apatheia of the soul, which the demons do not
            approach.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p n="S2">V,83. We have found that all the circumcisions are seven: four of them are of
            the sixth day, one of them of the seventh day, and the others of the eighth day.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p n="S2">V,84. The intelligible temple is the pure nous, which keeps [safe] within it the
            full manifold wisdom of God ; the temple of God is he who is a seer of the blessed
            Unity, and the altar of God is the contemplation of the Blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p n="S2">V,85. The first nature is for the One, the second towards the One, and the same
            in the One.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <p n="S2">V,86. The solitary who loves vainglory is he who, before apatheia, seeks to be
            glorified by men in things that are not made for the apatheia and the knowledge of
            God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p n="S2">V,87. The knowledge of seconds is in the first, and that of the first in it; but
            the second is not known.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p n="S2">V,88. Zion is the sign of the first knowledge, and Egypt the token of all vice;
            but the symbol of natural contemplation is Jerusalem, or it is the mountain of Zion,
            summit of the city.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p n="S2">V,89. Just as the destruction of the last world will not be accompanied by a
            creation, so the creation of the first world is not preceded by a destruction.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p n="S2">V,90. Objects such as they naturally are - either the pure nous sees [them], or
            the spiritual saying of the wise makes them know. But one who is deprived of these two
            proceeds to indict the writer. 1.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="epilogue" n="">
          <p n="S2">The End of the Fifth [Century]</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="VI">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p n="S2">VI,1. What the contemplation of beings is, the Holy Bible has not made known;
            but how it may be approached by the practice of commandments and by true doctrines, it
            has taught in an obvious fashion.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p n="S2">VI,2. Twofold is the contemplation of this world: the one obvious and dense, the
            other spiritual and intelligible. The first contemplation [can be]approached by the
            impious and demons; and the second by the just and the angels of God. And just as the
            angels comprehend spiritual contemplation more than the just, similarly more than the
            impious do the demons comprehend the dense contemplation - which it is thought they also
            provide to some of those who belong to them; and we, we have learned from the Holy Bible
            that the holy angels also practice this.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p n="S2">VI,3. The sensible nations are distinguished from one another by places, by
            laws, by languages, by clothes and sometimes also by qualities. The intelligible and
            holy (nations) (are distinguished) by worlds, by bodies, by knowledges and, it is said,
            also by languages. The father of first is Adam, and that of the second is the Christ, of
            whom Adam is (the representation).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p n="S2">VI,4. The Father is considered before the Son as Father, before the Holy Spirit
            as Principle, and He is anterior to the incorporeals and to the corporeals as
            Creator.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p n="S2">VI,5. The Uncreated is one before whom, because he is [such] by his essence,
            there is nothing which is prior.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p n="S2">VI,6. Just as the knife circumcizes the sensible Jew, in the same way the
            praktiké (circumcizes) the intelligible (Jew), he whom Christ has symbolically named the
            sword he has hurled into the world. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p n="S2">VI,7. If the eighth day is the symbol of the resurrection, and Christ is the
            resurrection, those therefore who are circumcized on the eighth day are circumcized in
            Christ.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p n="S2">VI,8. Just as Paradise is the {academy?} of the just, so also Sheol is capable
            of being the torment of the impious.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p n="S2">VI,9. If time is considered with generation and destruction, the generation of
            the incorporeals is therefore timeless, because there is no destruction prior to this
            generation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p n="S2">VI,10. The Blessed Trinity is not like a tetrad, a pentad, or a hexad; indeed,
            these "numericals" are forms without substance; but the Blessed Trinity is essential
            knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p n="S2">VI,11. The numerical triad is accompanied by a tetrad, but the Blessed Trinity
            is not accompanied by a tetrad; it is not therefore a numerical triad.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p n="S2">VI,12. The numerical triad is preceded by a numerical diad, but the Blessed
            Trinity is not preceded by a numerical diad; indeed, it is not a numerica; triad.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p n="S2">VI,13. The numerical triad is constituted by addition of units without
            substance; but it is not by addition of such units that the Blessed Trinity is
            constituted; it is not therefore a triad that is [constituted] with numbers.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p n="S2">VI,14. The Christ is not connatural with the Trinity. Indeed, he is also not
            essential knowledge; but he alone always has essential knowledge inseperably[with]in
            him. But Christ - I mean to say he who has come with the Word- God and in spirit is the
            Lord - is inseparable from his body; and by th[at] union he is connatural with his
            Father, because he is also essential knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p n="S2">VI,15. The feet of Christ are praktike and contemplation; and if he puts all his
            enemies beneath his feet, all therefore will know praktike and contemplation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p n="S2">VI,16. Christ is he who, proceeding from essential knowledge and from
            incorporeal and corporeal nature has appeared to us: and [any]one who says "two Christs"
            or "two Sons" resembles someone who calls the sage and his wisdom two sages or two
            wisdoms.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p n="S2">VI,17. A holy power is that which has been constituted by the contemplation of
            beings and by incorporeal nature and corporeal (nature).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p n="S2">VI,18. There was a time when Christ had no body; but there there was never [a
            time] when the Word of God was not in him. For it is with his genesis, , that the Word
            of God has also resided in him..</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p n="S2">VI,19. Conversion is the ascent away from (the)movement and away from vice and
            ignorance towards knowledge of the Blessed Trinity. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p n="S2">VI,20. Before the movement, God was good, powerful, sage, creator of the
            incorporeals, father of the logikoi and omnipotent; after the movement, he has become
            creator of bodies, judge, governor, physician, shephers, doctor, merciful and
            forbearing, and again door, way, lamb, high priest, with the other names that are spoken
            by modes. And he is Father and Principle even before the creation of the incorporeals:
            Father of the Christ, and Principle of the holy Spirit.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p n="S2">VI,21. Virtue is that state of the reasoning soul in which it is difficult to
            move it towards evil.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p n="S2">VI,22. If sensible words can make known even objects in the world to come, it is
            evident that sages of this world will also receive the kingdom of Heaven. But if it is
            the purity of the nous [sic, = "consciousness"] that sees and the appropriate word from
            it that makes [it]know, the sages of this world will be kept far from the knowledge of
            God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p n="S2">VI,23. Just as this saying here informs concerning objects in this world, so the
            saying of the spiritual body will make known objects of the world to come.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p n="S2">VI,24. If those, who in the world to come will be angels, also rule over five or
            on ten cities; it is evident that they will also receive the knowledge that can impel
            reasoning souls from vice to virtue, and from ignorance to the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p n="S2">VI,25. When demons are unable to move[tempting-]thoughts against the gnostikos,
            then they close his eyes by means a of severe cold and lead him into a heavy sleep;
            because the the bodies of demons are very cold, similar to ice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p n="S2">VI,26. Just as it is not fire itself that is in our bodies, but it its quality
            that has been put in them, so also in the bodies of demons it is not earth itself nor
            water itself, but their qualities that the Creator has sown there.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p n="S2">VI,27. If all the nations will come and prostrate before the Lord , it is
            evident that even the nations that want war will come. And if this is so, then all the
            natures of the logikoi will prostrate before the name the Lord Who will make known the
            Father Who is in Him. Indeed, that is the Name higher than every other name. .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p n="S2">VI,28. The Father is the [pro]genitor of essential knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p n="S2">VI,29. The Father is he who has a reasoning nature that is united to the
            knowledge of the Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p n="S2">VI,30. The Father is he who has a reasoning nature that is united to the
            contemplation of beings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p n="S2">VI,31. Begotten is one who has been begotten by someone, as by a father 1</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p n="S2">VI,32. [But] engendered is one who has been engendered by someone (as by a
            creator).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <p n="S2">VI,33. When the Christ will no longer be imprinted in the varied worlds and in
            names of all kinds, then he also will be submitted to God the Father and will delight in
            the knowledge of him alone, which is not divided in worlds and in increases of the
            logikoi.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <p n="S2">VI,34. In the worlds God will change the body of our humiliation into the
            resemblance of the glorious body of the Lord; and after all the worlds he will also
            bring us to the resemblance of the image of his Son , if the image of the Son is
            essential knowledge of God the Father.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S2">VI,35. By the intellections of the commandments holy angels purify us from evil
            and render us impassible; by those of nature and by the divine logoi, they liberate us
            from ignorance and make us wise and Knowers.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p n="S2">VI,36. He who was created to be the plaything (orlaughing-stock) of the angels
            of God, would [?this]not be he who was the initiator of the movement; and at the
            beginning has transgressed the borders of wickedness, and because of that has been
            called the. beginning of the Lord’s creatures ?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p n="S2">VI,37. Just as cranes fly in form of letters although they do not know letters,
            so also the demons recite sayings concerning the fear of God, although they do not know
            the fear of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p n="S2">VI,38. The intelligible cross is voluntary mortification of the body, which
            perfects the chastity of Christ.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S2">VI,39. The genesis of Christ is the regeneration of our interior man , which the
            Christ, like a good builder, has founded on the principal stone of the structure of his
            body in building it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p n="S2">VI,40. The crucifixion of Christ is the mortification of our old man, the
            canceling out of the sentence levelled against us and the remission makes us return to
            life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p n="S2">VI,41. The complete withdrawal softens the concupiscible portion of the soul and
            renders hard thethmikon (irascible).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <p n="S2">VI,42. The death of Christ is the mysterious operation that restores to eternal
            life those who have hoped in him in this life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p n="S2">VI,43. The providence of God accompanies free will; but his judgment considers
            the order of the logikoi.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p n="S2">VI,44. The spiritual demonstration is the carrying out of things that have been
            predicted in a divine manner by the Holy Spirit.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p n="S2">VI,45. Not one of the [subsequent] worlds has been superior to the first world;
            indeed, it is said that the former was made from the principal quality: and a[spiritual]
            athlete has apprised us that in [the first world] will be accomplished all worlds, and
            Knower.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p n="S2">VI,46. The kithara is the praktike soul moved by the commandments of Christ.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p n="S2">VI,47. The judgment of God will cause to enter into the Promised Land whoever
            will have followed Joshua, by giving to him a spiritual body and an appropriate world;
            but those who, because of the abundance of their goods will not have been able to obtain
            it, he will install on the shore of the Jordan according to their rank.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p n="S2">VI,48. The harp is the pure nous which is moved by spiritual knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p n="S2">VI,49. Egypt signifies vice, the desert the praktikethe land of Juda the
            contemplation of bodies,Jerusalem [contemplation] of the incorporeal, andZion is the
            symbol of the Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p n="S2">VI,50. Everything that is a part of this world belongs to corporeal nature; and
            everything that belongs to corporal nature is a part of this world.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p n="S2">VI,51. Since of all powers of the soul the reasoning part is the most honorable
            because it alone acts with[?is united to?] wisdom - the first of all virtues being
            wisdom; our wise master has also called it the spirit of filial adoption. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p n="S2">VI,52. Many passions are hidden in our souls which, when they escape our notice,
            temptations sharply reveal to us. And it is necessary to guard the heart with all
            vigilance , so that, when some matter occurs which induces a passion [within us], we are
            not suddenly snatched up by demons to perform something forbidden by God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p n="S2">VI,53. The intelligible arrow is the evil logismos, which is constituted by the
            passible part of the soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p n="S2">VI,54. If the nous discerns words and if the names and the words make objects
            known, the noustherefore discerns objects.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S2">VI,55. It is when the nous approaches the intelligible that it is no longer
            united to the logismos that comes from the passible part of the soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p n="S2">VI.56. If vision is said [ to consist] in sensation and in thought, and if
            Christ comes in the same way the disciples saw him ascend to heaven (Acts 1:11, how can
            it be said that they saw him? Rather, it is known that at all times Christ truly ascends
            in the holy, while he passes in descending towards the others.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p n="S2">VI,57. The recompense which reasoning nature will receive before the tribunal of
            Christ - these are spiritual or dark bodies, and the contemplation or ignorance
            appropriate to them: and for this reason it is said that the Christ whom we await comes
            for some as this and for others as that.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p n="S2">VI,58. Of those bodies that have been stable in the series of changes it is said
            that that they will depart spiritual bodies. But whether that will happen at the end (by
            separation?) from matter or from organa which will have come to be - you, too, [should]
            examine [this].</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S2">VI,59. Twofold is the providence of God: one part, it is said, cares for the
            sustasis of bodies and incorporeal [beings]; and the other urges the logikoiaway from
            vice and ignorance towards virtue and knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p n="S2">VI,60. Sterile is the nous which is deprived of spiritual doctrine, or which
            lacks seeds sown by the Holy Spirit.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p n="S2">VI,61. If God is the God of the living and not of dead, and if, according to the
            saying of holy Moses, the mediums question the dead , it is not Samuel that the medium
            caused to come up from the dead; for he is not dead but alive.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p n="S2">VI,62. Sterile is the reasoning soul that is always learning and is never able
            to attain to true knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p n="S2">VI,63. Just as those whose vision is unhealthy and who look the sun are trouble
            by their tears and see phantasms in the air, so also the pure nous, when it has been
            disturbed by anger, cannot receive spiritual contemplation; but it sees a kind of fog
            that rests on objects.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p n="S2">VI,64. Just as by the sensible healing of the paralytic our Savior has
            enlightened us concerning intelligible healing and by that which is manifest has
            confirmed what is hidden, so by the sensible exodus of the sons of Israel he has shown
            us the exodus out of vice and ignorance.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p n="S2">VI,65. The mystery is the spiritual contemplation that is not accessible to
            everyone.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p n="S2">VI,66. The knife of stone is the teaching of Christ our Savior, which
            circumcized with knowledge the nous that is covered by the passions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p n="S2">VI,67. More worlds will increase, also more names and logoi which are
            appropriate for them will make us know the blessed Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p n="S2">VI,68. "Submission" is the consent of the will of the reasoning nature with a
            view to the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p n="S2">VI,69. Angels see men and demons; men are deprived of seeing angels and demons,
            and demons see only men.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <p n="S2">VI,70. "Submission" is that weakness of the reasoning nature that cannot cross
            the limits of its rank; thus indeed, he has put all [things] under his feet, according
            to the saying of Paul .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p n="S2">VI,71. Just as to the sensible Israel are opposed sensible nations, in the same
            way to the intelligible Israel are opposed intelligible nations.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p n="S2">VI,72. The logos of matter is one thing; the [logos] of the quality that can
            make it known is another; [still]another is that [logos] of their internal part close to
            elements, another is that of the sensible elements, another is the contemplation of the
            body; [and]another is that of the human organon .</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p n="S2">VI,73. It is not because the nous is incorporeal that it bears the likeness of
            God, but because it has been made receptive of Him. And if it is because it is
            incorporeal that it bears the likeness of God, it is therefore essential knowledge; and
            it is not by receptivity that it has been made [in] the image of God. But examine
            whether this is the same thing, the fact that it is incorporeal and the fact that it is
            able to receive knowledge, or quite otherwise, like a statue and its bronze.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p n="S2">VI,74. The Christ will come before the judgement to judge the living and the
            dead, and he will be known after the judgement, if the Lord is known by the judgement he
            renders.;</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p n="S2">VI,75. The first knowledge that is in the logikoi is that of the BlessedTrinity;
            then there took place the movement of freedom, the beneficial providence and the
            non-abandonment, and then the judgement, and again the movement of freedom, providence,
            the judgment, and that up to the Blessed Trinity. Thus a judgment is interposed between
            the movement of freedom and the providence of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S2">VI,76. If "He who has ascended above all the heavens" has "accomplished
            everything" , it is evident that each of the ranks of celestial powers has truly learned
            the logoi concerning providence, by which they rapidly impel towards virtue and the
            knowledge of God those who are beneath them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p n="S2">VI,77. Did Gabriel announce to Mary the departure of Christ from the Father, or
            his arrival from the world of angels into the world of men? Investigate, too, this
            subject: did the disciples who lived with him in his corporeal state comewith him from
            the world that is seen by us, or from another world or worlds; and is this so for some
            of them, or for all? And investigate yet again whether it is because of the psychic
            state they had achieved that they attained to become disciples of the Christ.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p n="S2">VI,78. Equivalent in body is one who is is equal in quality.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S2">VI,79. The body of the Christ is connatural with our body, and his soul is of
            the nature of our souls; but the Word which is in him essentially is coessential with
            the Father.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p n="S2">VI,80. equivalent to the reasoning substance is he who is equal in
            knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p n="S2">VI,81. Just as it is not possible for a reasoning nature to be with the body
            apart from the world, so it is not possible for it, apart from the body, to be in the
            world.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p n="S2">VI,82. It is said that God is in corporeal nature like the architect in the
            things that have been made by him; and, like one, it is said who is as [if] in the
            statue, if he happened to have made a wooden statue.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p n="S2">VI,83. It is said that the nous ssees things that it knows and that it does not
            see things that it does not know; and because of this it is not all thoughts that the
            knowledge of God forbids it, but those which assail it from thumos and epithumia and
            those which are against nature</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p n="S2">VI,84. The choleric part of the soul is joined with the heart, where its
            intelligence also is; and its concupiscible part is joined with the flesh and blood, if
            it is necessary us to distance the heart from anger and the flesh from vice. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p n="S2">VI,85. If all powers that we and the beasts have in common belong to corporeal
            nature, it is therefore evident that thumos and epithumia do not seem to have been
            created with the reasoning nature before the movement.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <p n="S2">VI,86. Holy angels instruct some men through the word; they bring others back by
            means of dreams; they render still others chaste by nocturnal terrors, and they make
            others return to virtue though blows.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p n="S2">VI,87. The nous, according to the saying of Solomon, is joined to the heart; and
            the light which appears to it passes by coming from the sensible head.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p n="S2">VI,88. It is not the holy angels only who work with us for our salvation, but
            also the stars themselves; if in the days of Baraq they shot from heaven in the war with
            Sisara. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p n="S2">VI,89. Just as in this world Our Lord has been first-born from the dead, in the
            same way in the world to come he will be first-born of many brothers.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p n="S2">VI,90. Whoever will have obtained spiritual knowledge will help the holy angels
            and will return reasoning souls from vice to virtue and from ignorance to knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="epilogue" n="">
          <p n="S2">Scrutinize our words, O our brothers, and explicate with zeal these centuries,
            according to the number of the six days of creation.</p>
          <p n="S2">The End of the Six Centuries of the Blessed Evagrius</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
