<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../TAN-1-dev/schemas/TAN-TEI.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../TAN-1-dev/schemas/TAN-TEI.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://textalign.net/release/1/dev/schemas/TAN-TEI.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="http://textalign.net/release/1/dev/schemas/TAN-TEI.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<TEI TAN-version="1"
  id="tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:Evagrius_Kephalaia_Gnostika_eng_Dysinger_S1.TAN-TEI.001"
  xmlns:tan="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ἑξακόσια προγνωστικὰ προβλήματα</title>
        <author>Evagrius Ponticus</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>translated by</resp>
          <persName><forename>Luke</forename>
            <surname>Dysinger</surname>, O.S.B.</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <biblStruct type="website">
            <monogr>
              <title>St. Evagrius Ponticus (345-399)</title>
              <author>
                <name>Evagrius Ponticus</name>
              </author>
              <editor>Fr. <forename>Luke</forename>
                <surname>Dysinger</surname>, O.S.B. </editor>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>Valyermo, California</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Fr. Luke Dysinger, O.S.B.</publisher>
                <date>1990</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Assembled 2011-2012 by <persName>Joel Kalvesmaki</persName>, based on public-domain
          material found on the website of the translator.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Unnecessary spacing and reduplication silently corrected.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Transcription does not reflect the translator's original orthography (small caps not
            reflected); color; italics; indentation. It also does not distinguish author's
            metanarrative from the translation.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <list>
        <item>
          <date when="2012-05-12">12 May 2012</date> Updated by Joel Kalvesmaki</item>
      </list>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <head xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns">
    <name xml:lang="eng">Dysinger's translation of the Kephalaia Gnostika, Syriac S2</name>
    <master-location>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Arithmeticus/TAN-Evagrius/master/cpg2432.eng.dysinger-s1.xml</master-location>
    <rights-excluding-sources rights-holder="kalvesmaki">
      <IRI>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en_US</IRI>
      <name>Exclusive of rights held and licenses offered by rightsholders of the source or sources
        listed below, this data file, insofar as it constitutes an independent work, is licensed
        under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</name>
    </rights-excluding-sources>
    <source>
      <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:external_Evagrius_Kephalaia_Gnostika_eng_Dysinger_S2</IRI>
      <name>Dysinger's online translation</name>
      <location when-accessed="2013-04-13"
        >http://www.ldysinger.com/Evagrius/02_Gno-Keph/00a_start.htm</location>
    </source>
    <declarations>
      <work>
        <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2015:cpg2432</IRI>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:cpg2432</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">The Kephalaia Gnostika, written by Evagrius Ponticus</name>
      </work>
      <version>
        <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2015:cpg2432,S2-eng-Dysinger</IRI>
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:cpg2432#S2-eng-Dysinger</IRI>
        <name>Dysinger's English translation of S2</name>
      </version>
      <div-type xml:id="title">
        <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Title_(publishing)</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">title</name>
      </div-type>
      <div-type xml:id="century">
        <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:div-type-century</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">century</name>
      </div-type>
      <div-type xml:id="chapter">
        <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Chapter_(books)</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">chapter</name>
        <name xml:lang="grc">κεφάλαιον</name>
      </div-type>
      <div-type xml:id="epilogue">
        <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Epilogue</IRI>
        <name xml:lang="eng">epilogue</name>
      </div-type>
      <recommended-tokenization which="general-1"/>
      <recommended-div-type-refs>implicit</recommended-div-type-refs>
      <filter>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-small-caps-off</IRI>
          <name>Small caps removed.</name>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-color-off</IRI>
          <name>Color removed.</name>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-italics-off</IRI>
          <name>Italics removed.</name>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-xrefs-off</IRI>
          <name>Translator's references to other primary sources removed.</name>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:normalization-comments-off</IRI>
          <name>Translator's comments removed.</name>
        </normalization>
      </filter>
    </declarations>
    <agent xml:id="kalvesmaki" roles="editor">
      <IRI>http://viaf.org/viaf/299582703</IRI>
      <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:self</IRI>
      <name xml:lang="eng">Joel Kalvesmaki</name>
    </agent>
    <role xml:id="editor">
      <IRI>http://schema.org/editor</IRI>
      <name xml:lang="eng">Editor</name>
    </role>
    <change when="2014-10-30" who="kalvesmaki">Started TAN-TEI file.</change>
    <comment when="2014-10-30" who="kalvesmaki">From the source: Translation by Luke Dysinger,
      O.S.B. (translation in public domain) Note that the the majority of the Greek text below is
      Frankenberg’s retroversion from the [UNRELIABLE!] Syriac S1 MS. This text, should be used with
      extreme caution: it is NOT the basis for this English translation, which relies principally
      on: [1] Guillaumont’s Syriac S2 version, [2] his French translation of S2, and [3] assorted
      Greek fragments.[1] [1] The complete text of Evagrius’ Kephalaia Gnostica survives only in
      Syriac and Armenian translations with extant Greek fragments and parallels available for only
      about one-sixth of the complete text. The majority of these fragments are reproduced in the
      Greek text above, BUT the Greek text above largely consists of a retroversion into Greek of
      Frankenberg’s 1912 edition of the UNRELIABLE Syriac text (which includes a commentary by the
      seventh-century anti-Origenist abbot, Babai the Great). Guillaumont designated this the S1
      version of the Kephalaia Gnostica: it contains no evidence of the controversial Origenist
      doctrine condemned by councils from the sixth century onwards. The problematic nature of this
      S1 version was clarified in 1958, when Antoine Guillaumont published the critical edition of a
      new Syriac version based on a manuscript tradition he designated S2. This version exists in
      only a single manuscript. Although known in antiquity, it had been denounced by ancient Syriac
      authors as the work of heretical forgers who were alleged to have intentionally altered texts
      by ‘the blessed abbot Evagrius’ in order to justify their own teachings. The surviving Greek
      fragments of the Kephalaia Gnostica uniformly attest to the priority of the S2 version,
      revealing the more widespread S1 tradition to be a drastic re-editing of Evagrius’ text ,in
      which all passages suggestive of controversial Origenist doctrine had either been eliminated
      or modified. This (expurgated) S1 version appeared very quickly, possibly anticipating by
      several decades the anathemas of 543 and 553. The Syriac manuscript evidence places it no
      later than the first third of the sixth century; and an Armenian translation of S1 may have
      been made sometime in the fifth century, that is within a century of Evagrius’ death in 399.
      The existence of both expurgated and unexpurgated versions of Evagrius’ works during the sixth
      century reflects an uneasy attitude of reverence for his writings combined with anxiety
      concerning their orthodoxy which is well-attested elsewhere in the monastic literature of the
      period. The Syriac and Greek Versions used here include the following: the critical edition of
      Syriac S1 and S2 texts ed. and trans. by A. Guillaumont, Les six Centuries des ‘Kephalaia
      Gnostica’ d’Évagre le Pontique, Patrologia Orientalis 28.1, Nº 134 (Paris, 1958). Syriac S1
      text with commentary by Babai the Great and Greek retroversion, ed. and trans. by by W.
      Frankenberg, Evagrius Ponticus, Abhandlungen der königlichen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften
      zu Göttingen, Phil.-hist. Klasse, Neue Folge, vol. 13, no. 2. (Berlin, 1912), pp. 8-471.
      Principal Greek fragments ed. by: 1) I. Hausherr, ‘Nouveaux fragments grecs d’Evagre le
      Pontique’,Orientalia Christiana Periodica 5 (1939), pp. 229-233; 2) Muyldermans, ‘À Travers la
      Tradition Manuscrite d’ Èvagre le Pontique’, Bibliothèque du Muséon 3 (Louvain: Istas, 1933),
      pp. 74, 85, 89, 93; 3) Muyldermans, ‘Evagriana. Extrait de la revue Le Muséon, vol. 42,
      augmenté de nouveaux fragments grecs inédits’ (Paris, 1931), pp. 38-44; 4) Géhin, ‘Evagriana
      d’un Manuscrit Basilien, (Vaticanus Gr. 2028; olim Basilianus 67)’, Le Muséon 109 (1996), pp.
      59-85. </comment>
  </head>
  <text>
    <body xml:lang="eng" in-progress="false">
      <div type="century" n="I">
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p n="S1">[S1:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S1">: Even as the light, as it makes us see all, does not need another light with
            which it will be seen, so God as well when he makes everything seen, does not need
            another light with which he will be known; He, in fact, in his essence,"He is light"</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p n="S1">: This is not the same thing as the sense and the organ of sense , nor the
            sensitive and the sensible. The sense, in fact, is the power with which we are
            accustomed to feel the matter; the organ of the senses is the member in which the sense
            resides; the sensitive is the living subject which possesses the sense organs; the
            sensible is that which falls under the organs of sense. But the nous is not like that,
            because it is deprived of one of the four.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p n="S1">: The spiritual sense is the dispassion of the reasoning soul, which is produced
            by the grace of God</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p n="S1">: Just as, being awake, we say diverse things about dreams and that, when we are
            asleep, we learn them by experience, so all that we learn about God, when we were
            outside of him, it is when we will have been inside of him that we will receive the
            demonstration of them by experience.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S1">: When we were first made, the seeds of virtue were found naturally in us, but
            malice not at all. It is not that, in fact, that to which we are susceptible, has its
            power also in us, because that, because we can not have been that, the power of what we
            are not is not in us, if powers are qualities and what is not is not a quality.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p n="S1">: There was a time when evil did not exist, and there will be a time when it
            will no longer exist; but there was never a time when virtue did not exist, and there
            will never be a time when it will not exist. Indestructible, in effect, are the seeds of
            virtue. I am also convinced of this by the rich man who was condemned in the Shéol
            because of his evil and had pity for his brothers; thus to have pity is a beautiful seed
            of virtue</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p n="S1">: If death is second compared to life, and sickness second compared to health,
            it is evident that evil is second by comparison to virtue. Death and sickness of the
            soul, in effect, is evil, and virtue is more ancient also than that which is in the
            middle.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p n="S1">God is everywhere, and He is not somewhere; He is everywhere, because everything
            that has been produced is by His "wisdom full of variety"; but He is not somewhere,
            because He is not from among beings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p n="S1">: If the kingdom of heaven is known by what came before everything and what
            contains everything, the torment also of those who will be judged will be known by what
            is opposed</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p n="S1">: There is nothing among the bodiless which is in power in bodies; and bodiless
            is our nous, when it renders itself similar to God</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p n="S1">: All that is in power in the body, it possesses in act, and they are of the
            same nature as those from which they derive. But the nous which contemplates God is
            liberated from imprint and matter</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p n="S1">: There is nothing which could be in power in the soul which similarly could be
            naturally in it also in act; it is by liberty, in effect, that it grows and it is the
            power of God which perfects it</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p n="S1">: The imprints which are in the bodies similarly exist in those which have
            engendered them. But the soul, by the liberty which was given it by God, imprints its
            being as it wishes, either to render itself similar to God, or to render itself similar
            to the animals</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p n="S1">: It is not the Unity which apart from itself puts itself in motion; but it is
            put in motion by the receptivity of the nous, which, by its negligence, turns away its
            face and, by the fact of being deprived of it, engenders ignorance </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p n="S1">: All that was produced was produced for the knowledge of God; but among beings,
            some are firsts, and others seconds. Older than the first beings is (spiritual)
            knowledge, and (older) than the second beings is movement</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p n="S1">: Movement is the cause of evil, and the destroyer of evil is virtue; but the
            names of virtue are in the modes of conduct, and the cause of these is movement</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p n="S1">: When the true knowledge will be in those which are first by their genesis,
            then those also will obtain by grace also the knowledge of the holy Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p n="S1">[S1=S2: The demons which fight with the nous are called birds, animals those
            which trouble thumos, and beasts those which excite epithumia</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p n="S1">: Without end is the fullness of those who are first by their genesis, and
            within ends is the emptiness contained . The second beings are coextensive with
            emptiness , and they will rest when the perfect fullness will lead those who are
            receptive of it toward the knowledge of the Unity of the Holy Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S1">: Those who are first by their genesis will be delivered only from the act of
            corruption; but the deliverance from all will be achieved when the will of the Lord of
            all will have occurred</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p n="S1">: The good will be cause of knowledge and of torment, and the bad47 of torment
            only.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p n="S1">: Men dread the Sheol, and demons are terrified by the abyss.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p n="S1">: Among deaths, some are caused by the first condemnation. For others that cause
            is liberating grace; and the cause of the third death is remission that is done through
            mercy. But immortal are those for whom none of these occur.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S1">: Just as light and shadow are accidental things of the air, the same for the
            reasonable soul virtue and evil, knowledge and ignorance, virtue and knowledge being
            both first in it</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p n="S1">: If today they receive the well advised accountant in their houses it is
            obvious that yesterday they sat down and counted their bonds. However, he was called
            well advised because he gave to his colleagues part of the assets of the property.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p n="S1">: There are none of the second beings which would not be 49 susceptible of the
            knowledge, and none of the first beings which would be contained in a place.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p n="S1">: Knowledge is said to be in a place, when it frequents the intellections of
            creatures, but in no place when it admires the Holy Trinity</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p n="S1">: Whether the logikoi would be or would not be, that is the affair of the will
            of the Creator; but that they would be mortal or immortal, that is the affair of their
            will</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p n="S1">: All reasonable nature, in fact, is susceptible of an opposition.50 The true
            life of the logikoi is their activity in spirit, and their death is the activity against
            nature.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p n="S1">: In the growth of the intellections of the creatures there are works and
            combats. But in contemplation of the Holy Trinity it is peace and an ineffable
            quietude.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p n="S1">: The virtues are said to be before us, facing the senses which see them; but it
            is behind us that are said to be the bad actions, because they are accomplished in the
            shadows. We are ordered, in fact, to "flee fornication" and to "pursue hospitality".</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p n="S1">: Who will know the sustasis of this world, the activity of the elements and the
            practice of this instrument, how it will become a chariot by the practice of the
            commandments and will raise itself up by a spiritual ascension toward the Holy
            Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p n="S1">: Among the holy angels there is a predominance of the nous, among the humans,
            predominance of the épithumia, and among the demons predominance of the thumos. The
            Fathers say that the first approach the intermediaries by the mouth, and the last the
            intermediaries by the nostrils</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p n="S1">: The one who leads in knowledge has someone after him; but he who leads in
            ignorance has none.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p n="S1">: The end of the knowledge of nature is the knowledge of holy Unity; but to
            incomprehensibility, as the Fathers say, there is no end, as it is written: "There is no
            limit to His intelligence".</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p n="S1">: The Lord has pity on those to whom he gives spiritual knowledge, because it is
            written: "The just walk in the light and the insane in the shadows". But the Lord has
            pity also on the insane, in that it is not right away that He torments him but He fixes
            for him a model in order that he converts and lives.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p n="S1">: The light of the nous is divided in three, that is: in the knowledge of the
            adorable and holy Trinity, in bodiless and embodied nature, and in the intellection of
            the natures of creatures</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S1">It is not to the true knowledge which is hidden in the natures that ignorance is
            made the opposite, but to the knowledge of children. But, when children have become
            adults, they will win over ignorance.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p n="S1">THE nous of all the logikoi which are imprinted in the resemblance of their
            Creator is Christ our Savior; and it is He who perfects them in the knowledge of the
            holy Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p n="S1">The first renunciation of the world, which is done in the soul, is such: that
            with good will one abandons the things of this world for the science of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S1">The second renunciation is distancing oneself from evil, which is produced by
            the application of man and by the grace of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p n="S1">The third renunciation is the separation from ignorance, which usually appears
            to men as certain fantasies in combat, according to the degree of their growth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p n="S1">The glory and light of the nous is spiritual knowledge, the glory and light of
            the soul is its apatheia.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p n="S1">The nous of the logikoi is receptive of knowledge and ignorance, epithumiais
            receptive of chastity and of luxury, and following the thumos go love and hatred That
            which is first among the firsts is accompanied by what is first among the seconds, and
            what is first among the seconds (is accompanied) by what is first among the thirds.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p n="S1">The nous wanders, when it becomes impassioned, that it is to say it is
            uncontrollable when it achieves its diverse desires. But it restrains itself in its rush
            and renounces its distractions which surround it when it becomes dispassionate and when
            it has arrived in the company of those who are bodiless, those who fulfill all its
            spiritual desires.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <p n="S1">[S1=S2: Love is the excellent state of the reasonable soul, which in this cannot
            love anything which is among corruptible things more than the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p n="S1">Everything that was created was created for the knowledge of God; on the other
            hand, everything that was created for something else is less than what it was created
            for; in consequence, the knowledge of God is superior to everything, because everything
            was created for it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p n="S1">: Natural knowledge is true understanding of those created for the knowledge of
            the Holy Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p n="S1">All reasoning nature was naturally made to understand true knowledge, and God is
            essential knowledge. The reasoning nature that has been created therefore has opposed to
            it the fact of not being created; and opposed to liberty are evil and ignorance; but not
            one of those things is opposed to God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p n="S1">If today is the Friday when our Savior was crucified, all those who have died in
            Christ are the symbol of his tomb because with them the justice of God was buried, that
            which will be resuscitated on the third day, re clothed in a spiritual body. True
            indeed, is the word of our Savior, that "today and tomorrow He works miracles and on the
            third day it is completed."</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="II">
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p n="S1"> The praktike soul that by the grace of God has triumphed and is part of the
            body will be in those regions of knowledge where the wings of its apatheia will
            sendit.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p n="S1">] Desirable are things that are known through the organs of sense, but most
            desirable is the contemplation of true knowledge. But because sensation cannot attain
            knowledge due to its infirmity, it regards as superior what is closer, rather than that
            which is distant and [truly superior to it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p n="S1">] Just as is not material things that nourish the body, but rather their powers;
            so also it is not [external] matters themselves that make the soulgrow, but the
            varieties of the knowledge of [external matters.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S1">] The nous, also, has five spiritual senses, by which it sees and feels the
            minds of creatures. Vision shows it beings as [external objects; through hearing it
            receives the logoi that concern them; through smell it revels in the holy and unmixed
            fragrance, while the palate of his mouth delights in them;by touching it receives
            exactly the certainty that is true in them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p n="S1">] The sense organs and the nous share in sensible [things, but the only the nous
            has understanding of both both the intelligible (noetic) and sensible, indeed, itbecomes
            a seer of both objects and their logoi.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p n="S1"> Just as in the organs of sense, the senses are changed by differentqualities
            and colors, so too the nous is changed when it gazes upon different contemplations</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="III">
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p n="S1">It is possible to say what the movement of the nous is, but its nature is
            ineffable, because it has not been constituted of the four elements.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p n="S1">] The nous is healed by knowledge; the thumos, by love; and theépithumia, by
            chastity. And the cause of the first is the second, and that of the second is the
            third.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p n="S1">The world is the sustasis of the natures that have been constituted of different
            bodies and contain different logikoi for growth in the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S1"> If all evil is created by the three parts of the soul, that is by
            thelogistikon, by epithumia, or by thumos, and if it is possible to use these either
            well or badly, it is clear that evil is created by their use contrary to nature. And if
            this is the case, there is nothing that has been created by God that is evil.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p n="S1">] Of all creation, only the nous is receptive of the knowledge of the Holy
            Trinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S1"> When we were formed in the womb we lived the life of plants, when we were
            children, we lived the lives of animals, and when we becameadults, we live the life
            either of angels or of demons; that is, by virtue or bycontempt.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p n="S1"> The angels and the demons approach our world but we do notapproach their
            worlds. Indeed, we can not move closer to God's angels, nor can we imagine defiling the
            demons worse than they are.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p n="S1"> The demons do not cease slandering the gnostic, even when it is not at fault in
            order to attract them to the nous by thumos. Indeed, it is as if a dark cloud stands
            before the mind and drives the nous away at the time of contemplation if the demons are
            not reproved as slanderers.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="IV">
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S1">If in the world to come God shows His riches to the logikoi, it is evident that
            in this world they possess a part of it</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p n="S1">The key of the kingdom of the heavens is the spiritual gift which reveals to the
            nous the contemplation of the spiritual praktiké, the intellection which is in the
            natures and the logoi that concern the divinity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p n="S1">Christ, before his coming, appeared to men in various forms; and in His coming,
            He appeared to them in the truth of their bodies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p n="S1">While all pleasure which comes from the practice of good actions proceeds from
            the world to come, the pleasure of spiritual knowledge remains with the nous in this
            world and in the world to come.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p n="S1">There is one good love which remains eternally, that which is the love of the
            true knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p n="S1">In all the languages, the names and the words are known, and they inform about
            the objects. Thus, the language of the holy Spirit informs64 about the differences in
            the intellections.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S1">The utterances of the virtues are the mirror of the virtues; he who thus
            "listens" to the virtues and does not "practice them," he sees only the shadow of the
            virtues as in a mirror. But the true virtue is the exact face of the soul.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p n="S1">If the first Israel, many of whom were not from Israel, accompanied him, is it
            also with the new Israel many among the Egyptians 67 did not go out? </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p n="S1">The sensible things move the soul to make it take on their shapes: just as the
            intelligible intellections move the nous to make it take on their contemplation</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p n="S1">The spiritual "linen" is the justice of the soul, by which it is accustomed to
            win fame in works of beautiful actions and in the science of faith.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p n="S1">He who is full of passions and prays for his departure from this world to occur
            rapidly resembles a man who is sick and who asks the cabinet maker to quickly break up
            his bed before he gets well.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p n="S1">The sensible things are outside of the nous, and their view is inside it. But it
            is not therefore that way in regard to the holy Trinity, because that is essential
            knowledge.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="V">
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p n="S1"> He who fights for apatheia will arm himself with the commandments of God, and
            he who (fights) for the truth, will choose to arm himself with knowledge, and thus he
            will go out against their enemies. There will be a defeat of the first, when he will not
            do what is commanded of him and (defeat) of the second, when, in his doctrine, he will
            fall from the truth and will become the head of the erroneous doctrines.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p n="S1"> "The place of God" (Exod, 24:1) is called peace, and peace is the state of
            dispassion of the reasonable nature. He who therefore wishes that his God resides in him
            will purify with care his soul of all passions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p n="S1">The holy Trinity is not a thing having qualities, for that pertains to
            creatures.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p n="S1">He who was separated from things was deprived also of their contemplation; and
            he from whom was removed the contemplations will find himself outside of things. But the
            holy Trinity is not the same; we believed, in fact, that it is the essential
            knowledge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p n="S1"> The senses discern the sensible, and the nous their contemplation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p n="S1">Sense does not discern sense; the sense organs do not discern the other sense
            organs, but the sense. The nous discerns the sense organs and the sense.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p n="S1">When we consider matter, we remember their contemplation; and, once we have
            received the contemplation, we come to the memory of matter But it is not how it happens
            also in the contemplation of the Holy Trinity</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p n="S1">The Holy Trinity is not a thing having composition or qualities, whether missing
            or in excess; it is in fact, a unique essence, which in everything is always equal to
            itself</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p n="S1">In the contemplation of beings, there are ascents and descents, according to the
            diligence or the negligence. But it is not the same in the contemplation of the Holy
            Trinity. It is, in fact, a vision that is equal to itself, where there is neither ascent
            or descent.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p n="S1"> If "the four arms " were divided from only one source, let us understand with
            discernment their exits and their regions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p n="S1"> The nous is in admiration, when it looks at the natures, and it is not troubled
            when it meets a related and beloved contemplation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p n="S1"> The more the nous divests itself of passions, the more it looks at the
            intellections; and the more its zeal presses the more the knowledge enriches itself</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S1"> To perceive the contemplation of the natures appertains to the power of the
            nous; but to look at the holy Trinity does not appertain to its powers alone; but that
            is a superior gift of grace</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="century" n="VI">
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p n="S1"> The body of Christ is connatural with our body; his soul also is of the nature
            of our souls; in the same way also his divinity is coessential with the Father.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p n="S1"> Just as it is not possible for a reasoning nature to be with the body apart
            from the world, so it is not possible for a reasoning nature , apart from the body, to
            be in the new world.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p n="S1"> One says that God dwells in his creation in the same way as a builder in his
            house.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p n="S1"> Thumos slips into the heart and epithumia of the flesh into the blood. Because
            of this we have received the command to distance the heart from anger and the flesh from
            vice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p n="S1"> "It is not only the holy angels who work with us for our salvation, but also
            the saints, our companions, who themselves were of assistance in the Gospel to Our
            Lord"</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
