<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../TAN-2021/schemas/TAN-voc.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../TAN-2021/schemas/tan.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TAN-voc xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns"
         id="tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-key:evagrius-scripta"
         TAN-version="2021">
    <head>
        <name>Scripta pertaining to the writings of Evagrius</name>
        <license which="by_4.0" licensor="kalvesmaki"/>
        <vocabulary>
            <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-key:evagrius-agents</IRI>
            <name>General keywords associated with the TAN collection for Evagrius of Pontus</name>
            <location href="evagrius-agents-TAN-voc.xml" accessed-when="2019-08-12"/>
        </vocabulary>
        <vocabulary-key>
            <person xml:id="kalvesmaki" which="Joel Kalvesmaki"/>
        </vocabulary-key>
        <file-resp who="kalvesmaki"/>
        <resp who="kalvesmaki" roles="editor"/>
        <change when="2019-08-12" who="kalvesmaki">started file</change>
       <change when="2019-12-26" who="kalvesmaki">Converted bibliography, sorted items</change>
        <to-do>
            <comment when="2019-12-26" who="kalvesmaki">File will be updated when the Guide to Evagrius Pontus is updated.</comment>
        </to-do>
    </head>
    <body affects-element="source scriptum">
       <!-- manuscripts -->
       <item>
          <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ms:gb:london:bl:add-14578</IRI>
          <name>BL Add 14578</name>
          <name>B.L. Add. 14,578</name>
          <name>British Library, Add. 14,578</name>
          <name>Wright 557</name>
       </item>
       <item>
          <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ms:gb:london:bl:add-14581</IRI>
          <name>BL Add 14581</name>
          <name>B.L. Add. 14,581</name>
          <name>British Library, Add. 14,581</name>
          <name>Wright 734</name>
       </item>
       <item>
          <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ms:gb:london:bl:add-14616</IRI>
          <name>BL Add 14616</name>
          <name>B.L. Add. 14,616</name>
          <name>British Library, Add. 14,616</name>
          <name>Wright 744</name>
       </item>
       <item>
          <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ms:gb:london:bl:add-17165</IRI>
          <name>BL Add 17165</name>
          <name>B.L. Add. 17,165</name>
          <name>British Library, Add. 17,165</name>
          <name>Wright 733</name>
       </item>
       <item>
          <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ms:gb:london:bl:add-17167</IRI>
          <name>BL Add 17167</name>
          <name>B.L. Add. 17,167</name>
          <name>British Library, Add. 17,167</name>
          <name>Wright 743</name>
       </item>
       <item>
          <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ms:va:vat.gr.754</IRI>
          <name>Vat. gr. 754</name>
          <name>Vat gr 754</name>
       </item>
       <item>
          <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:private:2020:karapetian-and-young</IRI>
          <name>Karapetian and Young 2020</name>
          <desc>Suite of Word documents with Armenian edition of the letters, with facing
          English translations of the same and the Syriac versions of the letters.</desc>
       </item>
       
       <!-- print -->
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:garnier-1857</IRI>
         <name>Garnier 1839</name>
         <desc>Basil of Caesarea. Opera omnia: quae exstant, vel quae ejus nomine circumferuntur, ad MSS. codices Gallicanos .. Vol. 3. Paris: J. B. Coignard, 1839.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-960-518-440-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:aimilianos-2016</IRI>
         <name>Aimilianos 2016</name>
         <desc>Aimilianos, Elder. On Prayer: An Interpretation of St. Neilos / Περὶ προσευχῆς: Ἑρμηνεία στὸν ὅσιο Νείλο τοῦ ἀσκητή. Athens: Indiktos, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:alfeyev-1997</IRI>
         <name>Alfeyev 1997</name>
         <desc>Alfeyev, Hilarion. “The Patristic Background of St. Symeon the New Theologian's Doctrine of the Divine Light.” Studia Patristica 32 (1997): 229–38.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:allen-1995</IRI>
         <name>Allen 1995</name>
         <desc>Allen, Diogenes. “Ascetic Theology and the Eight Deadly Thoughts: [Evagrius of Pontus' Teachings as Resource for Spiritual Regeneration].” Evangelical Journal 13 (1995): 15–21.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:allen-1997</IRI>
         <name>Allen, Roberts, and Talbot 1997</name>
         <name>allen 1997</name>
         <desc>Allen, Diogenes. “Ascetic Theology and Psychology.”  In Limning the Psyche: Explorations in Christian Psychology. Edited by Robert Campbell Roberts and Mark R. Talbot, pp. 297–316. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1997. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:amélineau-1887</IRI>
         <name>Amélineau and Palladius 1887</name>
         <name>amélineau 1887</name>
         <desc>Amélineau, Emile and Palladius, Bishop of Aspuna. De Historia Lausiaca quaenam sit hujus ad monachorum Aegyptiorum historiam scribendam utilitas: Adjecta sunt quaedam hujus historiae Coptica fragmenta inedita. Paris: E. Leroux, 1887. archive.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0790581361</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:amélineau-1894</IRI>
         <name>Amélineau 1894</name>
         <desc>Amélineau, E. Histoire des monastères de la Basse-Egypte vies des saints Paul, Antoine, Macaire, Maxime et Domèce, Jean le Nain, &amp;a [sic]: Texte copte et traduction française. Annales du Musée Guimet 25. Paris: E. Leroux, 1894. harvard.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:arnou-1934</IRI>
         <name>Arnou 1934</name>
         <desc>Arnou, R. “Unité numérique et unité de nature chez les pères, après le Concile de Nicée.” Gregorianum 15 (1934): 242–54.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:arras-1963</IRI>
         <name>Arras 1963</name>
         <desc>Arras, Victor. Collectio monastica. Corpus scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium. Scriptores Aethiopici 45–46 238–239. Louvain,: Secrétariat du CSCO, 1963. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:arras-1986</IRI>
         <name>Arras 1986</name>
         <desc>Arras, Victor. Geronticon. Corpus scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium. Scriptores Aethiopici 79–80. Louvain: Peeters, 1986. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:arzhanov-2015</IRI>
         <name>Arzhanov, Rammelt, Schlarb, and Schlarb 2015</name>
         <name>arzhanov 2015</name>
         <desc>Arzhanov, Yuri. “Abba Platon und Abba Evagrius.”  In Begegnungen in Vergangenheit und Gegenwart: Beiträge dialogischer Existenz; Eine freundschaftliche Festgabe zum 60. Geburtstag von Martin Tamcke. Edited by Claudia Rammelt, Cornelia Schlarb, and Egbert Schlarb, pp. 75–82. Theologie 112. Berlin: LIT, 2015. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:augst-1988</IRI>
         <name>Augst 1988</name>
         <desc>Augst, Rüdiger. Acedia—religiöse Gleichgültigkeit als Logismos und Denkform bei Evagrius Ponticus. [n.p.]: Saarbrücken, 1988. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-631-42694-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:augst-1990</IRI>
         <name>Augst 1990</name>
         <desc>Augst, Rüdiger. Lebensverwirklichung und christlicher Glaube: Acedia-Religiöse Gleichgültigkeit als Problem der Spiritualität bei Evagrius Ponticus. Saarbrücker Theologische Forschungen 3. Frankfurt am Main and New York: Peter Lang, 1990. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:augustin-1993</IRI>
         <name>Augustin 1993</name>
         <desc>Augustin, Pierre. “Note critique sur deux traités d'Évagre.” Revue des Études Augustiniennes 39 (1993): 203–13.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bachmann-1893</IRI>
         <name>Bachmann 1893</name>
         <desc>Bachmann, Johannes. Aethiopische lesestücke: Inedita aethiopica für den gebrauch in universitäts-vorlesungen. Leipzig: J. C. Hinrichs, 1893. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bacht-1964</IRI>
         <name>Bacht and Wessel 1964</name>
         <name>bacht 1964</name>
         <desc>Bacht, Heinrich. “Pachomius und Evagrius.”  In Christentum am Nil, pp. 142–57. Recklinghausen: A. Bongers, 1964. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bacht-1977</IRI>
         <name>Bacht, Pflug, Eckert, and Friesenhahn 1977</name>
         <name>bacht 1977</name>
         <desc>Bacht, Heinrich. “Agrypnia: Die Motive des Schlafentzuges im frühen Mönchtum.”  In Bibliothek, Buch, Geschichte: Kurt Köster zum 65. Geburtstag, pp. 353–69. Sonderveröffentlichungen der Deutschen Bibliothek 5. Frankfurt am Main: Klostermann, 1977. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bacht-1981</IRI>
         <name>Bacht and Sudbrack 1981</name>
         <name>bacht 1981</name>
         <desc>Bacht, Heinrich. “Evagrius Ponticus und Pachomius von Tabennesi: Das Vermächtnis des Ursprungs.”  In Zeugen Christlicher Gotteserfahrung. Edited by Josef Sudbrack, pp. 34–63. Mainz: Matthias-Grünewald-Verlag, 1981. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bacht-1984</IRI>
         <name>Bacht, Sudbrack, and Ruhbach 1984</name>
         <name>bacht 1984</name>
         <desc>Bacht, Heinrich. “Evagrios Pontikos.”  In Grosse Mystiker: Leben und Wirken, pp. 36–50. Munich: C. H. Beck, 1984. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bady-tchernetska-2002</IRI>
         <name>Bady and Tchernetska 2002</name>
         <name>bady tchernetska 2002</name>
         <desc>Bady, Guillaume and Tchernetska, Natalie. “Un nouveau témoin direct des Scholies aux Proverbes d'Évagre le Pontique (Cambridge, Trinity Coll. O.1.55).” Revue d'Histoire des Textes 32 (2002): 63–72.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:balthasar-1939a</IRI>
         <name>balthasar 1939a</name>
         <desc>Balthasar, Hans Urs von. “Metaphysik und Mystik des Evagrius Pontikus.” Zeitschrift für Askese und Mystik  (1939): 31–47.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:balthasar-1939b</IRI>
         <name>balthasar 1939b</name>
         <desc>Balthasar, Hans Urs von. “Die Hiera des Evagrius.” Zeitschrift für Katholische Theologie 63 (1939): 86–106; 181–206.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:balthasar-1965</IRI>
         <name>Balthasar 1965</name>
         <desc>Balthasar, Hans Urs von. “The Metaphysics and Mystical Theology of Evagrius.” Monastic Studies 3 (1965): 183–195.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bamberger-1968</IRI>
         <name>Bamberger 1968</name>
         <desc>Bamberger, John Eudes. “Evagrius Ponticus: The Praktikosand Chapters on Prayer.” Cistercian Studies Quarterly 3, no. 2 (1968): 137–46.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-87907-804-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bamberger-1970</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Bamberger 1970</name>
         <name>bamberger 1970</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. The Praktikos: Chapters on Prayer. Translated by John Eudes Bamberger. Cistercian Studies Series 4. Spencer, Mass.: Cistercian Publications, 1970. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bamberger-1992</IRI>
         <name>Bamberger 1992</name>
         <desc>Bamberger, John Eudes. “Desert Calm: Evagrius Ponticus; The Theologian as Spiritual Guide.” Cistercian Studies Quarterly 27, no. 3 (1992): 185–98.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:90-5047-015-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bar-salibi-1991</IRI>
         <name>Dionysius bar Ṣalībī and Çiçek 1991</name>
         <name>bar salibi 1991</name>
         <desc>Dionysius bar Ṣalībī, Bishop of Amida. Pušaqa d-maʼwata d-qadiša Mar ʼEwagris Iḥidaya. Harvard College Library Assyrian collection. Holʼanda: Maṭbaʻta d-Bar ʻEbraya d-Dayra d-Mar ʼEprem Suryaya, 1991. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bar-salibi-2011</IRI>
         <name>Dionysius bar Ṣalībī and Çiçek 2011</name>
         <name>bar salibi 2011</name>
         <desc>Dionysius bar Ṣalībī, Bishop of Amida. A Commentary on the 100 Theses of Evagrius Ponticus. Bar Ebroyo Kloster Publications 10. Piscataway, N.J.: Gorgias Press, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-8306-7522-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:baán-2011</IRI>
         <name>Baán 2011</name>
         <desc>Baán, Izsák Zsolt. I "due occhi dell'anima": L'uso, l'interpretazione e il ruolo della Sacra Scrittura nell'insegnamento di Evagrio Pontico. Studia Anselmiana. Analecta monastica 11. Roma: Pontificio Ateneo S. Anselmo, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:berthold-1987</IRI>
         <name>Berthold and Lies 1987</name>
         <name>berthold 1987</name>
         <desc>Berthold, George C. “History and Exegesis in Evagrius and Maximus.”  In Origeniana quarta: Die Referate des 4. Internationalen Origenskongresses (Innsbruck, 2.-6. September 1985), pp. 390–404. Innsbrucker theologische Studien 19. Innsbruck: Tyrolia-Verlag, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bertocchi-1961</IRI>
         <name>Bertocchi 1961-1970</name>
         <name>bertocchi 1961</name>
         <desc>Bertocchi, P. “Evagrio Pontico.”  In Bibliotheca sanctorum, pp. 356–363. Rome: Istituto Giovanni XXIII nella Pontificia Università lateranense, 1961–1970. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bertrand-1999</IRI>
         <name>Bertrand, Bienert, and Kühneweg 1999</name>
         <name>bertrand 1999</name>
         <desc>Bertrand, Dominique. “L'implication du "nous" dans la prière chez Origène et Évagre le Pontique.”  In Origeniana septima: Origenes in den Auseinandersetzungen des 4. Jahrhunderts. Edited by Wolfgang Bienert and Uwe Kühneweg, pp. 355–63. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 137. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:88-7961-022-8</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-88-7961-022-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bettiolo-2000a</IRI>
         <name>bettiolo 2000a</name>
         <desc>Bettiolo, Paolo. L'epistula fidei di Evagrio Pontico: Temi, contesti, sviluppi; Atti del III convegno del gruppo italiano di ricerca su "Origene e la tradizione alessandrina". Studia Ephemeridis Augustinianum 72. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bettiolo-2000b</IRI>
         <name>bettiolo 2000b</name>
         <desc>Bettiolo, Paolo. “'Camminava sulle orme del Santo Basilio': Evagrio e il vescovo di Cesarea: Un rapporto problematico.”  In L'epistula fidei di Evagrio Pontico: Temi, contesti, sviluppi; Atti del III convegno del gruppo italiano di ricerca su "Origene e la tradizione alessandrina", pp. 59–86. Studia Ephemeridis Augustinianum 72. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bettiolo-2009</IRI>
         <name>Bettiolo 2009</name>
         <desc>Bettiolo, Paolo. “Discernimento dei pensieri e conoscenza del cuore: Natura e sovrannatura nell'insegnamento di Evagrio Pontico.” Rivista di storia del cristianesimo 6 (2009): 43–63.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:beyer-1981</IRI>
         <name>Beyer 1981</name>
         <desc>Beyer, Hans-Veit. “Die Lichtlehre der Mönche des vierzehnten und des vierten Jahrhunderts.” Jahrbuch der Österreichischen Byzantinistik 31 (1981): 473–512.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:beyschlag-1979</IRI>
         <name>Beyschlag 1979</name>
         <desc>Beyschlag, Karlmann. “Was heißt mystische Erfahrung: Entwickelt an den Beispielen Euagrios Pontikos und Symeon, dem Neuen Theologen.”  In Evangelium als Schicksal: Fünf Studien zur Geschichte der alten Kirche, pp. 113–34. Munich: Claudius-Verlag, 1979. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bigot-1680</IRI>
         <name>Bigot 1680</name>
         <desc>Bigot, Émery. Palladii episcopi helenopolitani De vita s. Johannis Chrysostomi dialogus: Accedunt homilia Sancti Johannis chrysostomi in laudem Diodori, Tarsensis episcopi, Acta Tarachi, Probi et andronici, Passio Banifatii Romani, Evagrius de octo cogitationibus, Nilus de octo vitiis. Luteciæ Parisiorum: Apud viduam Edmundi Martini, 1680. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bitton-ashkelony-2005</IRI>
         <name>Bitton-Ashkelony 2005</name>
         <desc>Bitton-Ashkelony, Brouria. Encountering the Sacred: The Debate on Christian Pilgrimage in Late Antiquity. Transformation of the classical heritage 38. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2005. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bitton-ashkelony-2011</IRI>
         <name>Bitton-Ashkelony 2011</name>
         <desc>Bitton-Ashkelony, Brouria. “The Limit of the Mind (νοῦς): Pure Prayer according to Evagrius Ponticus and Isaac of Nineveh.” Zeitschrift für Antikes Christentum / Journal of Ancient Christianity 15, no. 2 (2011): 291–321.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:blanchard-griffin-horn-timbie-2000</IRI>
         <name>Blanchard, Griffin, Horn, and Timbie 2000-2001</name>
         <name>blanchard griffin horn timbie 2000</name>
         <desc>Blanchard, Monica, Griffin, Carl, Horn, Cornelia, and Timbie, Janet. “The Armenian Version of the Life of Evagrius of Pontus.” St. Nersess Theological Review 5–6 (2000–2001): 25–37.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bloomfield-1952</IRI>
         <name>Bloomfield 1952</name>
         <desc>Bloomfield, Morton W. The Seven Deadly Sins: An Introduction to the History of a Religious Concept, with Special Reference to Medieval English Literature. East Lansing: Michigan State College Press, 1952. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:blum-1974</IRI>
         <name>Blum and Weinzierl 1974</name>
         <name>blum 1974</name>
         <desc>Blum, Wilhelm. “Modernismus in der Spätantike.”  In Der Modernismus: Beiträge zu seiner Erforschung, pp. 107–24. Graz, Vienna, and Köln: Verl. Styria, 1974. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:blum-1979</IRI>
         <name>Blum 1979</name>
         <desc>Blum, Georg Günter. “Vereinigung und Vermischung: Zwei grundmotive christlich-orientalischer Mystik.” Oriens Christianus 63 (1979): 41–60.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bocher-rasmussen-2005</IRI>
         <name>Bocher Rasmussen December 2005</name>
         <name>bocher rasmussen 2005</name>
         <desc>Bocher Rasmussen, Mette Sophia. “Like a Rock or Like God? The Concept of Apatheia in the Monastic Theology of Evagrius of Pontus.” Studia Theologica 59, no. 2 (December 2005): 147–162.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bousset-1923</IRI>
         <name>Bousset, Hermann, and Krüger 1923</name>
         <name>bousset 1923</name>
         <desc>Bousset, Wilhelm. Apophthegmata : Studien zur Geschichte des ältesten Mönchtums. Tübingen: Mohr, 1923. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bouyer-1963a</IRI>
         <name>bouyer 1963a</name>
         <desc>Bouyer, Louis. “Erudite Monasticism.”  In The Spirituality of the New Testament and the Fathers., pp. 380–394. History of Christian spirituality,; 1;. New York: Desclee, 1963. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-8164-0325-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bouyer-1963b</IRI>
         <name>bouyer 1963b</name>
         <desc>Bouyer, Louis. History of Christian spirituality. New York: Seabury Press, 1963. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bradford-2011</IRI>
         <name>Bradford October 2011</name>
         <name>bradford 2011</name>
         <desc>Bradford, David T. “Brain and Psyche in Early Christian Asceticism.” Psychological Reports 109, no. 2 (October 2011): 461–520.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bradford-2012</IRI>
         <name>Bradford 2012</name>
         <desc>Bradford, David T. “Evagrius Ponticus and the Psychology of 'Natural Contemplation'.” Studies in Spirituality 22 (2012): 109–125.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brague-1985</IRI>
         <name>Brague 1985</name>
         <desc>Brague, Rémi. “L'image et l'acédie: Remarques sur le premier Apophtegme.” Revue Thomiste 85 (1985): 197–228.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brajović-2001</IRI>
         <name>Brajović 2001</name>
         <desc>Brajović, Boris B. Aretologija Evagrija Pontijskog. Jasen: Nikšić, 2001. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brajović-2007</IRI>
         <name>Brajović 2007</name>
         <desc>Brajović, Boris B. “Obnovljenje i ovaploćenje u teoriji Evagrija Pontijskog.” Otačnik 1 (2007): 58–64.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brakke-1995</IRI>
         <name>Brakke 1995</name>
         <desc>Brakke, David. “The Problematization of Nocturnal Emissions in Early Christian Syria, Egypt, and Gaul.” Journal of Early Christian Studies 3 (1995): 419–60.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brakke-2005</IRI>
         <name>Brakke 2005</name>
         <desc>Brakke, David. “Making Public the Monastic Life: Reading the Self in Evagrius Ponticus' Talking Back.”  In Religion and the Self in Antiquity. Bloomington, Ind.: Indiana University Press, 2005. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0674018753</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brakke-2006</IRI>
         <name>Brakke 2006</name>
         <desc>Brakke, David. Demons and the Making of the Monk: Spiritual Combat in Early Christianity. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 2006. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brakke-2011</IRI>
         <name>Brakke, Bull, Lied, and Turner 2011</name>
         <name>brakke 2011</name>
         <desc>Brakke, David. “Mystery and Secrecy in the Egyptian Desert: Esotericism and Evagrius of Pontus.”  In Mystery and Secrecy in the Nag Hammadi Collection and Other Ancient Literature: Ideas and Practices. Edited by Christian H. Bull, Liv Ingeborg Lied, and John D. Turner. Nag Hammadi and Manichaean Studies 76. Leiden: Brill, 2011. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brakke-2013</IRI>
         <name>Brakke and Weidemann 2013</name>
         <name>brakke 2013</name>
         <desc>Brakke, David. “Reading the New Testament and Transforming the Self in Evagrius of Pontus.”  In Asceticism and Exegesis in Early Christianity: The Reception of New Testament Texts in Ancient Ascetic Discourses. Edited by Hans-Ulrich Weidemann, pp. 284–299. Novum Testamentum et orbis antiquus, Studien zur Umwelt des Neuen Testaments 101. Göttingen and Bristol, CT: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brakke-holman-2008</IRI>
         <name>Brakke and Holman 2008</name>
         <name>brakke holman 2008</name>
         <desc>Brakke, David. “Care for the Poor, Fear of Poverty, and Love of Money: Evagrius Ponticus on the Monk's Economic Vulnerability.”  In Wealth and Poverty in Early Church and Society. Grand Rapids and Brookline, Mass.: Baker Academic; Holy Cross Orthodox Press, 2008. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-87907-601-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brock-1987</IRI>
         <name>Brock 1987</name>
         <desc>Brock, Sebastian P. The Syriac fathers on prayer and the spiritual life. Cistercian Studies Series 101. Kalamazoo, Mich.: Cistercian Publications, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brock-2009</IRI>
         <name>Brock 2009</name>
         <desc>Brock, Sebastian. “Discerning the Evagrian in the Writings of Isaac of Nineveh.” Adamantius 15 (2009): 60–72.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:brésard</IRI>
         <name>Brésard n.d.</name>
         <name>brésard</name>
         <desc>Brésard, Luc. “Evagrius 345–399.” A History of Monastic Spirituality (Website). [n.p.]: [n.p.], n.d. scourmont.be</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bundy-1992</IRI>
         <name>Bundy and Daly 1992</name>
         <name>bundy 1992</name>
         <desc>Bundy, David. “The Philosophical Structures of Origenism: The Case of the Expurgated Version (S1) of the Kephalaia Gnostica of Evagrius.”  In Origeniana quinta: Historica, Text and Method, Biblica, Philosophica, Theologica, Origenism and Later developments: Papers of the 5th International Origen Congress, Boston College, 14–18 August 1989, pp. 577–584. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 105. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1982</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 1982</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Le "Lieu de la Limpidité": A propos d'un apophtègme énigmatique: Budge II, 494.” Irénikon 55 (1982): 7–18.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1983a</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1983a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Akedia: Die geistliche Lehre des Evagrios Pontikos vom Überdruss. Köln: Luthe-Verlag, 1983. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1983b</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1983b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Évagre le Pontique et les Deux Macaire.” Irénikon 56 (1983): 215–27; 323–60.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1986</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 1986</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Origenismus-Gnostizismus: Zum geistesgeschichtlichen Standort des Evagrios Pontikos.” Vigiliae Christianae 40 (1986): 24–54.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-922727-35-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1987a</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1987a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Das Geistgebet: Studien zum Traktat De oratione des Evagrios Pontikos. Schriftenreihe des Zentrums Patristischer Spiritualität Koinonia-Oriens im Erzbistum Cologne 25. Köln: Luthe-Verlag, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1987b</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1987b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “The "Spiritual Prayer": On the Trinitarian Mysticism of Evagrius of Pontus.” Monastic Studies 17 (1987): 191–208.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-7917-1205-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1988a</IRI>
         <name>Bunge and Nyssen 1988</name>
         <name>bunge 1988a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Geistliche Vaterschaft: Christliche Gnosis bei Evagrios Pontikos. Studia patristica et liturgica 23. Regensburg: Friedrich Pustet, 1988. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1988b</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 1988</name>
         <name>bunge 1988b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “"Priez sans cesse": Aux origenes de la prière hésychaste.” Studia Monastica 30 (1988): 7–16.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1989a</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1989a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Hénade ou Monade? Au sujet de deux notions centrales de la terminologie évagrienne.” Le Muséon 102 (1989): 69–91.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1989b</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1989b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Mysterium Unitatis: Der Gedanke der Einheit von Schöpfer und Geschöpf in der evagrianischen Mystik.” Freiburger Zeitschrift für Philosophie und Theologie 36 (1989): 449–69.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1989c</IRI>
         <name>Bunge and Nyssen 1989</name>
         <name>bunge 1989c</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “"Nach dem Intellekt Leben": Zum sog. "Intellektualismus" der evagrianischen Spiritualität.”  In Simandron: Der Wachklopfer; Gedenkschrift für Klaus Gamber (1919–1989). Schriftenreihe des Zentrums Patristischer Spiritualität Koinonia-Oriens im Erzbistum Köln 30. Köln: Luthe-Verlag, 1989. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-85589-352-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1991</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 1991</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Akèdia: La doctrine spirituelle d'Évagre le Pontique sur l'Acédie. Spiritualité orientale 52. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: Abbaye de Bellefontaine, 1991. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1994a</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1994a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “"Der mystische Sinn der Schrift": Anlässlich der Veroffentlichung der Scholien zum Ecclesiasten des Evagrios Pontikos.” Studia Monastica 36 (1994): 135–46.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-85589-361-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1994b</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1994b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Paternité spirituelle: La Gnose chrétienne chez Evagre le Pontique. Spiritualité orientale 61. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: Abbaye de Bellefontaine, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1994c</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1994c</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “The Mystical Meaning of Scripture: Remarks on the Occasion of the Publication of Evagrius Ponticus Scholien zum Ecclesiasten.” Studia Monastica 36, no. 2 (1994): 135–46.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-927894-22-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1996a</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 1996</name>
         <name>bunge 1996a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Irdene Gefässe: Die Praxis des persönlichen Gebetes nach der Uberlieferung der Heiligen Väter. Würzburg: Verl. "Der Christliche Osten", 1996. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1996b</IRI>
         <name>Bunge, Schneider, and Berschin 1996</name>
         <name>bunge 1996b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Praktike, physike und theologike als stufen der Erkenntnis bei Evagrios Pontikos.”  In Ab Oriente et Occidente (Mt 8,11): Kirche aus Ost und West; Gedenkschrift für Wilhelm Nyssen. Edited by Michael Schneider and Walter Berschin, pp. 59–72. St. Ottilien: EOS, 1996. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1997a</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1997a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Commentary on the Prologue of the Antirrhetikos by Evagrius of Pontus.” Studia Monastica 39, no. 1 (1997): 77–105.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1997b</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1997b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “"Créé pour être": A propos d'une citation scripturaire inaperçue dans le Peri Archon d'Origène (III, 5, 6).” Bulletin de Littérature Ecclésiastique 98 (1997): 21–29.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1997c</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1997c</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Evagrios Pontikos: Der Prolog des Antirrhetikos.” Studia Monastica 39 (1997): 77–106.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1999a</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1999a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Aktive und kontemplative Weise des Betens im Traktat De oratione des Evagrios Pontikos.” Studia Monastica 41 (1999): 211–27.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1999b</IRI>
         <name>Bunge, Largier, and Brinker-von der Heyde 1999</name>
         <name>bunge 1999b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Created and Renewed after the Image of God.”  In Homo Medietas: Aufsätze zu Religiosität, Literatur und Denkformen des Menschen vom Mittelalter bis in die Neuzeit; Festschrift für Alois Maria Haas zum 65. Geburtstag. Bern: Peter Lang, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-927894-30-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-1999c</IRI>
         <name>bunge 1999c</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Drachenwein und Engelsbrot: Die Lehre des Evagrios Pontikus von Zorn und Sanftmut. Würzburg: Der Christliche Osten, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2000</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 2000</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “La montagne intelligible: De la contemplation indirecte à la connaisance immédiate de Dieu dans le traité De oratione d'Évagre le Pontique.” Studia Monastica 42 (2000): 7–26.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-927894-19-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2004a</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 2004</name>
         <name>bunge 2004a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Akedia: Die geistliche Lehre des Evagrios Pontikos vom Überdruss. Würzburg: Der Christliche Osten, 2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2004b</IRI>
         <name>Bunge, Zelinsky, and Kostomarova 2004</name>
         <name>bunge 2004b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Вино дракона и хлеб ангельский. Учение Евагрия Понтийского о гневе и кротости.. Translated by Vladimir Zelinsky and Natalia Kostomarova. Riga: FiAM (Mezhdunarodniy blagotvoritel'nyi Fond imeni Aleksandra Men'a), 2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:83-7354-158-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2006</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 2006</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Ewagriusz z Pontu: Mistrz Zycia Duchowego. Zródla Monastyczne 19. Kraków: Tyniec - Wydawnictwo Benedyktynów, 2006. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780881413373</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0881413372</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2009a</IRI>
         <name>Bunge and Gythiel 2009</name>
         <name>bunge 2009a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Dragon's Wine and Angel's Bread: The Teaching of Evagrius Ponticus on Anger and Meekness. Translated by Anthony P. Gythiel. Crestwood, N.Y.: St. Vladimir's Seminary Press, 2009. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2009b</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 2009</name>
         <name>bunge 2009b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Encore une fois: Hénade ou Monade? Au sujet de deux notions-clés de la terminologie technique d'Évagre le Pontique.” Adamantius 15 (2009): 9–42.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-923946-81-5</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-923946-81-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2010</IRI>
         <name>Bunge and Witzenrath 2010</name>
         <name>bunge 2010</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. "In Geist und Wahrheit": Studien zu den 153 Kapiteln Über das Gebet des Evagrios Pontikos. Translated by Hagia Witzenrath. Hereditas 27. Bonn: Borengässer, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-87071-243-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2011</IRI>
         <name>Bunge and Kaffanke 2011</name>
         <name>bunge 2011</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. "Die Lehren der heiligen Väter" (RB 73, 2): Aufsätze zu Evagrios Pontikos aus drei Jahrzehnten. Weisungen der Väter 11. Beuron: Beuroner Kunstverlag, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-0-88141-394-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2012a</IRI>
         <name>bunge 2012a</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Despondency. Crestwood, N.Y.: St. Vladimir's Seminary Press, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-643-10782-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2012b</IRI>
         <name>bunge 2012b</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. Gastrimargia: Wissen und Lehre der Wüstenväter von Essen und Fasten; Dargestellt anhand der Schriften des Evagrios Pontikos. Eremos. Texte zur Spiritualität, Geschichte und Kunst 3. Berlin: Lit, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2015</IRI>
         <name>Bunge, Ilarion, and Popova 2015</name>
         <name>bunge 2015</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “From Greek to Syriac—and Back: The Misadventures of a Quotation from Evagrius Ponticus.”  In Saint Isaac the Syrian and His Spiritual Legacy: Proceedings of the International Patristics Conference, Held at the Sts Cyril and Methodius Institute for Postgraduate Studies, Moscow, October 10–11, 2013. Edited by Metropolitan of Volokolamsk Ilarion and Olʹga Sigismundovna Popova, pp. 135–45. Yonkers, New York: St Vladimir's Seminary Press, 2015. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-2018</IRI>
         <name>Bunge 2018</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel. “Évagre le Pontique fut-il un condisciple de saint Jean Chrysosotome?.” Irénikon 2018, no. 2–3 (2018): 163–183, 323–345.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-de-vogüé-1991</IRI>
         <name>Bunge and de Vogüé 1991</name>
         <name>bunge de vogüé 1991</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel and de Vogüé, Adalbert. “Palladiana III: La version copte de l'Histoire Lausiaque; II. La vie d'Évagre.” Studia Monastica 33 (1991): 7–21.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-89870-837-0</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:bunge-miller-2002</IRI>
         <name>Bunge and Miller 2002</name>
         <name>bunge miller 2002</name>
         <desc>Bunge, Gabriel and Miller, Michael J. Earthen Vessels: The Practice of Personal Prayer According to the Patristic Tradition. San Francisco: Ignatius Press, 2002. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:burke-2008</IRI>
         <name>Burke 2008</name>
         <desc>Burke, David. “The Enneagram of Evagrius of Pontus.” The Enneagram Journal 1, no. 1 (2008): 77–102, 123.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:burrus-2007</IRI>
         <name>Burrus, Burrus, and Keller 2007</name>
         <name>burrus 2007</name>
         <desc>Burrus, Virginia. “Praying Is Joying: Musings on Love in Evagrius Ponticus.”  In Toward a Theology of Eros: Transfiguring Passion at the Limits of Discipline. Edited by Virginia Burrus and Catherine Keller, pp. 194–204. New York: Fordham University Press, 2007. universitypressscholarship.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-8146-2377-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:butler-1995</IRI>
         <name>Butler, Farmer, and Burns 1995-2000</name>
         <name>butler 1995</name>
         <desc>Butler, Alban. Butler's Lives of the Saints. Tunbridge Wells, Kent and Collegeville, Minn.: Burns &amp; Oates; Liturgical Press, 1995–2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:cain-2016</IRI>
         <name>Cain 2016</name>
         <desc>Cain, Andrew. “Piety and Propaganda.”  In The Greek Historia Monachorum in Aegypto: Monastic Hagiography in the Late Fourth Century. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2016. oxfordscholarship.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:calvi-1939</IRI>
         <name>Calvi 1939</name>
         <desc>Calvi, Giovanni Battista. “La storia Lausiaca di Palladdio.” Salesianum 1 (1939): 268–79; 385–406.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:camplani-fiori-2009</IRI>
         <name>Camplani and Fiori 2009</name>
         <name>camplani fiori 2009</name>
         <desc>Camplani, Alberto and Fiori, Emiliano. “Origene e Evagrio nella cultura siriaca: storie, dottrine, testi / Origen and Evagrius in Syriac Culture: History, Doctrine, and Text.” Adamantius 15 (2009): 6–8.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:canivet-1965</IRI>
         <name>Canivet 1965</name>
         <desc>Canivet, Pierre. “Dorothée de Gaza est-il un disciple d'Évagre? (A propos d'une édition de ses oeuvres spirituelles).” Revue des Études Grecques 78 (1965): 336–46.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:case-2006</IRI>
         <name>Case 2006</name>
         <desc>Case, Hilary OSB. “Becoming One Spirit: Origen and Evagrius Ponticus on Prayer.” thesis. St Benedict / St John's, 2006. csbsju.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2002</IRI>
         <name>Casiday 2002</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “All Are from One: On St Antony the Great's Protology.” Studia Monastica 44, no. 2 (2002): 207–227.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2004a</IRI>
         <name>Casiday, Bielawski, and Hombergen 2004</name>
         <name>casiday 2004a</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “Christ, the Icon of the Father, in Evagrian Theology.”  In Il Monachesimo tra Eredità e Aperture: Testi e temi nella tradizione del monachesimo cristiano. Edited by Maciej Bielawski and Daniël Hombergen. Studia Anselmiana 140. Rome: Centro studi S. Anselmo, 2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2004b</IRI>
         <name>Casiday 2004</name>
         <name>casiday 2004b</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “Gabriel Bunge and the Study of Evagrius Ponticus: A Review Article.” St Vladimir's Theological Quarterly 48, no. 2 (2004): 249–297.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2005</IRI>
         <name>Casiday 2005</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “Evagrius Ponticus' Use of Different Versions of Scripture with Special Reference to his Scholia on Job.” Adamantius 11 (2005): 143–157.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2008</IRI>
         <name>Casiday 2008/12/23</name>
         <name>casiday 2008</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “On Heresy in Modern Patristic Scholarship: The Case of Evagrius Ponticus.” “”  (2008/12/23): 241–252.wiley.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2009</IRI>
         <name>Casiday, López-Tello García, and Zorzi 2009</name>
         <name>casiday 2009</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “Evagrius Engaged: Pastoral Aspects of His Life and Works.”  In Church, Society and Monasticism: Acts of the International Symposium, Rome, May 31–June 3, 2006. Edited by Eduarda López-Tello García and Benedetta Selene Zorzi, pp. 385–402. Studia Anselmiana 146. Rome: Centro studi S. Anselmo, 2009. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2010</IRI>
         <name>Casiday 2010</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “Universal Restoration in Evagrius Ponticus’ ‘Great Letter’.” Studia Patristica 47 (2010): 223–228.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2013a</IRI>
         <name>casiday 2013a</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. Reconstructing the Theology of Evagrius Ponticus: Beyond Heresy. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2013b</IRI>
         <name>casiday 2013b</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “Translation, Controversies, and Adaptations at St Sabas Monastery during the Sixth Century.” The Journal of Medieval Monastic Studies 2 (2013): .</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:casiday-2015</IRI>
         <name>Casiday 2015</name>
         <desc>Casiday, Augustine. “Connaissance de soi et examen de conscience – Évagre le Pontique (IVe siècle).” Communio. Revue internationale catholique 40, no. 5 (2015): 39–48.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-88-88758-22-0</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-88-88758-21-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:cataldo-2007</IRI>
         <name>Cataldo 2007</name>
         <desc>Cataldo, Giovanni. Vita come tensione nell'antropologia di Evagrio Pontico. Analecta Nicolaiana 3. Bari: Ecumenica, 2007. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:cattoi-2013</IRI>
         <name>Cattoi 2013</name>
         <desc>Cattoi, Thomas. “An Evagrian ὑπόστασις? Leontios of Byzantium and the 'Composite Subjectivity' of the Person of Christ.” Studia Patristica 68 (2013): 133–148.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ceillier-1860</IRI>
         <name>Ceillier, Bauzon, and Rondet 1860-1865</name>
         <name>ceillier 1860</name>
         <desc>Ceillier, Remi. “Évagre de Pont, archidiacre de Constantinople et abbé dans le désert des Cellules.”  In Histoire générale des auteurs sacrés et ecclésiastiques .., pp. 110–119. Paris: L. Vives, 1860–1865. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-521-04607-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:chadwick-1968</IRI>
         <name>Chadwick 1968</name>
         <desc>Chadwick, Owen. John Cassian. London: Cambridge University Press, 1968. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:chaîne-1960</IRI>
         <name>Chaîne 1960</name>
         <desc>Chaîne, M. Le manuscrit de la version copte en dialecte sahidique des “Apophthegmata Patrum. Bibliothèque d’études coptes 6. Cairo: Institut Français d'Archéologie Orientale du Caire, 1960. wordpress.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:chialà-2009</IRI>
         <name>Chialà 2009</name>
         <desc>Chialà, Sabino. “Evagrio il Pontico negli scritti di Isacco di Ninive.” Adamantius 15 (2009): 73–82.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:chitty-1954</IRI>
         <name>Chitty 1954</name>
         <desc>Chitty, Derwas J. “Pachomian Sources Reconsidered.” The Journal of Ecclesiastical History 5 (1954): 38–77.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-19-981232-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:christie-2012</IRI>
         <name>Christie 2012</name>
         <desc>Christie, Douglas E. The Blue Sapphire of the Mind: Notes for a Contemplative Ecology. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:clark-1990</IRI>
         <name>Clark 1990</name>
         <desc>Clark, Elizabeth A. “New Perspectives on the Origenist Controversy: Human Embodiment and Ascetic Strategies.” Church History 59 (1990): 145–62.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-691-03173-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:clark-1992</IRI>
         <name>Clark 1992</name>
         <desc>Clark, Elizabeth A. The Origenist Controversy: The Cultural Construction of an Early Christian Debate. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:colless-1973</IRI>
         <name>Colless 1973</name>
         <desc>Colless, Brian E. “The Mysticism of John Saba.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 39 (1973): 83–102.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:collins-2016</IRI>
         <name>Collins, OSB 2016</name>
         <name>collins 2016</name>
         <desc>Collins, OSB, Gregory. “The Evagrian Heritage in Late Byzantine Monasticism.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 317–331. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:colombás-1959</IRI>
         <name>Colombás 1959</name>
         <desc>Colombás, García M. “El concepto de monje y vida monástica hasta fines del siglo V.” Studia Monastica 1 (1959): 257–342.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:conio-1974</IRI>
         <name>Conio and Mahadevan 1974</name>
         <name>conio 1974</name>
         <desc>Conio, Caterina. “Theory and Practice in Evagrius Ponticus.”  In Philosophy, Theory and Practice: Proceedings of the International Seminar on World Philosophy, Madras, December 7–17, 1970, pp. 49–62. Madras: Centre for Advanced Study in Philosophy, University of Madras, 1974. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:constas-2016</IRI>
         <name>Constas, Andreopoulos, and Speake 2016</name>
         <name>constas 2016</name>
         <desc>Constas, Maximos. “Nothing is Greater than Divine Love: Evagrios, Maximos the Confessor, and the Philokalia.”  In Rightly Dividing the Word of Truth: Studies in Honour of Metropolitan Kallistos of Diokleia. Edited by Andreas Andreopoulos and Graham Speake, pp. 57–74. Bern: Peter Lang, 2016. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:contreras-1976</IRI>
         <name>Contreras 1976</name>
         <desc>Contreras, E. “Evagrio Póntico: Su vida, su obra, su doctrina.” Cuadernos Monásticos 11 (1976): 83–95.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:contreras-1986</IRI>
         <name>Contreras 1986</name>
         <desc>Contreras, Enrique. “Evagrio Pontico en los catalogos de varones ilustres.” Salmanticensis 33 (1986): 333–343.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-0-227-17342-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:cook-2011</IRI>
         <name>Cook 2011</name>
         <desc>Cook, Christopher. The Philokalia and the Inner Life on Passions and Prayer. London: James Clarke and Co, 2011. jamesclarke.co</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:corrigan-2007</IRI>
         <name>Corrigan and Stern-Gillet 2007</name>
         <name>corrigan 2007</name>
         <desc>Corrigan, Kevin. “The Organization of the Soul: Some Overlooked Aspects of Interpretation from Plato to Late Antiquity.”  In Reading Ancient Texts: Essays in Honour of Denis O'Brien, pp. 99–113. Brill's studies in intellectual history 161–162. Leiden: Brill, 2007. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780754616856</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0754616851</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780754692874</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:corrigan-2009</IRI>
         <name>Corrigan 2009</name>
         <desc>Corrigan, Kevin. Evagrius and Gregory: Mind, Soul and Body in the 4th Century. Ashgate Studies in Philosophy &amp; Theology in Late Antiquity. Farnham and Burlington: Ashgate, 2009. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:corrigan-2013</IRI>
         <name>Corrigan 2013</name>
         <desc>Corrigan, Kevin. “Suffocation or Germination: Infinity, Formation and Calibration of the Mind in Evagrius’ Notion of Contemplation.” Studia Patristica 57 (2013): 9–26.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:corrigan-2016</IRI>
         <name>Corrigan 2016</name>
         <desc>Corrigan, Kevin. “Thoughts that Cut: Cutting, Imprinting, and Lingering in Evagrius of Ponticus.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 49–72. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:corrigan-glazov-2014</IRI>
         <name>Corrigan and Glazov 2014</name>
         <name>corrigan glazov 2014</name>
         <desc>Corrigan, Kevin and Glazov, Gregory Yuri. “Compunction and Compassion: Two Overlooked Virtues in Evagrius of Pontus.” Journal of Early Christian Studies 22, no. 1 (2014): 61–77.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:cotelerius-1677-vol3</IRI>
         <name>Cotelerius 1677</name>
         <name>cotelerius 1677 vol3</name>
         <desc>Cotelerius, Johannes Baptista. Ecclesiae Graecae monumenta. Paris: Apud Franciscum Muguet, 1677. google.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:cramer-1844</IRI>
         <name>Cramer 1844</name>
         <desc>Cramer, J. A. Catenæ græcorum patrum in novum testamentum. Oxford: E Typographeo Academico, 1844. archive.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:crouzel-1961</IRI>
         <name>Crouzel 1961</name>
         <desc>Crouzel, Henri. “Recherches sur Origène et son influence.” Bulletin de Littérature Ecclésiastique 6e sér, 62 (1961): 3–15; 105–13.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:crouzel-1986</IRI>
         <name>Crouzel 1986</name>
         <desc>Crouzel, Henri. “Origène a-t-il tenu que le règne du Christ prendrait fin?.” Augustinianum 26 (1986): 51–61.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:csányi-1960</IRI>
         <name>Csányi 1960</name>
         <desc>Csányi, Daniel A. “'Optima Pars': Die Auslegungsgeschichte von Lk 10,38–42 bei den Kirchenvätern der ersten vier Jahrhunderte.” Studia Monastica 2 (1960): 5–78.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:da-lagarde-1886</IRI>
         <name>de Lagarde 1886</name>
         <name>da lagarde 1886</name>
         <desc>de Lagarde, Paul. Catenae in evangelia aegyptiacae quae supersunt Pauli de Lagarde studio et sumptibus edita. Gottingae: A. Hoyer, 1886. google.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-7013-0762-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dahme-1989</IRI>
         <name>Dahme, Nicodemus, Makarios, and Dahme 1989-1995</name>
         <name>dahme 1989</name>
         <desc>Dahme, Klaus. Byzantinische Mystik: Ein Textbuch aus der Philokalia. Translated by Klaus Dahme. Salzburg: O. Müller, 1989–1995. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:daley-1976</IRI>
         <name>Daley 1976</name>
         <desc>Daley, Brian E. “The Origenism of Leontius of Byzantium.” The Journal of Theological Studies n.s, 27 (1976): 333–69.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:daley-1982</IRI>
         <name>Daley, Heinzer, and Schönborn 1982</name>
         <name>daley 1982</name>
         <desc>Daley, Brian E. “Apokatastasis and "Honorable Silence" in the Eschatology of Maximus the Confessor.”  In Maximus Confessor: Actes Du Symposium Sur Maxime Le Confesseur, Fribourg, 2–5 Septembre, 1980, pp. 309–39. Paradosis 27. Fribourg, Suisse: Editions universitaires, 1982. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:daley-1995</IRI>
         <name>Daley, Dorival, and Le Boulluec 1995</name>
         <name>daley 1995</name>
         <desc>Daley, Brian E. “What Did 'Origenism' Mean in the Sixth Century?.”  In Origeniana sexta: Origène et la Bible = Origen and the Bible; Actes du Colloquium Origenianum Sextum, Chantilly, 30 août-3 septembre 1993, pp. 627–38. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 118. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1995. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:daley-2016</IRI>
         <name>Daley, S.J. 2016</name>
         <name>daley 2016</name>
         <desc>Daley, S.J, Brian E. “Evagrian and Cappadocian Orthodoxy.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 14–48. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dalmais-1952</IRI>
         <name>Dalmais 1952</name>
         <desc>Dalmais, Irénée-Henri. “L'oeuvre spirituelle de Saint Maxime le Confesseur: Notes sur son développement et sa signification.” Supplément de la Vie Spirituelle 21 (1952): 216–26.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dalmais-1953a</IRI>
         <name>dalmais 1953a</name>
         <desc>Dalmais, Irénée-Henri. “La doctrine ascétique de S. Maxime le Confesseur, d'après le 'Liber asceticus'.” Irénikon 26 (1953): 17–39.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dalmais-1953b</IRI>
         <name>dalmais 1953b</name>
         <desc>Dalmais, Irénée-Henri. “Un traité de théologie contemplative: Le commentaire du Pater de S. Maxime le Confesseur.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 29 (1953): 123–59.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dalmais-1966</IRI>
         <name>Dalmais 1966</name>
         <desc>Dalmais, Irénée-Henri. “L'héritage Évagrien dans la synthèse de Saint Maxime le Confesseur.” Texte und Untersuchungen 93 (1966): 356–62.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:daniélou-1964</IRI>
         <name>Daniélou 1964</name>
         <desc>Daniélou, Jean. “[Dans] Bulletin d'Histoire des Origines Chrétiennes.” Recherches de Science Religieuse 52 (1964): 135–40.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:darling-young-2002</IRI>
         <name>Darling Young, Russell Christman, Hunter, Darling Young, and Blowers 2002</name>
         <name>darling young 2002</name>
         <desc>Darling Young, Robin. “Appropriating Genesis and Exodus in Evagrius's On Prayer.”  In In Dominico Eloquio – in Lordly Eloquence: Essays on Patristic Exegesis in Honor of Robert Louis Wilken. Edited by Angela Russell Christman, David Hunter, Robin Darling Young, and Paul M. Blowers, pp. 242–258. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 2002. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:de-aldama-1963</IRI>
         <name>de Aldama 1963</name>
         <desc>de Aldama, José Antionio. “La naissance du seigneur dans l'exégèse patristique du Ps. 21,10a.” Recherches de Science Religieuse 51 (1963): 5–29.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:de-lagarde-1887</IRI>
         <name>de Lagarde 1887</name>
         <desc>de Lagarde, Paul. Onomastica sacra. Göttingen: Horstmann, 1887. archive.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:de-vogüé-1989</IRI>
         <name>de Vogüé 1989</name>
         <desc>de Vogüé, Adalbert. “Les fragments coptes de l'Histoire Lausiaque: L'édition d'Amélineau et le manuscrit.” Orientalia 58, no. 3 (1989): 326–332.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dechow-1987a</IRI>
         <name>dechow 1987a</name>
         <desc>Dechow, Jon F. “Origen's 'Heresy': From Eustathius to Epiphanius.”  In Origeniana quarta: Die Referate des 4. Internationalen Origenskongresses (Innsbruck, 2.-6. September 1985). Innsbrucker theologische Studien 19. Innsbruck: Tyrolia-Verlag, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-86554-311-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dechow-1988</IRI>
         <name>Dechow 1988</name>
         <desc>Dechow, Jon F. Dogma and Mysticism in Early Christianity: Epiphanius of Cyprus and the Legacy of Origen. Patristic monograph series 13. Macon, Ga.: Peeters and Mercer University Press, 1988. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dechow1987b</IRI>
         <name>dechow1987b</name>
         <desc>Dechow, Jon F. “The Heresy Charges against Origen.”  In Origeniana quarta: Die Referate des 4. Internationalen Origenskongresses (Innsbruck, 2.-6. September 1985). Innsbrucker theologische Studien 19. Innsbruck: Tyrolia-Verlag, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:degenhart-1915</IRI>
         <name>Degenhart 1915</name>
         <desc>Degenhart, Friedrich. Der hl. Nilus Sinaita, sein leben und seine lehre vom mönchtum. Beiträge zur geschichte des alten mönchtums und des Benediktinerordens 6. Münster in Westfalen: Aschendorff, 1915. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:degenhart-1918</IRI>
         <name>Degenhart 1918</name>
         <desc>Degenhart, Friedrich. Neue Beiträge zur Nilusforschung. Münster in Westfalen: Aschendorff, 1918. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:delcogliano-2003</IRI>
         <name>DelCogliano 2003</name>
         <desc>DelCogliano, Mark. “Situating Sarapion's Sorrow: The Anthropomorphite Controversy as the Historical and Theological Context of Cassian's Tenth Conference on Pure Prayer.” Cistercian Studies Quarterly 38, no. 4 (2003): 377–421.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:delcogliano-2011</IRI>
         <name>DelCogliano 2011</name>
         <desc>DelCogliano, Mark. “The Quest for Evagrius Ponticus: A Historiographical Essay.” American Benedictine Review 62 (2011): 388–401.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dempf-1970</IRI>
         <name>Dempf 1970</name>
         <desc>Dempf, Alois. “Evagrios Pontikos als Metaphysiker und Mystiker.” Philosophisches-Jahrbuch 77 (1970): 297–319.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:desœudres-1989</IRI>
         <name>Desœudres, Mottier, and Bosson 1989</name>
         <name>desœudres 1989</name>
         <desc>Desœudres, G. “L’architecture des ermitages et des sanctuaries.”  In Les Kellia. Ermitages coptes en Basse Égypte. Edited by Yvette Mottier and Nathalie Bosson. Genève: Editions du Tricorne, 1989. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:deville-2014</IRI>
         <name>Deville Monday, June 16, 2014</name>
         <name>deville 2014</name>
         <desc>Deville, Adam. “Eastern Christian Books: Augustine Casiday on Evagrius of Pontus.” Eastern Christian Books (Blog). [n.p.]: [n.p.], Monday, June 16, 2014. blogspot.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>http://lccn.loc.gov/ltf90006847</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:devreesse-1959</IRI>
         <name>Devreesse 1959</name>
         <desc>Devreesse, Robert. Les anciens commentateurs grecs de l'Octateuque et des Rois: [Fragments tirés des chaînes]. Studi e testi 201. Città del Vaticano: Biblioteca apostolica vaticana, 1959. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:diadochus-1627</IRI>
         <name>Diadochus, Castro Silva, Evagrius, Hesychius, Nilus, Raynaud, and de La Bottière 1627</name>
         <name>diadochus 1627</name>
         <desc>Diadochus, Castro Silva, José Vicente, Evagrius, Ponticus, Hesychius, of Jerusalem, Nilus, of Ancyra, Raynaud, Théophile, and de La Bottière, François. Sancti Diadochi episcopi Photices in vetere Epiro Illyrici capita centum de perfectione spirituali: S. Nili Capita centum quinquaginta de oratione ad Deum; Hesychii presbyteri antirrhetika kai eutika, siue Doctrina compendiaria binis capitum centuriis comprehensa, de spirituali temperantia &amp; cordis puritate, reluctando &amp; orando, comparanda. Lyon: Sumpt. Francisci de la Bottiere, in via Mercatoria, 1627. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-402-03450-6</IRI>
         <IRI>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/11058889</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:diekamp-1981</IRI>
         <name>Diekamp, Phanourgakēs, and Chrysos 1981</name>
         <name>diekamp 1981</name>
         <desc>Diekamp, Franz, Phanourgakēs, Vasileios D, and Chrysos, Euangelos K. Doctrina patrum de incarnatione verbi: Ein griechisches Florilegium aus der Wende des 7. und 8. Jahrhunderts. Münster in Westfalen: Aschendorff, 1981. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3825885569</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:diem-2005</IRI>
         <name>Diem 2005</name>
         <desc>Diem, Albrecht. Das monastische Experiment: Die Rolle der Keuschheit bei der Entstehung des westlichen Klosterwesens. Vita regularis. Abhandlungen 24. Münster: Lit, 2005. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:draguet-1946</IRI>
         <name>Draguet 1946-1947</name>
         <name>draguet 1946</name>
         <desc>Draguet, René. “L'Histoire Lausiaque; une oeuvre écrite dans l'esprit d'Évagre.” Revue d'Histoire Ecclésiastique 41, 42 (1946–1947): 321–64; 5–49.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:draguet-1957</IRI>
         <name>Draguet 1957</name>
         <desc>Draguet, René. “Un morceau grec inédit des vies de Pachôme apparié à un texte d'Évagre en partie inconnu.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 70 (1957): 267–306.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:drioton-1915</IRI>
         <name>Drioton 1915-1917</name>
         <name>drioton 1915</name>
         <desc>Drioton, Etienne. “La discussion d'un moine antropomorphite audien avec le Patriarche Théophile d'Alexandre en l'année 399.” Revue de L'Orient Chrétien 2e ser. 10 (= 20) (1915–1917): 92–100, 113–28.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1989</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll 1989</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “Listlessness in The Mirror for Monks of Evagrius Ponticus.” Cistercian Studies 24 (1989): 206–14.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1990a</IRI>
         <name>driscoll 1990a</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “A Key for Reading the Ad Monachos of Evagrius Ponticus.” Augustinianum 30 (1990): 361–92.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1990b</IRI>
         <name>driscoll 1990b</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “Gentleness in the Ad Monachos of Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Monastica 32 (1990): 295–321.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1991</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll and Evagrius 1991</name>
         <name>driscoll 1991</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy and Evagrius, Ponticus. The "Ad monachos" of Evagrius Ponticus: Its Structure and a Select Commentary. Studia Anselmiana 104. Rome: Abbazia S. Paolo, 1991. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1994a</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll 1994</name>
         <name>driscoll 1994a</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “Penthos and Tears in Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Monastica 36, no. 2 (1994): 147–63.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1994b</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll and Sheridan 1994</name>
         <name>driscoll 1994b</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “Spiritual Progress in the Works of Evagrius Ponticus.”  In Spiritual Progress: Studies in the Spirituality of Late Antiquity and Early Monasticism; Papers of the Symposium of the Monastic Institute, Rome, Pontificio Ateneo S. Anselmo, 14–15 May 1992, pp. 47–84. Studia Anselmiana 115. Rome: Pontificio Ateneo S. Anselmo, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1996</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll 1996</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “Spousal Images in Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Monastica 38, no. 2 (1996): 243–56.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1997a</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll 1997</name>
         <name>driscoll 1997a</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “Evagrius and Paphnutius on Causes for Abandonment by God.” Studia Monastica 39, no. 2 (1997): 259–86.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-1997b</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll, Luckman, and Kulzer 1999</name>
         <name>driscoll 1997b</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “Apatheia and Purity of Heart in Evagrius Ponticus.”  In Purity of Heart in Early Ascetic and Monastic Literature: Essays in Honor of Juana Raasch, O.S.B., pp. 141–159. Collegeville, Minn.: Liturgical Press, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-2000</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll 2000</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “The Fathers of Poemen and the Evagrian Connection.” Studia Monastica 42 (2000): 27–51.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-2001</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll 2001</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “'Love of Money' in Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Monastica 43 (2001): 21–30.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-2003</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll 2003</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. “The "Circle of Evagrius": Then and Now.” Studia Monastica 45 (2003): 7–18.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0809142643</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:driscoll-2005</IRI>
         <name>Driscoll 2005</name>
         <desc>Driscoll, Jeremy. Steps to Spiritual Perfection: Studies on Spiritual Progress in Evagrius Ponticus. New York: Newman Press, 2005. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:drottz-nykvist-2009</IRI>
         <name>Drottz Nykvist 2009</name>
         <desc>Drottz Nykvist, Martin. “En kristen buddhist i öknen? En studie av buddhistiska element i Evagrius Ponticus teologi.” thesis. Högskolan Dalarna, Institutionen för Akademin Humaniora och medier, 2009. diva-portal.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dräseke-1894</IRI>
         <name>Dräseke 1894</name>
         <desc>Dräseke, Johannes. “Zu Evagrios Pontikos.” Zeitschrift für wissenschaftliche Theologie 37 (1894): 125–37.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:drączkowski-1996</IRI>
         <name>Drączkowski and Palucki 1996</name>
         <name>drączkowski 1996</name>
         <desc>Drączkowski, Franciszek and Palucki, Jerzy. “Sticki ideal zgodnosci z natura w nauce Ewagriusza z Pontu [The Stoic ideal of harmony with nature in Evagrius Ponticus teaching].”  In Godnosc chrzescijanina w nauczaniu ojców kosciola, pp. 115–136. Lublin: Polihymnia, 1996. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:durand-1976</IRI>
         <name>Durand 1976</name>
         <desc>Durand, Georges-Matthieu de. “Évagre le Pontique et le Dialogue Sur la Vie de Saint Jean Chrysostome.” Bulletin de Littérature Ecclésiastique 77 (1976): 191–206.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dysinger-1990</IRI>
         <name>Dysinger 1990</name>
         <desc>Luke Dysinger, “St. Evagrius Ponticus (345-399),” Monastic Spirituality Self-Study, 1990, http://www.ldysinger.com/Evagrius/00a_start.htm.</desc>
         <location href="http://www.ldysinger.com/Evagrius/00a_start.htm" accessed-when="2020-10-02"/>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dysinger-1997</IRI>
         <name>Dysinger 1997</name>
         <desc>Dysinger, Luke. “The Significance of Psalmody in the Mystical Theology of Evagrius of Pontus.” Studia Patristica 30 (1997): 176–182.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dysinger-1999</IRI>
         <name>Dysinger 1999</name>
         <desc>Dysinger, Luke. “The Relationship between Psalmody and Prayer in the Writings of Evagrius Ponticus.” PhD dissertation. Oxford University, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0199273200</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dysinger-2005</IRI>
         <name>Dysinger 2005</name>
         <desc>Dysinger, Luke. Psalmody and Prayer in the Writings of Evagrius Ponticus. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2005. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dysinger-2010</IRI>
         <name>Dysinger 2010</name>
         <desc>Dysinger, Luke. “Exegesis and Spiritual Guidance in Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Patristica 47 (2010): 209–222.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dysinger-2013</IRI>
         <name>Dysinger 2013</name>
         <desc>Dysinger, Luke. “An Exegetical Way of Seeing: Contemplation and Spiritual Guidance in Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Patristica 57 (2013): 31–50.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:dysinger-2016</IRI>
         <name>Dysinger OSB 2016</name>
         <name>dysinger 2016</name>
         <desc>Dysinger OSB, Luke. “Evagrius Ponticus, Exegete of the Soul.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 73–95. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ekman-2011</IRI>
         <name>Ekman 2011</name>
         <desc>Ekman, Benjamin. “On the Texture of an Invisible God: Biblical Exegesis and Imageless Prayer in Evagrius Ponticus.” MPhil. University of Wales, 2011. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:elm-1990</IRI>
         <name>Elm 1990</name>
         <desc>Elm, Susanna K. “The Sententiae ad virginem by Evagrius Ponticus and the Problem of Early Monastic Rules.” Augustinianum 30 (1990): 393–404.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:elm-1991</IRI>
         <name>Elm 1991</name>
         <desc>Elm, Susanna K. “Evagrius Ponticus' Sententiae ad virginem.” Dumbarton Oaks Papers 45 (1991): 97–120.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0198149204</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:elm-1994</IRI>
         <name>Elm 1994</name>
         <desc>Elm, Susanna. Virgins of God: The Making of Asceticism in Late Antiquity. Oxford classical monographs. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:elm-1997</IRI>
         <name>Elm 1997</name>
         <desc>Elm, Susanna K. “The Polemical Use of Genealogies: Jerome's Classification of Pelagius and Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Patristica 33 (1997): 311–318.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:engelmann-2013</IRI>
         <name>Engelmann 2013</name>
         <desc>Engelmann, Till. “Kommentar zu den Kephalaia des Euagrios Pontikos.”  In Annahme Christi und Gottesschau: Die Theologie Babais des Großen. [n.p.]: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:erasmus-1532</IRI>
         <name>Basil of Caesarea and Erasmus 1532</name>
         <name>erasmus 1532</name>
         <desc>Basil of Caesarea. En amice lector, Thesaurum damus inaestimabilem D. Basilium uere Magnum sua lingua disertissime loquentem quem hactenus habuisti Latine balbutientem: unum hunc dedit nobis Graecia numeris omnibus absolutum, siue pietatem animi spectes, siue sacrae pariter ac prophanae philosophi[a]e peritiam, siue diuinitus afflatam eloquentiam : mihi crede, reddet te tibi meliorem, quisquis hunc familiarem habere uoles. [n.p.]: Ex officina Frobeniana, 1532. handle.net</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:eusebius-1570</IRI>
         <name>Eusebius of Caesarea, Rufinus of Aquileia, Socrates Scholasticus, Theodore Lector, Theodoret of Cyrrhus, Sozomen, Evagrius Ponticus, Dorotheus of Gaza, and Grynaeus 1570</name>
         <name>eusebius 1570</name>
         <desc>Eusebius of Caesarea, Rufinus of Aquileia, Socrates Scholasticus, Theodore Lector, Theodoret of Cyrrhus, Sozomen, Evagrius Ponticus, and Dorotheus of Gaza. Eusebii Pamphili, Ruffini, Socratis, Theodoriti, Sozomeni, Theodori, Evagrii, et Dorothei Ecclesiastica historia: Sex propè seculorum res gestas complectens; Latinè iam olim à doctissimis uiris partim scripta, partim è Graeco eleganter conuersa; Et nunc ex fide Graecorum codicum... Basileae: Ex officina Eusebii Episcopii, &amp; Nic. Fratris Haeredum, 1570. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:eusebius-1611</IRI>
         <name>Eusebius of Caesarea, Rufinus of Aquileia, Socrates Scholasticus, Theodoret of Cyrrhus, Sozomen, Evagrius Ponticus, Theodore Lector, Dorotheus of Gaza, Bucholtzer, and Grynaeus 1611</name>
         <name>eusebius 1611</name>
         <desc>Eusebius of Caesarea, Rufinus of Aquileia, Socrates Scholasticus, Theodoret of Cyrrhus, Sozomen, Evagrius Ponticus, Theodore Lector, Dorotheus of Gaza, and Bucholtzer, Abraham. Eusebii Pamphili, Ruffini, Socratis, Theodoriti, Sozomeni, Evagrii et Dorothei Ecclesiastica historia : sex propè seculorum res gestas complectens: Latinè iam olim à doctissimis viris partim scripta, partim è Græco à clarissimis viris, Vuolfgango Muscolo, Ioachimo Camerario &amp; Iohanne Christophersono Britanno, eleganter conuersa: Et nunc ex fide Græcorum codicum .. per Ioan. Basileae: Per S. Henricpetri, 1611. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-1750</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus 1750</name>
         <name>evagrius 1750</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Girkʻ utʻn khorhrdotsʻ meghats. Constantinople: I Tparani Atsaturi, 1750. hathitrust.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-1925</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus 1925</name>
         <name>evagrius 1925</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. “Traité de la prière De Oratione.” La Vie Spirituelle 12 (1925): 472–97.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-1965</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Diadochus 1965</name>
         <name>evagrius 1965</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Diadochus. In geest en Waarheid. Levensbronnen. Brugge [etc.]: Desclée de Brouwer, 1965. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-1994</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus 1994</name>
         <name>evagrius 1994</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. “Un écrit ascétique d'Évagre le Pontique ['Institutio seu paraenesis ad monachos' ('Recensio breuior')].” La Vie Spirituelle 148 (1994): 389–93.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-87868-238-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bamberger-1986</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Bamberger, and Joos 1986</name>
         <name>evagrius bamberger 1986</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Praktikos: Über das Gebet. Translated by John Eudes Bamberger and Guido Joos. Schriften zur Kontemplation 2. Münsterschwarzach: Vier-Türme-Verlag, 1986. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:88-85227-82-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bettiolo-1996</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Bettiolo 1996</name>
         <name>evagrius bettiolo 1996</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Per conoscere lui: Esortazione a una vergine; Ai monaci; Ragioni delle osservanze monastiche; Lettera ad Anatolio; Pratico; Gnostico. Translated by Paolo Bettiolo. Magnano Biella: Qiqajon Comunità di Bose, 1996. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780879073299</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-brakke-2009</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Brakke 2009</name>
         <name>evagrius brakke 2009</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Brakke, David. Talking Back: A Monastic Handbook for Combating Demons. Cistercian Studies Series 229. Collegeville, Minn.: Cistercian Publications, 2009. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bundy-1990</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Bundy, and Wimbush 1990</name>
         <name>evagrius bundy 1990</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. “The Kephalaia Gnostica.”  In Ascetic Behavior in Greco-Roman Antiquity: A Sourcebook. Edited by Vincent L. Wimbush, pp. 175–186. Studies in Antiquity and Christianity. Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 1990. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-7902-1410-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bunge-1986</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Bunge 1986</name>
         <name>evagrius bunge 1986</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Briefe aus der Wüste. Translated by Gabriel Bunge. Sophia 24. Trier: Paulinus-Verlag, 1986. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-922727-46-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bunge-1989</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Bunge, and Haas 1989</name>
         <name>evagrius bunge 1989</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Praktikos, oder, Der Mönch: Hundert Kapitel über das geistliche Leben. Translated by Gabriel Bunge. Schriftenreihe des Zentrums patristischer Spiritualität Kinonia-Oriens im Erzbistum Köln 32. Köln: Luthe-Verlag, 1989. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-429-01416-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bunge-1992</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Bunge 1992</name>
         <name>evagrius bunge 1992</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Bunge, Gabriel. Über die acht Gedanken. Würzburg: Echter, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bunge-1995</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Bunge, and di Meglio 1995</name>
         <name>evagrius bunge 1995</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Lettere dal Deserto: Epistulae. Translated by Gabriel Bunge and Salvatore di Meglio. Testi dei padri della chiesa 19. Magnano: Edizioni Qiqajon-Monastero di Bose, 1995. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2855893679</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bunge-1996</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Bunge, and Peternell 1996</name>
         <name>evagrius bunge 1996</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Traité pratique, ou, Le moine: Cent chapitres sur la vie spirituelle. Translated by Gabriel Bunge and Paul Peternell. Spiritualité orientale 67. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: Abbaye de Bellefontaine, 1996. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-87071-170-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-bunge-2008</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Bunge 2008</name>
         <name>evagrius bunge 2008</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Bunge, Gabriel. Der Praktikos (Der Mönch): Hundert Kapitel über das geistliche Leben. Weisungen der Väter 6. Beuron: Beuroner Kunstverlag, 2008. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0415324467</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0415324475</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0203356977</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780415324465</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780415324472</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-casiday-2006</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Casiday 2006</name>
         <name>evagrius casiday 2006</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Evagrius Ponticus. Translated by Augustine Casiday. London and New York: Routledge, 2006. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-88-311-8215-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-coco-2010</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Coco 2010</name>
         <name>evagrius coco 2010</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Sentenze; Gli otto spiriti della malvagità. Translated by Lucio Coco. Collana di Testi Patristici 215. Rome: Città nuova, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-8146-2208-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-driscoll-1993</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Driscoll 1993</name>
         <name>evagrius driscoll 1993</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. The Mind's Long Journey to the Holy Trinity: The Ad Monachos of Evagrius Ponticus. Translated by Jeremy Driscoll. Collegeville, Minn.: Liturgical Press, 1993. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0809105608</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-driscoll-2003</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Driscoll 2003</name>
         <name>evagrius driscoll 2003</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Evagrius Ponticus: Ad monachos. Translated by Jeremy Driscoll. Ancient Christian Writers 59. New York: Newman Press, 2003. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-451-30956-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-joest-2012</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Joest 2012</name>
         <name>evagrius joest 2012</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Ad monachos; Ad virginem; Institutio ad monachos = Der Mönchsspiegel; Der Nonnenspiegel; Ermahnungen an Mönche. Fontes Christiani 51. Freiburg im Breisgau: Herder, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-89680-704-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-joos-2011</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Joos 2011</name>
         <name>evagrius joos 2011</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Über das Gebet. Translated by Guido Joos. Quellen der Spiritualität 4. [n.p.]: Münsterschwarzach Vier-Türme-Verl, 2011. d-nb.info</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-jourdan-gueyer-goudet-1992</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Jourdan-Gueyer, and Goudet 1992</name>
         <name>evagrius jourdan gueyer goudet 1992</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. De la prière à la perfection: Au moine euloge. Translated by Marie Ange Jourdan-Gueyer and Marie-Odile Goudet. Les Pères dans la Foi 47. Paris: Migne, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-9972-212-44-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-lazzeri-egrejas-2010</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Lazzeri, and Egrejas 2010</name>
         <name>evagrius lazzeri egrejas 2010</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Contra los pensamientos malignos: Antirrhetikos. Translated by Valerio Lazzeri and Júlio Egrejas. Lima: Vida y Espiritualidad, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:88-311-3117-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-messana-1994</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Messana 1994</name>
         <name>evagrius messana 1994</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. La preghiera. Translated by Vincenzo Messana. Collana di Testi Patristici 117. Rome: Città nuova, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:88-215-3279-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-moscatelli-1996</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Moscatelli 1996</name>
         <name>evagrius moscatelli 1996</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Gli otto spiriti della malvagità; Sui diversi pensieri della malvagità. Translated by Francesca Moscatelli. Cinisello Balsamo Milano: Editioni San Paolo, 1996. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:960-315-456-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-moutsoulas-2000</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Moutsoulas, Kallinterēs, and Kounavē 2000</name>
         <name>evagrius moutsoulas 2000</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Euagrios Pontikos (Meros 2). Translated by Ēlias D. Moutsoulas. Βιβλιοθήκη Ἑλλήνων Πατέρων καὶ Ἐκκλησιαστικῶν Συγγράφεων 79. Athens: Αποστολική Διακονία της Εκκλησίας της Ελλάδος, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:960-315-465-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-moutsoulas-2001</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Moutsoulas, Kallinterēs, and Kounavē 2001</name>
         <name>evagrius moutsoulas 2001</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Euagrios Pontikos (Meros 3). Translated by Ēlias D. Moutsoulas. Βιβλιοθήκη Ἑλλήνων Πατέρων καὶ Ἐκκλησιαστικῶν Συγγράφεων 80. Athens: Αποστολική Διακονία της Εκκλησίας της Ελλάδος, 2001. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:960-315-479-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-moutsoulas-2002</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Moutsoulas, Kallinterēs, and Kounavē 2002</name>
         <name>evagrius moutsoulas 2002</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Euagrios Pontikos (Meros 1). Translated by Ēlias D. Moutsoulas. Βιβλιοθήκη Ἑλλήνων Πατέρων καὶ Ἐκκλησιαστικῶν Συγγράφεων 78. Athens: Αποστολική Διακονία της Εκκλησίας της Ελλάδος, 2002. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-1-291-01733-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-nau-2012</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Nau 2012</name>
         <name>evagrius nau 2012</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Nau, Sr. Pascale-Dominique. Evagrius Ponticus' Chapters on Prayer: Introduction, English Translation and Notes. Rome: [n.p.], 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:83-87525-18-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-nieścior-1998</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Nieścior, and Bielawski 1998–2005</name>
         <name>evagrius nieścior 1998</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Ewagriusz z Pontu: Pisma ascetyczne. Translated by Leon Nieścior and Krzysztof Bielawski. Zródla Monastyczne 18. Kraków: Tyniec - Wydawnictwo Benedyktynów, 1998–2005. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2226060898</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0755-1835</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-ponticus-1992</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Leloup, Guillaumont, and Guill 1992</name>
         <name>evagrius ponticus 1992</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus, Antoine. Praxis et gnosis d'Evagre le Pontique, ou, La guérison de l'esprit; Textes choisis. Translated by Antoine Guillaumont and Claire Guill. Spiritualités vivantes 102. Paris: A. Michel, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:84-86987-84-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-rubio-sadia-1995</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Rubio Sadia, and Gonzáles Villanueva 1995</name>
         <name>evagrius rubio sadia 1995</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Tratrado Práctico, A los monjes, Exhortacióna una virgen, Sobre la oración. Translated by Juan Pablo Rubio Sadia. Biblioteca de patristica 28. Madrid: Ciudad Nueva, 1995. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9783896807069</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-ruppert-iesele-2012</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Ruppert, and Eisele 2012</name>
         <name>evagrius ruppert iesele 2012</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Worte an die Mönche; Worte an eine Jungfrau = Sententiae ad monachos; Sententiae ad virginem. Translated by Fidelis Ruppert and Wilfried Eisele. Quellen der Spiritualität 6. Münsterschwarzach: Vier-Türme-Verlag, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:5-7248-0014-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-sidorov-1994</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Сидоров 1994</name>
         <name>evagrius sidorov 1994</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Творения Аввы Евагрия: Аскетические и богословские трактаты. Translated by А. И. Сидоров. Moscow: Martis, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-19-925993-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-sinkewicz-2003</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Sinkewicz 2003</name>
         <name>evagrius sinkewicz 2003</name>
         <name>sinkewicz 2003</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Evagrius of Pontus: The Greek Ascetic Corpus. Translated by Robert E. Sinkewicz. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2003. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-tesserae-2010</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus n.d.</name>
         <name>evagrius tesserae 2010</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. “Tesserae—Evagrius Ponticus: Antirrhetikos.” [n.p.]: [n.p.], n.d. tesserae.de</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-89680-701-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-trunk-2010</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Trunk 2010</name>
         <name>evagrius trunk 2010</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Die grosse Widerrede. Translated by Leo Trunk. Quellen der Spiritualität 1. Münsterschwarzach: Vier-Türme-Verl, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-tugwell-1987</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Tugwell 1987</name>
         <name>evagrius tugwell 1987</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Praktikos and On Prayer. Translated by Simon Tugwell. Oxford: Faculty of Theology, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-vitestam-1964</IRI>
         <name>Vitestam 1964</name>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Vitestam 1964</name>
         <name>evagrius vitestam 1964</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Vitestam, Gösta. Seconde partie du traité, qui passe sous le nom de "La grande lettre d'Évagre le Pontique à Mélanie l'Ancienne". Scripta minora regiae societatis humaniorum litterarum Lundensis 3. Lund: Gleerup, 1964. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:90-71837-03-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-wagenaar-1987</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Wagenaar 1987</name>
         <name>evagrius wagenaar 1987</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Geestelijke Geschriften. Translated by Christofoor Wagenaar. Monastieke cahiers 34–35. Bonheiden: Abdij Bethlehem, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evagrius-wimbush-1990</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Wimbush, and O'Laughlin 1990</name>
         <name>evagrius wimbush 1990</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. “Antirrheticus (Selections).”  In Ascetic Behavior in Greco-Roman Antiquity: A Sourcebook. Edited by Vincent L. Wimbush, pp. 243–262. Studies in Antiquity and Christianity. Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 1990. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:evans-1970</IRI>
         <name>Evans 1970</name>
         <desc>Evans, David Beecher. Leontius of Byzantium: An Origenist Christology.. Dumbarton Oaks Studies 13. Washington, D.C.: Dumbarton Oaks, 1970. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2503503004</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:fedwick-1993</IRI>
         <name>Fedwick 1993-2004</name>
         <name>fedwick 1993</name>
         <desc>Fedwick, Paul Jonathan. Bibliotheca Basiliana universalis: A Study of the Manuscript Tradition of the Works of Basil of Caesarea. Corpus Christianorum. Turnhout: Brepols, 1993–2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0815330723</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ferguson-1999</IRI>
         <name>Ferguson 1999</name>
         <desc>Ferguson, Everett. Forms of Devotion: Conversion, Worship, Spirituality, and Asceticism. Recent Studies in Early Christianity 5. New York: Garland, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:festugière-lucchesi-ssaffrey-1984</IRI>
         <name>Festugière, Lucchesi, and Saffrey 1984</name>
         <name>festugière lucchesi ssaffrey 1984</name>
         <desc>Festugière, A. J, Lucchesi, Enzo, and Saffrey, H. D. “Le vrai visage d'un père du désert ou Abba Jean Colobos à travers ses apophtegmes.”  In Mémorial André-Jean Festugière: Antiquité païenne et chrétienne; Vingt-cinq études, pp. 225–234. Cahiers d'orientalisme 10. Genève: P. Cramer, 1984. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:fiori-2009</IRI>
         <name>Fiori 2009</name>
         <desc>Fiori, Emiliano. “"È lui che mi ha donato la conoscenza senza menzogna" (Sap 7,17): Origene, Evagrio, Dionigi e la figura del maestro nel Discorso sulla vita spirituale di Sergio di Rešٔ aynā.” Adamantius 15 (2009): 43–59.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:flipo-1993</IRI>
         <name>Flipo 1993</name>
         <desc>Flipo, Claude. “L'acédie dans la tradition spirituelle.” Christus 40 (1993): 51–61.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:florovsky-1960</IRI>
         <name>Florovsky, Dölger, and Beck 1960</name>
         <name>florovsky 1960</name>
         <desc>Florovsky, Georges. “The Anthropomorphites in the Egyptian Desert.”  In Akten des XI. internationalen Byzantinistenkongresses, München, 1958, pp. 154–159. Munich: C. H. Beck, 1960. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:florovsky-1965</IRI>
         <name>Florovsky 1965</name>
         <desc>Florovsky, Georges. “Theophilus of Alexandria and Apa Aphou of Pemdje.”  In Harry Austryn Wolfson: Jubilee Volume on the Occasion of His Seventy-fifth Birthday, pp. 275–310. Jerusalem: [n.p.], 1965. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:fogielman-2015</IRI>
         <name>Fogielman 2015</name>
         <desc>Fogielman, Charles-Antoine. “Les deux traités à Euloge d'Evagre le Pontique: Introduction, édition critique, traduction, commentaire et notes.” PhD diss. École pratique des hautes études, 2015. scribd.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-204-12617-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:fogielman-2018</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Fogielman 2017</name>
         <name>fogielman 2018</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. A Euloge: Les vices opposés aux vertus. Sources Chrétiennes 591. Paris: Les Éditions du Cerf, 2017. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:88-05-03731-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:forlin-patrucco-1983</IRI>
         <IRI>http://lccn.loc.gov/84168256</IRI>
         <name>Basil of Caesarea, Forlin Patrucco, and Gribomont 1983-</name>
         <name>forlin patrucco 1983</name>
         <name>Gribomont 1983</name>
         <desc>Basil of Caesarea and Forlin Patrucco, Marcella. Le lettere. Corona Patrum 11. Torino: Società editrice internazionale, 1983–. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/4013565</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:frankenberg-1912</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:external_Evagrius_syr_Frankenberg</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Frankenberg 1912</name>
         <name>frankenberg 1912</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Euagrius Ponticus. Abhandlungen der Königlichen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen. Philologisch-Historische Klasse, n.F. 13, no. 2. Berlin: Weidmannsche Buchhandlung, 1912. archive.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:frankenberg-1940</IRI>
         <name>Frankenberg 1940</name>
         <desc>Frankenberg, W. “Fragment Armenien du Ad virgines d'Évagre.” Le Muséon 53 (1940): 77–87.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:88-210-0702-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:furrer-pilliod-2000</IRI>
         <name>Furrer-Pilliod 2000</name>
         <desc>Furrer-Pilliod, Christiane. Oroi kai ypographai: Collections alphabétiques de définitions profanes et sacrées. Studi e testi (Biblioteca apostolica vaticana) 395. Città del Vaticano: Biblioteca apostolica Vaticana, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gallandi-1765</IRI>
         <name>Gallandi 1765</name>
         <desc>Gallandi, Andreas. Bibliotheca veterum patrum atiquorumque scriptorum ecclesiasticorum, postrema Lugdunensi longe locupletior atque accuratior. Venice: J.B. Albritii Hieron fil, 1765.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:garitte-1956</IRI>
         <name>Garitte 1956</name>
         <desc>Garitte, Gérard. Catalogue des manuscrits géorgiens littéraires du Mont Sinaï. Corpus scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 165 (Subsidia 9). Louvain: L. Durbecq, 1956. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:garzya-1988</IRI>
         <name>Garzya 1988</name>
         <desc>Garzya, Antonio. “Osservazioni su un'epistola di Evagrio Pontico.”  In Mémorial Dom Jean Gribomont (1920–1986), pp. 299–305. Studia Ephemeridis "Augustinianum" 27. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 1988. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-503-05061-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:geerard-glorie-1974</IRI>
         <name>Geerard and Glorie 1974-</name>
         <name>geerard glorie 1974</name>
         <desc>Geerard, Maurice and Glorie, François. Clavis Patrum Graecorum. Corpus Christianorum. Turnhout: Brepols, 1974–. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gendle-1985</IRI>
         <name>Gendle 1985</name>
         <desc>Gendle, Nicholas. “Cappadocian Elements in the Mystical Theology of Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Patristica 16.2 (1985): 373–84.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gianfrancesco-2008</IRI>
         <name>Gianfrancesco January-March 2008</name>
         <name>gianfrancesco 2008</name>
         <desc>Gianfrancesco, Angelo. “Monachisme ancien et psychopathologie.” L'Évolution Psychiatrique 73, no. 1 (January-March 2008): 105–126.over-blog.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gibbons-2011</IRI>
         <name>Gibbons 2011</name>
         <desc>Gibbons, Kathleen. “Vice and Self Examination in the Christian Desert: An Intellectual Historical Reading of Evagrius Ponticus.” thesis. University of Toronto, 2011. utoronto.ca</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gibbons-2015</IRI>
         <name>Gibbons October 2015</name>
         <name>gibbons 2015</name>
         <desc>Gibbons, Kathleen. “Passions, Pleasures, and Perceptions: Rethinking Evagrius Ponticus on Mental Representation.” “”  (October 2015): 297–330.degruyter.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-0-7618-5169-1</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-7618-5169-0</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gilette-2010</IRI>
         <name>Gillette 2010</name>
         <name>gilette 2010</name>
         <desc>Gillette, Gertrude. Four Faces of Anger: Seneca, Evagrius Ponticus, Cassian, and Augustine. Lanham, MD: University Press of America, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:giulea-2007</IRI>
         <name>Giulea 2007</name>
         <desc>Giulea, Dragos-Andrei. “The Watchers' Whispers: Athenagoras's Legatio 25, 1–3 and the &lt;i&gt;Book of the Watchers&lt;/I&gt;.” Vigiliae Christianae 61, no. 3 (2007): 258–81.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:glotobdky-1962</IRI>
         <name>Glotobdky 1962-1968</name>
         <name>glotobdky 1962</name>
         <desc>Glotobdky, Hrothrd. “Εὐάγριος ὁ Πόντικος.”  In Θρησκευτική και ηθική ενκυκλοπαιδεία, pp. s.v. Athens: Ath. Martinos, 1962–1968. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:golitzin-2013</IRI>
         <name>Golitzin 2013</name>
         <desc>Golitzin, Alexander. “Dionysius’ Predecessors: Evagrius and Macarius.”  In Mystagogy: A Monastic Reading of Dionysius Areopagita, pp. 305–361. [n.p.]: Cistercian Publications, 2013. cistercianpublications.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gombos-2013</IRI>
         <name>Gombos 2013</name>
         <desc>Gombos, Chris S. “Divine Sovereignty, Divine Providence,and Prayer in the Thought of Evagrius Ponticus.” Ph.D. Loyola University, 2013. luc.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gouillard-1939</IRI>
         <name>Gouillard 1939</name>
         <desc>Gouillard, Jean. “Un auteur spirituel Byzantin du 12e siècle: Pierre Damascène.” Échos d'Orient 38 (1939): 257–78.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gouillard-1947</IRI>
         <name>Gouillard 1947</name>
         <desc>Gouillard, Jean. “Supercheries et méprises littéraires: L'oeuvres de Saint Théodore d'Édesse.” Revue des Études Byzantines 5 (1947): 137–57.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gouillard-1977</IRI>
         <name>Gouillard 1977-1978</name>
         <name>gouillard 1977</name>
         <desc>Gouillard, Jean. “Contemplation et imagerie sacrée dans le Christianisme Byzantin.” Annuaire de l'école pratique des hautes études, Ve section, Sciences Religieuses 86 (1977–1978): 27–50.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gould-1992</IRI>
         <name>Gould and Daly 1992</name>
         <name>gould 1992</name>
         <desc>Gould, Graham. “The Image of God and the Anthropomorphite Controversy in Fourth Century Monasticism.”  In Origeniana quinta: Historica, Text and Method, Biblica, Philosophica, Theologica, Origenism and Later developments: Papers of the 5th International Origen Congress, Boston College, 14–18 August 1989, pp. 549–57. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 105. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gould-1997</IRI>
         <name>Gould 1997</name>
         <desc>Gould, Graham. “An Ancient Monastic Writing Giving Advice to Spiritual Directors (Evagrius of Pontus, On Teachers and Disciples).” Hallel 22 (1997): 96–103.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:graf-1944</IRI>
         <name>Graf 1944-1953</name>
         <name>graf 1944</name>
         <desc>Graf, Georg. Geschichte der Christlichen Arabischen Literatur. Studi e testi 118, 133, 146–147, 172. [n.p.]: Città del Vaticano, Biblioteca apostolica vaticana, 1944–1953. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:graiver-2018</IRI>
         <name>Graiver 2018</name>
         <desc>Graiver, Inbar. “Possible Selves in Late Antiquity: Ideal Selfhood and Embodied Selves in Evagrian Anthropology *.” “”  (2018): 59–89.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:elter-1892</IRI>
         <name>Elter, Evagrius Ponticus, Cleitarchus, Epictetus, and Moschion 1892</name>
         <name>elter 1892</name>
         <desc>Elter, Antonio. Gnomica. Leipzig: Teubner, 1892. google.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0790518317</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gressmann-1913</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gressmann-1913b</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Gressmann 1913</name>
         <name>gressmann 1913</name>
         <name>gressmann 1913b</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Gressmann, Hugo. Nonnenspiegel und Mönchsspiegel des Euagrios Pontikos: Zum ersten Male in der Urschrift. Texte und Untersuchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 39.4. Leipzig: J. C. Hinrichs, 1913. archive.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gribomont-1981</IRI>
         <name>Gribomont 1981</name>
         <desc>Gribomont, Jean. “Prayer in Eastern Monasticism and in St Benedict.” Word and Spirit 3 (1981): 1–22.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gribomont-1985</IRI>
         <name>Gribomont, McGinn, Meyendorff, and Leclercq 1985</name>
         <name>gribomont 1985</name>
         <desc>Gribomont, Jean. “Eastern Christianity: Monasticism and Asceticism.”  In Christian Spirituality: Origins to the Twelfth Century, pp. 89–112. World Spirituality 16. New York: Crossroad, 1985. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:gribomont-1987</IRI>
         <name>Gribomont 1987</name>
         <desc>Gribomont, Jean. “L'édition romaine (1673) des Tractatus de S. Nil et l'Ottobonianus gr. 25.” Texte und Untersuchungen 133 (1987): 187–202.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:griffin-1926</IRI>
         <name>Griffin 1926</name>
         <desc>Griffin, R. Liber graduum. Patrologia syriaca 3. Paris: Firmin-Didot et socii, 1926. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:grillmeier-1981</IRI>
         <name>Grillmeier, Treu, Paschke, Dummer, and Irmscher 1981</name>
         <name>grillmeier 1981</name>
         <desc>Grillmeier, Alois. “Markos Eremites und der Origenismus: Versuch cr Neudeutung von Op[usculum] XI.”  In Überlieferungsgeschichtliche Untersuchungen, pp. 253–284. Texte und Untersuchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 125. Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 1981. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:grossi-1986</IRI>
         <name>Grossi 1986</name>
         <desc>Grossi, Vittorino. “A proposito della presenza di Origene in 'praedestinatus': Il Cristianesimo Latino del sec. V tra Origene e Agostino.” Augustinianum 26 (1986): 229–40.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:grébaut-1913a</IRI>
         <name>grébaut 1913a</name>
         <desc>Grébaut, Sylvain. “Exhortations aux anachorètes.” Revue de l'Orient Chrétien 18 (1913): 317–25.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:grébaut-1913b</IRI>
         <name>grébaut 1913b</name>
         <desc>Grébaut, Sylvain. “La mauvaise passion de la colère selon Évagrius.” Revue de l'Orient Chrétien 18 (1913): 213–25.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:grébaut-1913c</IRI>
         <name>Grébaut 1913-1921</name>
         <name>grébaut 1913c</name>
         <desc>Grébaut, Sylvain. “Sentences ascétiques.” Revue de l'Orient Chrétien 18, 20, 22 (1913–1921): 423–27; 207–9; 443–47.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:grébaut-1914</IRI>
         <name>Grébaut 1914</name>
         <desc>Grébaut, Sylvain. “Les manuscrits éthiopiens de M.E. Delorme.” Revue de l'Orient Chrétien 19 (1914): 174–82.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:grébaut-1915</IRI>
         <name>Grébaut 1915-1921</name>
         <name>grébaut 1915</name>
         <desc>Grébaut, Sylvain. “Sentences d'Évagre.” Revue de l'Orient Chrétien 20, 22 (1915–1921): 211–14, 435–39; 206–11.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-89680-821-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:grün-2013</IRI>
         <name>Grün 2013</name>
         <desc>Grün, Anselm. Die spirituelle Hausapotheke: Für alle Fälle. Münsterschwarzach: Vier Türme; Katholisches Bibelwerk, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1950</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont, Guillaumont, and Klauser 1950-</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1950</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine and Guillaumont, Claire. “Evagrius Pontikos: Persönlichkeit, Leben, Wirkung.”  In Reallexikon für Antike und Christentum: Sachwörterbuch zur Auseinandersetzung des Christentums mit der antiken Welt, pp. 1088–1107. Stuttgart: Hiersemann, 1950–. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1951</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1951-1952</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1951</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Le texte syriaque édité des Six Centuries d'Évagre le Pontique.” Semitica 4 (1951–1952): 59–66.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1952</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont and Guillaumont 1952</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1952</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine and Guillaumont, Claire. “Le texte véritable des Gnostica d'Évagre le Pontique.” Revue de l'Histoire des Religions 142 (1952): 156–205.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>http://lccn.loc.gov/a68000023</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1958</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1958</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. Les six centuries des “Kephalaia gnostica”: Édition critique de
             la version syriaque commune et édition d’une nouvelle version syriaque, intégrale, avec
             une double traduction française; Kephalaia gnostica. Patrologia Orientalis 28. Paris:
             Firmin-Didot, 1958. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1958b</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1958b</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Sources de la doctrine de Joseph Hazzâyâ.” L'Orient Syrien 3 (1958): 3–24.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1961</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1961</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Évagre et les anathémismes antiorigénistes de 553.” Studia Patristica 3 (1961): 219–226.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1962</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1962</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. Les "Képhalaia gnostica" d'Évagre le Pontique et l'histoire de l'origénisme chez les Grecs et chez les Syriens. Publications de la Sorbonne série patristica Sorbonensia 5. Paris: Éditions du Seuil, 1962. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1964</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1964</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “De l'eschatologie à la mystique: histoire d'une sentence d'Évagre.”  In Mémorial du cinquantenaire, 1914–1964., pp. 187–192. Travaux de l'Institut catholique de Paris 10. Paris: Bloud &amp; Gay, 1964. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1968a</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1968-1969</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1968a</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Le dépaysement comme forme d'ascèse dans le monachisme ancien.” Annuaire de l'école pratique des hautes études, Ve section, Sciences Religieuses 76 (1968–1969): 31–58.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1968b</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1968</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1968b</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Une inscription Copte sur la 'Prière de Jésus'.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 34 (1968): 310–25.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1971</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont and Guillaumont 1971</name>
         <name>Guillaumonts 1971</name>
         <name>Guillaumont 1971</name>
         <name>Traité pratique, ou, Le moine</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus, Claire Guillaumont, and Antoine Guillaumont, Traité Pratique,
             Ou, Le Moine, 2 vols., Sources Chrétiennes 170–171 (Paris: Éditions du Cerf,
             1971).</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1972</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1972</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Un philosophe au désert: Évagre le Pontique.” Revue de l'Histoire des Religions 181 (1972): 29–56.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1974a</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1974a</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Jesus Prayer among the Monks of Egypt.” Eastern Churches Review 6 (1974): 66–71.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1974c</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1974c</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “La prière de Jésus chez les moines d'Égypte.” Eastern Churches Review 6 (1974): 66–71.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1975a</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1975a</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Conception du désert chez les moines d'Egypte.” Revue de l'Histoire des Religions 188 (1975): 3–21.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1975b</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1975-1976</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1975b</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Fragments syriaques des Disciples d'Évagre.” Parole de l'Orient 6–7 (1975–1976): 115–23.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1975c</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1975c</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Le problème des deux Macaire dans les Apophthegmata patrum.” Irénikon 48 (1975): 41–59.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1977a</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont, Balz, Krause, and Müller 1977-</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1977a</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Evagrius Ponticus: Leben, Werk, Nachwirkung, Quellen/Literatur.”  In Theologische Realenzyklopädie, pp. 565–570. Berlin: de Gruyter, 1977–. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1977b</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1977b</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Histoire des moines aux Kellia.” Orientalia Lovaniensia Periodica 8 (1977): 187–203.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1977c</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1977-1978</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1977c</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Les fondements de la vie monastique selon Évagre le Pontique.” Annuaire du Collège de France 78 (1977–1978): 467–77.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1977d</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1977d</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Les visions mystiques dans la monachisme oriental Chrétien.”  In Colloque sur les visions mystiques: [a L'occasion Du] 3e centenaire des visions de Marguerite-Marie Alacoque, pp. 116–127. Nouvelles Institut Catholique de Paris 1. Paris: Institut catholique, 1977. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1978</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1978-1979</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1978</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “L'ascèse évagrienne.” Annuaire du Collège de France 79 (1978–1979): 395–99.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-85589-030-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1979</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1979</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. Aux origines du monachisme chrétien: Pour une phénoménologie du monachisme. Spiritualité orientale 30. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: Abbaye de Bellefontaine, 1979. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1979b</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1979, 1967</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1979b</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “La travail manuel dans le monachisme ancien: Contestation et valorisation.”  In Aux origines du monachisme chrétien: Pour une phénoménologie du monachisme, pp. 118–126. Spiritualité orientale 30. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: Abbaye de Bellefontaine, 1979, 1967. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1979c</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1979-1980</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1979c</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “La vie gnostique selon Évagre le Pontique.” Annuaire du Collège de France 80 (1979–1980): 467–70.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1980a</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1980a</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “[Dans] Christianismes Orientaux.” Annuaire de l'école pratique des hautes études, Ve section, Sciences Religieuses 89 (1980–1981): 471–72.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1980b</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1980b</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “La métaphysique évagrienne.” Annuaire du Collège de France 81 (1980–1981): 407–11.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1980c</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont, Limet, and Ries 1980</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1980c</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Le problème de la priere continuelle dans le monachisme ancien.”  In L'expérience de la prière dans les grandes religions: Actes du colloque de Louvain-la-Neuve et Liège (22–23 novembre 1978). Homo religiosus 5. Louvain-la-Neuve: Centre d'histoire des religions, 1980. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1982</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont, Ries, Janssens, and Sevrin 1982</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1982</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Gnose et Monachisme.”  In Gnosticisme et monde hellénistique: Actes du colloque de Louvain-la-Neuve (11–14 mars 1980). Publications de l'Institut orientaliste de Louvain 27. Louvain-la-Neuve: Université catholique de Louvain, Institut orientaliste, 1982. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1983</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1983</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Les versions syriaques de l'oeuvre d'Évagre le Pontique et leur rôle dans la formation du vocabulaire ascétique syriaque.” Orientalia Christiana Analecta 221 (1983): 35–41.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1984</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1984</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “La vision de l'intellect par lui-même dans la mystique Évagrienne.” Mélanges de l'Université Saint-Joseph 50 (1984): 255–62.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1985</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1985</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Le rôle des versions orientales dans la récupération de l'oeuvre d'Évagre le Pontique.” Comptes rendus des séances de l'Académie des inscriptions et belles-lettres 129 (1985): 64–74.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1987a</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1987a</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Le gnostique chez Clément d'Alexandrie et chez Évagre le Pontique.”  In Alexandrina: Hellénisme, judaïsme et christianisme à Alexandrie; Mélanges offerts au P. Claude Mondésert., pp. 151–160. Spiritualité orientale 66. Paris: Editions du Cerf, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1987b</IRI>
         <name>guillaumont 1987b</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. “Une nouvelle version syriaque du Gnostique d'Évagre le Pontique.” Muséon 100 (1987): 161–69.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1987c</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont, Irmscher, Paschke, Treu, and Dummer 1987</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1987c</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Claire. “Fragments grecs inédits d'Évagre le Pontique.”  In Texte und Textkritik: Eine Aufsatzsammlung, pp. 209–221. Texte und Untersuchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 133. Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1989</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1989</name>
         <name>Guillaumonts 1989</name>
         <name>SC 356</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus, Antoine Guillaumont, and Claire Guillaumont, Le Gnostique, Ou,
             A Celui Qui Est Devenu Digne de La Science, Sources Chrétiennes 356 (Paris: Éditions
             du Cerf, 1989).</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1991a</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont and Guillaumont 1991</name>
         <name>guillaumont 1991a</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine and Guillaumont, Claire. “Les versions orientales et le texte grec des Lettres d'Evagre le Pontique.”  In Langues orientales anciennes philologie et linguistique, pp. 151–162. Louvain: Peeters, 1991. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-85589-366-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-1996</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 1996</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. Études sur la spiritualité de l'Orient chrétien. Spiritualité orientale, Série Monachisme primitif 66. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: Abbaye de Bellefontaine, 1996. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-7116-1683-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:guillaumont-2004</IRI>
         <name>Guillaumont 2004</name>
         <desc>Guillaumont, Antoine. Un philosophe au désert: Évagre le Pontique. Textes et Traditions 8. Paris: Vrin, 2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1979</IRI>
         <name>Géhin 1979</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Un nouvel inédit d'Évagre le Pontique: son commentaire de l'Ecclésiaste.” Byzantion 49 (1979): 188–98.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-204-02885-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1987</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Géhin 1987</name>
         <name>SC 340</name>
         <name>géhin 1987</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Géhin, Paul. Scholies aux Proverbes. Sources chrétiennes 340. Paris: Éditions du Cerf, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1990</IRI>
         <name>Géhin 1990</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “À propos d'Évagre le Pontique.” Revue des Études Grecques 103 (1990): 263–67.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1992</IRI>
         <name>Géhin 1992</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Un recueil d'extraits patristiques: Les Miscellanea Coisliniana (Parisinus Coislinianus 193 et Sinaiticus Gr. 461).” Revue d'Histoire des Textes 22 (1992): 89–130.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-204-04873-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1993</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Géhin 1993</name>
         <name>SC 397</name>
         <name>géhin 1993</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Géhin, Paul. Scholies à l'Ecclésiaste. Sources chrétiennes 397. Paris: Éditions du Cerf, 1993. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1994</IRI>
         <name>Géhin 1994</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Nouveaux fragments grecs des lettres d'Évagre.” Revue d'Histoire des Textes 24 (1994): 117–47.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1996</IRI>
         <name>Géhin 1996</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Evagriana d'un manuscrit Basilien (Vaticanus gr. 2028; olim Basilianus 67).” Le Muséon 109 (1996): 59–85.peeters-leuven.be</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-204-06081-X</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1998</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Géhin, Guillaumont, and Guillaumont 1998</name>
         <name>SC 438</name>
         <name>géhin 1998</name>
         <name>guillaumonts and géhin 1998</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus, Géhin, Paul, Guillaumont, Claire, and Guillaumont, Antoine. Sur les pensées. Sources chrétiennes 438. Paris: Éditions du Cerf, 1998. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-1998b</IRI>
         <name>géhin 1998b</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Évagre le Pontique: Une anachorèse spirituelle vers le 'Lieu de Dieu.'.” Connaissance des Pères de l'Église 72 (1998): n.p.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2000</IRI>
         <name>Géhin and Bettiolo 2000</name>
         <name>géhin 2000</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “La place de la Lettre sur la foi dans l'oeuvre d'Evagre.”  In L'epistula fidei di Evagrio Pontico: Temi, contesti, sviluppi; Atti del III convegno del gruppo italiano di ricerca su "Origene e la tradizione alessandrina". Edited by Paolo Bettiolo, pp. 25–58. Studia Ephemeridis Augustinianum 72. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2004</IRI>
         <name>Géhin 2004</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Les développements récents de la recherche évagrienne.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 70, no. 1 (2004): 103–125.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2005a</IRI>
         <name>géhin 2005a</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Les versions syriaques et arabes des Chapitres sur la prière d'Évagre le Pontique: Quelques données nouvelles.”  In Les Syriques transmetteurs de civilisations: L'expérience du Bilâd El-Shâm à l'époque omeyyade., pp. 181–197. Actes du Colloque 9. Anṭilyās: Markaz al-Dirāsāt wa-al-Abḥāth al-Mashriqīyah, al-Jāmiʻah al-Anṭūnīyah, 2005. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2005b</IRI>
         <name>géhin 2005b</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Reconstitution et datation d’un recueil syriaque melkite (Ambr. A 296 inf, ff. 22–224 + Sinaï syr. 10).” Rivista di Studi Byzantini e Neoellenici 42 (2005): 51–68.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2006</IRI>
         <name>Géhin 2006</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “La tradition arabe d'Évagre le Pontique.” Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 3 (2006): 83–104.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-204-08468-0</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-204-08468-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2007</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Géhin 2007</name>
         <name>SC 514</name>
         <name>géhin 2007</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Géhin, Paul. Chapitres des disciples d'Évagre. Sources chrétiennes 514. Paris: Éditions du Cerf, 2007. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2009a</IRI>
         <name>géhin 2009a</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Antoine Guillaumont (1915–2000) et Claire Guillaumont (1916–2005): Cinquante ans de recherches sur le monachisme ancien et Évagre le Pontique.” Adamantius 15 (2009): 85–92.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2009b</IRI>
         <name>géhin 2009b</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Fragments patristiques syriaques des Nouvelles découvertes du Sinai.” Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 6 (2009): 67–93.uco.es</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2010a</IRI>
         <name>géhin 2010a</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “En marge de la constitution d'un repertorium Evagrianum Syriacum: Quelques remarques sur l'organisation en corpus des oeuvres d'Évagre.” Parole de l'Orient 35 (2010): 285–301.inist.fr</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2010b</IRI>
         <name>géhin 2010b</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “La dette d'Isaac de Ninive envers Évagre le Pontique.” Connaissance des Pères de l'Eglise 119 (2010): 40–52.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2011a</IRI>
         <name>Géhin and Rigo 2011</name>
         <name>géhin 2011a</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “À propos d’une expression des Chapitres sur la prière d’Évagre: 'Vis selon l’intellect'.”  In Byzantine Theology and Its Philosophical Background. Edited by Antonio Rigo, pp. 17–31. Studies in Byzantine History and Civilization 4. Turnhout: Brepols, 2011. metapress.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2011b</IRI>
         <name>Géhin, Jullien, and Pierre 2011</name>
         <name>géhin 2011b</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “D’Égypte en Mésopotamie: La réception d’Évagre le Pontique dans les communautés syriaques.”  In Monachismes d'Orient: Images, échanges, influences; hommage à Antoine Guillaumont; cinquantenaire de la chaire des "Christianismes orientaux", EPHE SR. Edited by Florence Jullien and Marie-Joseph Pierre, pp. 29–49. Bibliothèque de l'École des hautes études. Section des sciences religieuses 148. Turnhout: Brepols, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2013</IRI>
         <name>Géhin and Rigo 2013</name>
         <name>géhin 2013</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “Les collections de Kephalaia monastiques: Naissance et succès d'un genre entre création originale, plagiat et florilège.”  In The Minor Genres of Byzantine Theological Literature. Edited by Antonio Rigo, pp. 1–50. Studies in Byzantine History and Civilization 8. Turnhout: Brepols, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2016</IRI>
         <name>Géhin and Mellerin 2016</name>
         <name>géhin 2016</name>
         <desc>Géhin, Paul. “L’Ecclésiaste à l’épreuve de l’allégorie dans les scholies d’Évagre le Pontique.”  In La réception du livre de Qohélet (ier-xiiie s.). Edited by Laurence Mellerin, pp. 133–148. Patrimoines. Paris: Editions du Cerf, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-204-12207-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:géhin-2017</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Géhin 2017</name>
         <name>SC 589</name>
         <name>géhin 2017</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Chapitres sur la prière. Sources chrétiennes 589. Paris: Les Éditions du Cerf, 2017. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:göbel-2002</IRI>
         <name>Göbel 2002</name>
         <desc>Göbel, C. “Philosophie des Mönchseins: Am Beispiel des Ad Monachos des Evagrius Ponticus und seines Bezuges zum 'asketischen' Charakter der antiken Ethik.” Wissenschaft und Weisheit 65 (2002): 3–23.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:göbel-2003</IRI>
         <name>Göbel 2003</name>
         <desc>Göbel, C. “Wahrheit und Methode: Platonische Dialektik und Evagrische Seelenführung.” Teresianum 54 (2003): 231–60.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hadot-1978</IRI>
         <name>Hadot 1978-1979</name>
         <name>hadot 1978</name>
         <desc>Hadot, Pierre. “Centre d'études des religions du livre. Laboratoire associé au C.N.R.S. No 152.” Annuaire de l'école pratique des hautes études, Ve section, Sciences Religieuses 87 (1978–1979): 441–60.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3110144832</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hagedorn-hagedorn-1994</IRI>
         <name>Hagedorn and Hagedorn 1994-2004</name>
         <name>hagedorn hagedorn 1994</name>
         <desc>Hagedorn, Ursula and Hagedorn, Dieter. Die älteren griechischen Katenen zum Buch Hiob. Patristische Texte und Studien 40, 48, 53, 59. Berlin: W. de Gruyter, 1994–2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hager-2011</IRI>
         <name>Hager 2011</name>
         <desc>Hager, Kathryn. “John Cassian: The Devil in the Details.” Studia Patristica 64 (2011): 59–64.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:haidacher-1905</IRI>
         <name>Haidacher 1905</name>
         <desc>Haidacher, Sebastian. “Nilus-Exzerpte im Pandektes des Antiochus.” Revue Bénédictine 22 (1905): 244–50.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:halter-2012</IRI>
         <name>Halter 1999</name>
         <name>halter 2012</name>
         <desc>Halter, Ann. Contextualizing the Spiritual Doctrine of Evagrius of Pontus in Fourth Century Egyptian Monasticism: Determining the Source of Desert Animosity. Portland, Or.: Reed College, Religion Dept, 1999. google.ca</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hansen-1955</IRI>
         <name>Hansen 1955</name>
         <desc>Hansen, Olaf. Berliner Sogdische Texte, vol. 2, Bruchstücke der grossen Sammelhandschrift C 2. Abhandlungen der Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaftlichen Klasse 15. Mainz and Wiesbaden: Akademie der Wissenschaften und der Literatur; in Kommission bei F. Steiner, 1955. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:harb-1974</IRI>
         <name>Harb 1974</name>
         <desc>Harb, Paul. “Les origines de la doctrine de la 'La-hasusuta' (apatheia) chez Philoxène de Mabbug.” Parole de l'Orient 5 (1974): 227–41.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:harb-khouri-sarkis-1969</IRI>
         <name>Harb and Khouri-Sarkis 1969</name>
         <name>harb khouri sarkis 1969</name>
         <desc>Harb, Paul and Khouri-Sarkis, Gabriel. “L'Attitude de Philoxène de Mabboug à l'égard de la spiritualité "savante" d'Évagre le Pontique.”  In Mémorial Mgr Gabriel Khouri-Sarkis, 1898–1968, fondateur et directeur de l'Orient syrien, 1956–1967: Revue d'étude et de recherches sur les églises de langue syriaque, pp. 135–155. Louvain: Impr. orientaliste, 1969. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:harl-1971</IRI>
         <name>Harl 1971</name>
         <desc>Harl, Marguerite. “Y a-t-il une influence du "Grec biblique" sur la langue spirituelle des Chrétiens? Exemples tirés du Psaume 118 et de ses commentateurs d'Origène à Théodoret.”  In La Bible et les Pères, colloque de Strasbourg, pp. 243–262. Bibliothèque des centres d'études supérieures spécialisés; Travaux du Centre d'études supérieures spécialisé d'histoire des religions de Strasbourg. Paris: Presses universitaires de France, 1971. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:harmless-2001</IRI>
         <name>Harmless 2001</name>
         <desc>Harmless, William. “"Salt for the Impure, Light for the Pure": Reflections on the Pedagogy of Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Patristica 37 (2001): 514–526.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-19-516222-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:harmless-2004</IRI>
         <name>Harmless 2004</name>
         <desc>Harmless, William. Desert Christians: An Introduction to the Literature of Early Monasticism. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2004. loc.gov</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780195300383</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0195300386</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780195300390</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0195300394</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9781435617797</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:harmless-2008</IRI>
         <name>Harmless 2008</name>
         <desc>Harmless, William. Mystics. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2008. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:harmless-fitzgerald-2001</IRI>
         <name>Harmless and Fitzgerald 2001</name>
         <name>harmless fitzgerald 2001</name>
         <desc>Harmless, William and Fitzgerald, Raymond R. “The Sapphire Light of the Mind: The Skemmata of Evagrius Ponticus.” Theological Studies 62, no. 3 (2001): 493–529.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1831</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1831</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. Les versions syriaque et arménienne d'évagre le pontique: Leur valeur, leur relation, leur utilisation. Orientalia Christiana 69. Rome: Pont. Institutum Orientalium Studiorum, 1931. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1831b</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1831b</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Les versions syriaque et arménienne d'Évagre le Pontique, leur valeur, leur situation, leur utilisation.” Orientalia Christiana 22, no. 2 (1931): 69–118.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1932c</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1932</name>
         <name>hausherr 1932c</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Par delà l'oraison pure grâce à une coquille. À propos d'un texte d'Évagre.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 13 (1932): 184–88.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1933a</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1933a</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Contemplation et sainteté, une remarquable mise au point par Philoxène de Mabboug.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 14 (1933): 171–195.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1933b</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1933-</name>
         <name>hausherr 1933b</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. De doctrina spirituali christianorum orientalium: Questiones et scripta. Orientalia Christiana 30.3 (no. 86). Rome: Pont. Institutum Orientalium Studiorum, 1933–. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1933c</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1933c</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Evagrii Pontici tria capita de Oratione.” Orientalia Christiana 30, no. 3 (1933): 149–52.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1933d</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1933d</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Le De oratione de Nil et Évagre.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 14 (1933): 196–98.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1933e</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1933e</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “L'origine de la théorie orientale des huit péchés capitaux.” Orientalia Christiana 30, no. 3 (1933): 164–75.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1933f</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1933f</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Une énigme d'Évagre le Pontique; Centurie II, 50.” Recherches de Science Religieuse 23 (1933): 321–25.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1934</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1934</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Le Traité De l'Oraison d'Évagre le Pontique (Pseudo-Nil).” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 15 (1934): 34–93; 113–70.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1935</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1935</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Les grands courants de la spiritualité orientale.” Orientalia Christiana 11 (1935): 114–38.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1936</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1936</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Ignorance infinie.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 2 (1936): 351–62.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1938</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1938</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Aux origines de la mystique syrienne: Grégoire de Chypre ou Jean de Lycopolis?.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 4 (1938): 497–520.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1939a</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1939a</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Le De Oratione d'Évagre le Pontique en Syriaque et en Arabe.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 5 (1939): 7–71.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1939b</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1939b</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Nouveaux fragments grecs d'Évagre le Pontique.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 5 (1939): 229–33.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1940</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1940</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Eulogios - Loukios.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 6 (1940): 216–20.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1944</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1944</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. Penthos: La doctrine de la componction dans l'Orient chrétien. Orientalia Christiana analecta 132. Rome: Pont. Institutum Orientalium Studiorum, 1944. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1946</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1946</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Les orientaux connaissent-ils les Nuits de Saint Jean de la Croix?.” Orientalia Christiana 12 (1946): 5–46.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1947</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1947</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Dogme et spiritualité orientale.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 23 (1947): 3–37.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1956a</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1956a</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Comment priaient les Pères.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 32 (1956): 33–58; 284–96.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1956b</IRI>
         <name>hausherr 1956b</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “L'hésychasme: Etude de spiritualité.” Orientalia Christiana 22 (1956): 5–40; 247–85.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1959a</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1959</name>
         <name>hausherr 1959a</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Ignorance infinie ou science infinie?.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 25 (1959): 44–52.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1959b</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1959-1960</name>
         <name>hausherr 1959b</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. “Le Traité de l'Oraison d'Évagre le Pontique: Introduction, authenticité, traduction française et commentaire.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 35, 36 (1959–1960): 3–26, 121–46, 241–65, 361–85; 3–35, 137–87.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1960</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Nilus of Ancyra, and Hausherr 1960</name>
         <name>hausherr 1960</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Nilus of Ancyra. Les leçons d'un contemplatif: Le traité de l'oraison d'Évagre le Pontique. Translated by Irénée Hausherr. Paris: Beauchesne, 1960. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-87907-853-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hausherr-1982</IRI>
         <name>Hausherr 1982</name>
         <desc>Hausherr, Irénée. Penthos: The Doctrine of Compunction in the Christian East. Cistercian Studies Series 53. Kalamazoo, Mich.: Cistercian Publications, 1982. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hayden-2015</IRI>
         <name>Hayden 2015</name>
         <desc>Hayden, Evagrius. “"Wisdom Has Built Herself a Home": Evagrius Ponticus and The Wisdom of Creation.” Master's Thesis. International Theological Institute, 2015. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:heussi-1917</IRI>
         <name>Heussi 1917</name>
         <desc>Heussi, Karl. Untersuchungen zu Nilus Dem Asketen. Texte und Untersuchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 42, no. 2. Leipzig: J. C. Hinrichs, 1917. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hill-2010</IRI>
         <name>Hill 2010 February 01</name>
         <name>hill 2010</name>
         <desc>Hill, Jonathan. “Did Evagrius Ponticus (AD 346–99) Have Obsessive–Compulsive Disorder?.” Journal of Medical Biography 18, no. 1 (2010 February 01): 49–56.rsmjournals.comacademia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hiżycki-2013</IRI>
         <name>Hiżycki 2013</name>
         <desc>Hiżycki, Szymon. “Ermeneutica ed esegesi biblica secondo gli scritti di Evagrio Pontico.” PhD. Pontificium Athenaeum S. Anselmi de Urbe, 2013. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:holden-2004</IRI>
         <name>Holden 2004</name>
         <desc>Holden, W. David. “The Christian Ascetic Tradition on Dejection and Despondency.” OCAMPR Ejournal 2, no. 2 (2004): .ocampr.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:88-8139-091-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hombergen-2001a</IRI>
         <name>hombergen 2001a</name>
         <desc>Hombergen, Daniël. The Second Origenist Controversy: A New Perspective on Cyril of Scythopolis' Monastic Biographies as Historical Sources for Sixth-Century Origenism. Studia Anselmiana 132. Rome: Centro studi S. Anselmo, 2001. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hombergen-2001b</IRI>
         <name>hombergen 2001b</name>
         <desc>Hombergen, Daniël. “Cyril of Scythopolis and the Second Origenist Controversy.” “”  (2001): 31–46.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:horyacha-2013</IRI>
         <name>Horyacha 2013</name>
         <desc>Horyacha, Mariya. “Monastic Thought on the Passions: Pseudo-Macarius versus Evagrius Ponticus.” Byzantion 83 (2013): 113–147.peeters-leuven.be</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:hunt-1973</IRI>
         <name>Hunt 1973</name>
         <desc>Hunt, E. D. “Palladius of Helenopolis: a Party and Its Supporters in the Church of the Late Fourth Century.” Journal of Theological Studies n.s, 24 (1973): 456–80.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:jackson-1895</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus, Basil, and Jackson 1895</name>
         <name>jackson 1895</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus and Basil. St. Basil: Letters and Select Works. Translated by Blomfield Jackson. A Select Library of Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers of the Christian Church, 2nd series 8. New York: The Christian Literature Company, 1895. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:janiszewski-2008</IRI>
         <name>Janiszewski 2008</name>
         <desc>Janiszewski, Pawel. “Why Can’t We See Demons? The Evagrian Concept of the Structure of Bodies Originating from Three Parallel Material Worlds, in the Context of Aristotelian Quality Theory.” Palamedes: A Journal of Ancient History 3 (2008): 189–208.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:jelisavčić-2007</IRI>
         <name>Jelisavčić 2007</name>
         <desc>Jelisavčić, Zoran. “Evagrije Pontijski o duši i umu.” Otačnik 1 (2007): 65–66.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:joest-1993</IRI>
         <name>Joest 1993</name>
         <desc>Joest, Christoph. “Die Bedeutung von Akedia und Apatheia bei Evagrios Pontikos.” Studia Monastica 35, no. 1 (1993): 7–53.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:joest-2000</IRI>
         <name>Joest 2000</name>
         <desc>Joest, Christoph. “Die Praktike bei Evagrios Pontikos und in den Pachom-Briefen.” Ostkirchliche Studien 49 (2000): 31–54.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:joest-2004</IRI>
         <name>Joest 2004</name>
         <desc>Joest, Christoph. “The Significance of Acedia and Apatheia in Evagrius Ponticus.” American Benedictine Review 55, no. 2–3 (2004): 121–50, 273–307.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:joest-2008</IRI>
         <name>Joest 2008</name>
         <desc>Joest, Christoph. “Horsiese zwischen Pachom und Evagrios Pontikos.” Studia Monastica 50 (2008): 69–85.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:joest-2018</IRI>
         <name>Joest 2018</name>
         <desc>Joest, Christoph. “Die arithmetische Feinstruktur im Traktat De oratione des Evagrios Pontikos.” Vigiliae Christianae 72, no. 2018 (2018): 21–40.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-06-064182-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:jones-1985</IRI>
         <name>Jones 1985</name>
         <desc>Jones, Alan W. Soul Making: The Desert Way of Spirituality. San Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1985. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-503-54144-0</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:jullien-pierre-2011</IRI>
         <name>Jullien and Pierre 2011</name>
         <name>jullien pierre 2011</name>
         <desc>Jullien, Florence and Pierre, Marie-Joseph. Monachismes d'Orient: Images, échanges, influences; hommage à Antoine Guillaumont; cinquantenaire de la chaire des "Christianismes orientaux", EPHE SR. Bibliothèque de l'École des hautes études. Section des sciences religieuses 148. Turnhout: Brepols, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-8309-0646-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:junod-1991</IRI>
         <name>Junod 1991</name>
         <desc>Junod, Eric. Les sages du désert: Antoine, Pachôme, Évagre, Syméon. Entrée Libre 16. Genève: Labor et fides, 1991. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kalvesmaki-2012</IRI>
         <name>Kalvesmaki 2012</name>
         <desc>Kalvesmaki, Joel. “The Epistula fidei of Evagrius of Pontus: An Answer to Constantinople.” Journal of Early Christian Studies 20, no. 1 (2012): 113–139.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kalvesmaki-2014</IRI>
         <name>Kalvesmaki June 2014</name>
         <name>kalvesmaki 2014</name>
         <desc>Kalvesmaki, Joel. “The Soul's Cure in Letters: The Death of Gregory of Nazianzus and the Consolation of Evagrius of Pontus.” The American Benedictine Review 65, no. 2 (June 2014): 135–144.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kalvesmaki-2016</IRI>
         <name>Kalvesmaki, Kalvesmaki, and Young 2016</name>
         <name>kalvesmaki 2016</name>
         <desc>Kalvesmaki, Joel. “Evagrius in the Byzantine Genre of Chapters.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 257–287. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-268-03329-3</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-0-268-03329-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kalvesmaki-young-2016</IRI>
         <name>Kalvesmaki and Young 2016</name>
         <name>kalvesmaki young 2016</name>
         <desc>Kalvesmaki, Joel and Young, Robin Darling. Evagrius and His Legacy. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kannengiesser-1995</IRI>
         <name>Kannengiesser 1995</name>
         <desc>Kannengiesser, Charles. “Antony, Athanasius, Evagrius: The Egyptian Fate of Origenism.” Coptic Church Review 16 (1995): 3–8.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:karapetyan-2000</IRI>
         <name>Karapetyan 2000-2001</name>
         <name>karapetyan 2000</name>
         <desc>Karapetyan, T. “Kirakos Erznkaci's On the Eight Thoughts of Evagrius..” St. Nersess Theological Review 5–6 (2000–2001): 39–118.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-19-969696-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:katos-2011</IRI>
         <name>Katos 2011</name>
         <desc>Katos, Demetrios S. Palladius of Helenopolis: The Origenist Advocate. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kavanagh-1984</IRI>
         <name>Kavanagh, Verdon, and Dally 1984</name>
         <name>kavanagh 1984</name>
         <desc>Kavanagh, Aidan. “Eastern Influences on the Rule of Saint Benedict.”  In Monasticism and the Arts, pp. 53–62. Syracuse, N.Y.: Syracuse University Press, 1984. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-90-04-28440-1</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:90-04-28440-0</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kavvadas-2015</IRI>
         <name>Kavvadas 2015</name>
         <desc>Kavvadas, Nestor. Isaak von Ninive und seine Kephalaia Gnostika: Die Pneumatologie und ihr Kontext. Supplements to Vigiliae Christianae 128. Leiden: Brill, 2015. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kerlouégan-1982</IRI>
         <name>Kerlouégan 1982</name>
         <desc>Kerlouégan, François. “Les citations d'auteurs latins Chrétiens dans les vies de saints Bretons Carolingiennes.” Etudes Celtiques 19 (1982): 215–57.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kessel-2010</IRI>
         <name>Briquel-Chatonnet, Debié, and Kessel 2010</name>
         <name>kessel 2010</name>
         <desc>Briquel-Chatonnet, Françoise and Debié, Muriel. “Sinai Syr. 24 as an Important Witness to the Reception History of Some Syriac Ascetic Texts.”  In Sur les pas des Araméens chrétiens: Mélanges offerts à Alain Desreumaux. Edited by Françoise Briquel-Chatonnet and Muriel Debié, pp. 207–218. Cahiers d'études syriaques 1. Paris: Geuthner, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kline-1985</IRI>
         <name>Kline 1985</name>
         <desc>Kline, Francis. “The Christology of Evagrius and the Parent System of Origen.” Cistercian Studies 20 (1985): 155–83.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kline-1987</IRI>
         <name>Kline and Sommerfeldt 1987</name>
         <name>kline 1987</name>
         <desc>Kline, Francis. “Regula Benedicti 73:8: A Rule for Beginners.”  In Erudition at God's Service, pp. 97–108. Cistercian Studies Series 98. Kalamazoo, Mich.: Cistercian Publications, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kocijančič-and-širca-2015</IRI>
         <name>Kocijančič and Širca 2015</name>
         <name>Spisi in Pisma</name>
         <name>Kocijančič and Širca, Spisi in Pisma</name>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:kohlbacher-1994</IRI>
         <name>Kohlbacher and Lesinski 1994</name>
         <name>kohlbacher 1994</name>
         <desc>Kohlbacher, Michael. “Unpublizierte Fragmente des Markianos von Bethlehem (CPG 3898).”  In Horizonte der Christenheit : Festschrift für Friedrich Heyer zu seinem 85. Geburtstag. Oikonomia 34. Erlangen: Lehrstuhl für Geschichte und Theologie des christlichen Ostens, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9780754662655</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:konstantinovsky-2009</IRI>
         <name>Konstantinovsky 2009</name>
         <desc>Konstantinovsky, Julia. Evagrius Ponticus: The Making of a Gnostic. Ashgate New Critical Thinking in Religion, Theology, and Biblical Studies. Farnham and Burlington: Ashgate, 2009. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:konstantinovsky-2012</IRI>
         <name>Konstantinovsky, Bingaman, and Nassif 2012</name>
         <name>konstantinovsky 2012</name>
         <desc>Konstantinovsky, Julia. “Evagrius in the Philokalia of Sts. Macarius and Nicodemus.”  In The Philokalia: A Classic Text of Orthodox Spirituality. Edited by Brock Bingaman and Bradley Nassif. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:konstantinovsky-2013</IRI>
         <name>Konstantinovsky 2013</name>
         <desc>Konstantinovsky, Julia. “Evagrius Ponticus on Being Good in God and Christ.” Studies in Christian Ethics 26 (2013): 317–332.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:konstantinovsky-2016</IRI>
         <name>Konstantinovsky 2016</name>
         <desc>Konstantinovsky, Julia. “Evagrius Ponticus and Maximus the Confessor: The Building of the Self in Praxis and Contemplation.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 128–153. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:krausmuller-2016</IRI>
         <name>Krausmuller 2016</name>
         <desc>Krausmuller, Dirk. “Origenism and Anti-Origenism in the Late Sixth and Seventh Centuries.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 288–316. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:krawiec-2013</IRI>
         <name>Krawiec Fall 2013</name>
         <name>krawiec 2013</name>
         <desc>Krawiec, Rebecca. “Literacy and Memory in Evagrius’s Monasticism.” Journal of Early Christian Studies 21, no. 3 (Fall 2013): 363–390.jhu.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:krivocheine-1996</IRI>
         <name>Krivocheine 1996</name>
         <desc>Krivocheine, Archbishop Basil. “Ангелы и бесы в духовной жизни по учению восточных отцов.”  In Богословские труды, 1952–1983. Статьи, доклады, переводы., pp. 375. Nizhny Novgorod: Izdatel'stvo bratstva vo imia sviatogo kniazia Aleksandra Nevskogo, 1996. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:krüger-1960</IRI>
         <name>Krüger 1960</name>
         <desc>Krüger, Paul. “Zum theologischen Menschenbild Babais den Großen nach seinem noch unveröffentlichten Kommentar zu den beiden Sermones des Mönches Markus über Das geistige Gesetz.” Oriens Christianus 44 (1960): 46–74.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:krüger-1962</IRI>
         <name>Krüger 1962</name>
         <desc>Krüger, Paul. “Das Problem des Pelagianismus bei Babai dem Großen.” Oriens Christianus 46 (1962): 77–86.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:krüger-1963</IRI>
         <name>Krüger 1963</name>
         <desc>Krüger, Paul. “Das Geheimnis der Taufe in den Werken Babai dem Großen.” Oriens Christianus 47 (1963): 98–110.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:labate-1978</IRI>
         <name>Labate, Livrea, and Privitera 1978</name>
         <name>labate 1978</name>
         <desc>Labate, Antonio. “L'esegesi di Evagrio al libro dell'Ecclesiaste.”  In Studi in onore di Anthos Ardizzoni, pp. 483–490. Filologia e critica 25. Rome: Edizioni dell'Ateneo &amp; Bizzarri, 1978. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:labate-1984</IRI>
         <name>Labate 1984</name>
         <desc>Labate, Antonio. “Nuove catene esegetiche sull'Ecclesiaste.”  In Antidōron: Hulde aan Dr. Maurits Geerard bij de voltooiing van de Clavis patrum Graecorum = hommage à Maurits Geerard pour célébrer l'achèvement de la Clavis patrum Graecorum, pp. 241–263. Wetteren, Belgium: Cultura, 1984. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2503402410</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:labate-1992</IRI>
         <name>Labate and Dionysius of Alexandria 1992</name>
         <name>labate 1992</name>
         <desc>Labate, Antonio and Dionysius of Alexandria. Catena Havniensis in Ecclesiasten: In qua saepe exegesis servatur Dionysii Alexandrini. Corpus Christianorum. Series Graeca 24. Turnhout: Brepols, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lackner-1966</IRI>
         <name>Lackner and Gerstinger 1966</name>
         <name>lackner 1966</name>
         <desc>Lackner, Wolfgang. “Zur profanen Bildung des Euagrios Pontikos.”  In Hans Gerstinger: Festgabe zum 80. Geburtstag; Arbeiten aus dem Grazer Schülerkreis, pp. 17–29. Graz: Akademische Druck- und Verlagsanatalt, 1966. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lantschoot-1964</IRI>
         <name>Lantschoot 1964</name>
         <desc>Lantschoot, Arnold van. “Un opuscule inédit de F. C. Conybeare.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 77 (1964): 121–35.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:leanza-1977</IRI>
         <name>Leanza 1977</name>
         <desc>Leanza, Sandro. “Le catene esegetiche sull'Ecclesiaste.” Augustinianum 17 (1977): 545–52.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:leanza-1997</IRI>
         <name>Leanza 1997</name>
         <desc>Leanza, Sandro. “A proposito di una recente edizione del presunto Commentario all'Ecclesiaste di Evagrio Pontico.” Rivista di Storia e Letteratura Religiosa 33, no. 2 (1997): 365–98.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lebon-1949</IRI>
         <name>Severus of Antioch, Sergius the Grammarian, and Lebon 1949</name>
         <name>lebon 1949</name>
         <desc>Severus of Antioch and Sergius the Grammarian. Severi Antiocheni Orationes ad Nephalium: Eiusdem ac Sergii Grammatici epistulae mutuae. Corpus scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 119–120. Louvain: L. Durbecq, 1949. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:leboulluec-1991</IRI>
         <name>LeBoulluec 1991-1992</name>
         <name>leboulluec 1991</name>
         <desc>LeBoulluec, Alain. “Recherches sur la postérité littéraire et doctrinale de Clément d'Alexandrie.” Annuaire de l'école pratique des hautes études, Ve section, Sciences Religieuses 100 (1991–1992): 343–46.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lebreton-1924</IRI>
         <name>Lebreton 1924</name>
         <desc>Lebreton, Jules. “[Dans] Chronique d'histoire des Origines Chrétiennes.” Recherches de Science Religieuse 14 (1924): 360–64.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:leclercq-1951</IRI>
         <name>Leclercq 1951</name>
         <desc>Leclercq, Jean. “L'ancienne version latine des Sentences d'Évagre pour les Moines.” Scriptorium 5 (1951): 195–213.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lefort-1950</IRI>
         <name>Lefort 1950</name>
         <desc>Lefort, L. Théophile. “À propos d'un aphorisme d'Evagrius Ponticus.” Bulletin de l'Académie Royale de Belgique. Classe des Lettres et des Sciences Morales et Politiques, 5e Série 36 (1950): 70–79.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:leroux-1972</IRI>
         <name>Leroux, Fontaine, and Kannengiesser 1972</name>
         <name>leroux 1972</name>
         <desc>Leroux, Jean M. “Jean Chrysostome et la querelle Origéniste.”  In Epektasis: Mélanges patristiques offerts au cardinal Jean Danielou, pp. 335–341. Paris: Beauchesne, 1972. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:levasti-1968</IRI>
         <name>Levasti 1968</name>
         <desc>Levasti, Arrigo. “Il più grande mistico del deserto: Evagrio il Pontico (m. 399).” Rivista di Ascetica e Mistica 13 (1968): 242–64.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lienhard-1980</IRI>
         <name>Lienhard 1980</name>
         <desc>Lienhard, Joseph T. “On 'Discernment of Spirits' in the Early Church.” Theological Studies 41 (1980): 505–29.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:linge-2000</IRI>
         <name>Linge 2000</name>
         <desc>Linge, David E. “Leading the Life of Angels: Ascetic Practice and Reflection in the Writings of Evagrius of Pontus.” Journal of the American Academy of Religion 68 (2000): 537–68.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lolasvili-1984</IRI>
         <name>Lolasvili 1984-1985</name>
         <name>lolasvili 1984</name>
         <desc>Lolasvili, Ivane. Zveli k`art`uli mcerlobis matiane. Tbilisi: Mec`niereba, 1984–1985. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lossky-1972</IRI>
         <name>Lossky 1972</name>
         <desc>Lossky, Vladimir. “The Problem of the Vision Face to Face and Byzantine Patristic Tradition.” The Greek Orthodox Theological Review 17 (1972): 231–54.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lot-borodine-1932</IRI>
         <name>Lot-Borodine 1932</name>
         <desc>Lot-Borodine, Myrrha. “La doctrine de la déification dans l'Eglise grecque jusqu'au XIe siècle.” Revue de l'Histoire des Religions 106 (1932): 525–74.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lot-borodine-1933</IRI>
         <name>Lot-Borodine 1933</name>
         <desc>Lot-Borodine, Myrrha. “La doctrine de la déification dans l'Eglise grecque jusqu'au XIe siècle.” Revue de l'Histoire des Religions 107 (1933): 8–55.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:louf-1974</IRI>
         <name>Louf 1974</name>
         <desc>Louf, André. “L'acédie chez Évagre le Pontique.” Concilium (F) 99 (1974): 113–17.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:louth-2010</IRI>
         <name>Louth 2010</name>
         <desc>Louth, Andrew. “Evagrios on Anger.” Studia Patristica 47 (2010): 179–186.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:louth-2012</IRI>
         <name>Louth 2012</name>
         <desc>Louth, Andrew. “Review of Greg Peters, Peter of Damascus: Byzantine Monk and Spiritual Theologian (Toronto, 2011).” “”  (2012): 543–544.jhu.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:louth-raitt-1998</IRI>
         <name>Louth and Raitt 1998</name>
         <name>louth raitt 1998</name>
         <desc>Louth, Andrew and Raitt, Jill. Wisdom of the Byzantine Church : Evagrios of Pontos and Maximos the Confessor. Columbia, Missouri: Department of Religious Studies, University of Missouri, 1998. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lugaresi-2000</IRI>
         <name>Lugaresi and Bettiolo 2000</name>
         <name>lugaresi 2000</name>
         <desc>Lugaresi, L. “'Non disprezziamo l'economia': L'influsso del pensiero teologico di Gregorio Nazianzeno sull'Epistula fidei.”  In L'epistula fidei di Evagrio Pontico: Temi, contesti, sviluppi; Atti del III convegno del gruppo italiano di ricerca su "Origene e la tradizione alessandrina". Edited by Paolo Bettiolo, pp. 87–144. Studia Ephemeridis Augustinianum 72. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:lynch-1975</IRI>
         <name>Lynch 1975</name>
         <desc>Lynch, John J. “Leontius of Byzantium: A Cyrillian Christology.” Theological Studies 36 (1975): 455–71.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:mai-1825</IRI>
         <name>Mai 1825-1838</name>
         <name>mai 1825</name>
         <desc>Mai, Angelo. Scriptorum veterum nova collectio e vaticanis codicibus. Rome: Burliaeum, 1825–1838. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:maier-1994</IRI>
         <name>Maier 1994</name>
         <desc>Maier, Barbara. “Apatheia bei den Stoikern und Akedia bei Evagrios Pontikos: ein Ideal und die Kehrseite seiner Realität.” Oriens Christianus 78 (1994): 230–49.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:makariem-1868</IRI>
         <name>Eastern Orthodox Church 1868</name>
         <name>makariem 1868</name>
         <desc>Eastern Orthodox Church. Velikija Minei Cetij sobrannyja vserossijskim mitropolitom Makariem. St. Petersburg: [n.p.], 1868. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:maraval-1988</IRI>
         <name>Maraval 1988</name>
         <desc>Maraval, Pierre. “Un correspondant de Grégoire de Nazianze identifié: Pansophios d'Ibora.” Vigiliae Christianae 66 (1988): 24–27.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:marchini-2009</IRI>
         <name>Marchini, Heidl, and Somos 2009</name>
         <name>marchini 2009</name>
         <desc>Marchini, Diego. “La tradizione latina del De octo spiritibus malitiae di Evagrio Pontico.”  In Origeniana nona: Origen and the Religious Practice of His Time; Papers of the 9th International Origen Congress, Pécs, Hungary, 29 August - 2 September 2005. Edited by György Heidl and Róbert Somos, pp. 565–575. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 228. Leuven: Peeters, 2009. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:marsili-1936</IRI>
         <name>Marsili 1936</name>
         <desc>Marsili, Salvatore. Giovanni Cassiano ed Evagrio Pontico: Dottrina sulla carità e contemplazione. Studia Anselmiana philosophica theologica 5. Rome: Herder, 1936. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:mcginn-1991</IRI>
         <name>McGinn 1991</name>
         <desc>McGinn, Bernard. “The Foundations of Mysticism.”  In The Presence of God: A History of Western Christian Mysticism. The Foundations of Mysticism. New York: Crossroad, 1991. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0824521064</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:mcginn-mcginn-2003</IRI>
         <name>McGinn and McGinn 2003</name>
         <name>mcginn mcginn 2003</name>
         <desc>McGinn, Bernard and McGinn, Patricia Ferris. Early Christian Mystics: The Divine Vision of the Spiritual Masters. New York: Crossroad Pub, 2003. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:mcguckin-1999</IRI>
         <name>McGuckin and Allen 1999</name>
         <name>mcguckin 1999</name>
         <desc>McGuckin, John Anthony. “The Prayer of the Heart in Patristic &amp; Early Byzantine Tradition.”  In Prayer and Spirituality in the Early Church. Edited by Pauline Allen, pp. 69–108. Everton Park, Qld.: Centre for Early Christian Studies, Australian Catholic University, 1999. sgtt.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:1-57062-900-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:mcguckin-2002</IRI>
         <name>McGuckin 2002</name>
         <desc>McGuckin, John Anthony. The Book of Mystical Chapters: Meditations on the Soul's Ascent, from the Desert Fathers and Other Early Christian Contemplatives. Boston, Mass.: Shambhala, 2002. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:mcguire-deferrari-1926-v1</IRI>
         <name>Basil, McGuire, and Deferrari 1926</name>
         <name>mcguire deferrari 1926 v1</name>
         <desc>Basil, McGuire, Martin R. P, and Deferrari, Roy J. Saint Basil, the Letters. Loeb Classical Library. London: W. Heinemann, 1926. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:melcher-1923</IRI>
         <name>Melcher 1923</name>
         <desc>Melcher, Robert. Der 8 [achte] Brief des hl. Basilius, ein Werk des Evagrius Pontikus. Münsterische Beiträge zur Theologie 1. Münster in Westfalen: Aschendorff, 1923. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:mercati-1914</IRI>
         <name>Mercati 1914</name>
         <desc>Mercati, Giovanni. “Intorno ad uno scolio creduto di Evagrio.” Revue Biblique Internationale n.s, 11 (1914): 534–42.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:messana-1982</IRI>
         <name>Messana and Felici 1982</name>
         <name>messana 1982</name>
         <desc>Messana, Vincenzo. “La chiesa orante nella catechesi spirituale di Evagrio Pontico.”  In Ecclesiologia e catechesi patristica, "sentirsi Chiesa": Convegno di studio e aggiornamento, Pontificium Institutum Altioris Latinitatis (Facoltà di lettere cristiane e classiche) Roma, 6–7 marzo 1981, pp. 173–186. Biblioteca di scienze religiose 46. Rome: Libreria Ateneo salesiano, 1982. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:messana-1995</IRI>
         <name>Messana 1995</name>
         <desc>Messana, Vincenzo. “Le definizioni di proseuche nel De oratione de Evagrio Pontico.”  In Oeconomus gratiae: Studi per il 20. anniversario di episcopato di Alfredo M. Garsia, pp. 69–87. Quaderni di presenza culturale 32. Caltanissetta: Edizioni del Seminario, 1995. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:meyer-2013</IRI>
         <name>Meyer 2013</name>
         <desc>Meyer, Eric Daryl. “"Marvel at the Intelligence of Unthinking Creatures!": Contemplative Animals in Gregory of Nazianzus and Evagrius of Pontus.”  In Animals as Religious Subjects: Transdisciplinary Perspectives. London: Blomsbury T&amp;T Clark, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-0-19-872296-0</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:michelson-2014</IRI>
         <name>Michelson 2014</name>
         <desc>Michelson, David. The Practical Christology of Philoxenos of Mabbug. Oxford Early Christian Studies. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:michelson-2016</IRI>
         <name>Michelson 2016</name>
         <desc>Michelson, David A. “Philoxenos of Mabbug and the Simplicity of Evagrian Gnosis.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 175–205. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Patrologia_Graeca</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:migne-1857</IRI>
         <name>Migne 1857</name>
         <name>Patrologia Graeca</name>
         <name>PG</name>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:miquel-1967</IRI>
         <name>Miquel 1967</name>
         <desc>Miquel, Pierre. “L'appel à l'expérience chez quelques auteurs de la Philocalie.” Irénikon 40 (1967): 354–76.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2855890446</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0768-021X</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:miquel-1986</IRI>
         <name>Miquel 1986</name>
         <desc>Miquel, Pierre. Lexique du désert: Étude de quelques mots-clés du vocabulaire monastique grec ancien. Spiritualité orientale 44. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: Abbaye de Bellefontaine :, 1986. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-910184-00-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:miquel-1993</IRI>
         <name>Miquel and de Vogüé 1993</name>
         <name>miquel 1993</name>
         <desc>Miquel, Pierre. Déserts chrétiens d'Egypte. Collection Le portique. Nice: Culture sud, 1993. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:misiarczyk-2001</IRI>
         <name>Misiarczyk 2001</name>
         <desc>Misiarczyk, Leszek. “Mysli zmyslowej czesci duszy i sposoby walki z nimi wedlug Ewagriusza z Pontu [Thoughts of the sensual part of soul and the way to combat them according to Evagrius Ponticus].” Studa Plockie 29 (2001): 147–65.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:misiarczyk-2002</IRI>
         <name>Misiarczyk 2002</name>
         <desc>Misiarczyk, Leszek. “Smutek i zlosc w nauce duchowej Ewagriusza z Pontu [Grief and anger in the spiritual teaching of Evagrius Ponticus].” Studa Plockie 30 (2002): 83–96.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:misiarczyk-2003</IRI>
         <name>Misiarczyk 2003</name>
         <desc>Misiarczyk, Leszek. “Próznosc i pycha: mysli racjonalnej czesci duszy w duchowej walce wedlug Ewagriusza z Pontu [Vanity and hubris: thoughts of the rational part of the soul in spiritual straggle according to Ecagrius Ponticus].” Studia Plockie 31 (2003): 27–38.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:misiarczyk-2004</IRI>
         <name>Misiarczyk 2004</name>
         <desc>Misiarczyk, Leszek. “Acedia in Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Plockie 32 (2004): 63–84.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-83-7354-195-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:misiarczyk-2007</IRI>
         <name>Misiarczyk 2007</name>
         <desc>Misiarczyk, Leszek. Osiem logismoi w pismach Ewagriusza z Pontu. Kraków: Tyniec - Wydawnictwo Benedyktynów, 2007. kalvesmaki.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:misiarczyk-2012</IRI>
         <name>Misiarczyk and Drączkowski 2012</name>
         <name>misiarczyk 2012</name>
         <desc>Misiarczyk, Leszek. “Syryjskie przekłady Kephalaia Gnostica Ewagriusza z Pontu [Syriac Versions of Evagrius Ponticus’ Kephalaia Gnostica].”  In Ortodoksja, herezja, schizma w Kościele starożytnym [Orthodoxy, Heresy and Schism in Early Church]. Edited by Franciszek Drączkowski, pp. 157–167. Lublin: Polihymnia, 2012. docplayer.pl</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:misiarczyk-2013</IRI>
         <name>Misiarczyk 2013</name>
         <desc>Misiarczyk, Leszek. “The Relationship Between Nous, Pneuma and Logistikon in Evagrius Ponticus’ Anthropology.” Studia Patristica 68 (2013): 149–154.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:moisescu-1937</IRI>
         <name>Moisescu 1937</name>
         <desc>Moisescu, Iustin I. Εὐάγριος ὁ Πόντικος: Βίος, συγγράμματα, διδασκαλία. Athens: "Pyrsou", 1937. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:88-311-1630-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:moreschini-2008</IRI>
         <name>Moreschini 2008</name>
         <desc>Moreschini, Claudio. I Padri cappadoci: Storia, letteratura, teologia. Rome: Città nuova, 2008. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muckle-1942</IRI>
         <name>Muckle 1942</name>
         <desc>Muckle, J. T. “Greek Works Translated Directly into Latin Before 1350.” Medieval Studies 4 (1942): 33–42.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-0-19-993193-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muehlberger-2013</IRI>
         <name>Muehlberger 2013</name>
         <desc>Muehlberger, Ellen. Angels in Late Ancient Christianity. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013. amazon.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muehlberger-2017a</IRI>
         <name>muehlberger 2017a</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. “Evagrius of Pontus, Protrepticus.” In The Cambridge Edition of Early Christian Writings, Vol. 2, Practice, edited and translated by Ellen Muehlberger, 75–79. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2017.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muehlberger-2017b</IRI>
         <name>muehlberger 2017b</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. “Evagrius of Pontus, Paraeneticus.” In The Cambridge Edition of Early Christian Writings, Vol. 2, Practice, edited and translated by Ellen Muehlberger, 80–85. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2017.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muehlberger-2018</IRI>
         <name>Muehlberger, Larsen, and Rubenson 2018</name>
         <name>muehlberger 2018</name>
         <desc>Muehlberger, Ellen. “Affecting Rhetoric: The Adoption of Ethopoeia in Evagrius of Pontus’ Ascetic Program.”  In Monastic Education in Late Antiquity: The Transformation of Classical 'Paideia'. Edited by Lillian Larsen and Samuel Rubenson, pp. 182–94. New York: Cambridge University Press, 2018. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muravjev-2003</IRI>
         <name>Muravjev, Perrone, Bernardino, and Marchini 2003</name>
         <name>muravjev 2003</name>
         <desc>Muravjev, Alexej. “Macarian or Evagrian: The Problem of Origenist Legacy in Eastern Syriac Mystical Literature.”  In Origeniana octava: Origen and the Alexandrian Tradition = Origene E La Tradizione Alessandrina: Papers of the 8th International Origen Congress, Pisa, 27–31 August 2001. Edited by Lorenzo Perrone, P. Bernardino, and D. Marchini, pp. 1185–1191. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 164. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 2003. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:murphy-1985</IRI>
         <name>Murphy, Hanson, and Crouzel 1985</name>
         <name>murphy 1985</name>
         <desc>Murphy, Francis X. “Evagrius Ponticus and Origenism.”  In Origeniana tertia: The Third International Colloquium for Origen Studies, University of Manchester September 7th-11th, 1981; Papers, pp. 253–269. Rome: Edizioni dell'Ateneo, 1985. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1929a</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1929a</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “La teneur du Practicus d'Evagrius le Pontique.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 42 (1929): 74–89.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1929b</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1929b</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Le discours de Xystus dans la version arménienne d'Évagre le Pontique.” Revue des Études Arméniennes 9 (1929): 183–201.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1931a</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1931a</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Evagriana.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 44 (1931): 37–68.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1931b</IRI>
         <IRI>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/558798869</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1931b</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. Evagriana: Extrait de la revue Le Muséon, vol. 44, augmenté de nouveax fragments grecs inédits. Paris: Paul Geuthner, 1931. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1931c</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1931c</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Note additionnelle à: Euagriana.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 44 (1931): 369–83.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/7564753</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1932</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1932</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. À travers la tradition manuscrite d'Evagre le Pontique: Essai sur les manuscrits grecs conservés à la Bibliothèque nationale de Paris. Bibliothèque du Muséon 3. Louvain: Bureaux du Muséon, 1932. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1934a</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1934a</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Évagre le Pontique: Les Capita cognoscitiua dans les versions syriaque et arménienne.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 47 (1934): 73–106.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1934b</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1934b</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Miscellanea armeniaca.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 47 (1934): 293–96.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1938</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1938</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Evagriana: Le Vatic. Barb. Graec. 515.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 51 (1938): 191–226.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1939</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1939</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Une nouvelle recension du De octo spiritibus malitiae de S. Nil.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 52 (1939): 235–74.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1940</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1940</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Fragment arménien du Ad virgines d'Évagre.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 53 (1940): 77–87.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1941</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1941</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Evagriana de la Vaticane.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 54 (1941): 1–15.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1943</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1943</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “S. Nil en version arménienne.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 56 (1943): 77–113.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1946</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1946</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Sur les séraphins et Sur les chérubins d'Évagre le Pontique dans les versions syriaque et arménienne.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 59 (1946): 367–79.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1952</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Muyldermans 1952</name>
         <name>muyldermans 1952</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Evagriana syriaca: Textes inedits du British Museum et de la Vaticane. Bibliothèque du Muséon 31. Louvain: Publications universitaires, 1952. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1952b</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1952b</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “À propos d'un feuillet de manuscrit arménien (Brit. Mus, cod. arm. 118).” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 65 (1952): 11–16.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1953</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1953</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Une texte grec inédit attribué à Jean de Lycopolis.” Recherches de science religieuse 41 (1953): 525–30.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1955a</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1955a</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “À propos d'un texte grec attribué à Jean de Lycopolis.” Recherches de science religieuse 43 (1955): 395–401.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1955b</IRI>
         <name>muyldermans 1955b</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Les manuscripts arméniens d'Évagre le Pontique à Jérusalem.” Bazmavep 113 (1955): 72–78, 108–14.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1961</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1961</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Les citations bibliques dans la version arménienne de l'Antirrheticus d'Èvagre le Pontique.” Handes Amsoreay 72 (1961): 441–48.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:muyldermans-1963</IRI>
         <name>Muyldermans 1963</name>
         <desc>Muyldermans, Joseph. “Euagriana coptica.” Le Muséon. Revue d'Études Orientales 76 (1963): 271–76.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ménager-1936</IRI>
         <name>Ménager 1936</name>
         <desc>Ménager, A. “A propos de Cassien.” La Vie Spirituelle 46 (1936): 73–109.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:mühmelt-1954</IRI>
         <name>Mühmelt 1954</name>
         <desc>Mühmelt, Martin. “Zu der neuen lateinischen Übersetzung des Mönchsspiegels des Euagrius.” Vigiliae Christianae 8 (1954): 101–3.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-204-06490-4</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-204-06490-3</IRI>
         <IRI>http://lccn.loc.gov/98122568</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:neyt-1997</IRI>
         <name>Barsanuphius, John of Gaza, and Neyt 2001</name>
         <name>SC 451</name>
         <name>neyt 1997</name>
         <desc>Barsanuphius, John of Gaza, and Neyt, François. Correspondance: vol. 2, pt. 2, Aux cénobites, Lettres 399–616. Sources chrétiennes 451. Paris: Éditions du Cerf, 2001. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nešić-2013</IRI>
         <name>Nešić 2013</name>
         <desc>Nešić, Lazar. “Изабрана писма Писмо прво [Меланији].” Теолошки погледи / Theological Views 46, no. 2 (2013): 331–336.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nešić-2014</IRI>
         <name>Nešić 2014</name>
         <desc>Nešić, Lazar. “Евагрије Понтски: Монасима у манастирима и заједницама (Εὐαγρίου Ποντικοῦ: Πρὸς τοὺς ἐν κοινοβίοις ἢ συνοδίαις μοναχούς) - превод (translation).” Theological Views 47, no. 1 (2014): 13–32.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:niculescu-2004</IRI>
         <name>Niculescu 2004</name>
         <desc>Niculescu, Vlad. “Coping with the Grief of Ignorance: Evagrius Ponticus's Hermeneutics of the Distance Between God and Humanity.” Arches: Revue Internationale des Sciences Humaines 7 (2004): .arches.ro</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1993</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior 1993</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Uwagi bibliograficzne na temat literatury zwiazanej z Ewagriuszem z Pontu [Bibligraphical remarks regarding Evagrius Ponticus Literature].” Collectanea Theologica 63, no. 4 (1993): 115–20.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1994</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior, Palucki, and Draczkowski 1994</name>
         <name>nieścior 1994</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Apostolat na pustyni w pismach Ewagriusza z Pontu [Apostolate in the Desert in Evagrius's Works].”  In Ewangelizacja W Epoce Patrystycznej [Evangelization in the Patristic Period], pp. 61–81. Lublin: Polihymnia, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1995a</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 1995a</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Ocena moralna sfery popedowej w nauce Ewagriusza z Pontu o naturze ludzkiej [Moral judgement of irrascible sphere in Evagrius Ponticus's doctrine on human nature].” Collectanea Theologica 65, no. 4 (1995): 39–53.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1995b</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 1995b</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Trudy (pónoi) jako termin ascetyczny u Ewagriusza z Pontu [Hardships as a ascetic concept in Evagrius Ponticus].” Studia Paradyskie 5 (1995): 81–108.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1996a</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 1996a</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Chrzescijanska asceza rozumiana inaczej [Christian ascetism seen in another way].” Homo Dei 65 (1996): 37–51.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1996b</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 1996b</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Ewagriusza z Pontu 'De malignis cogitationibus': O samym dziele; Tlumaczenie [Evagrius of Pontus, 'De malignis cogitationibus': About the work; translation].” Cenobium 10 (1996): 28–50.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1996c</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 1996c</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Kategorie mysli w nauce scetycznej Ewagriusza z Pontu [Categories of Thougths in Evagrius Ponticus's ascetic doctrine].” Roczniki Humanistyczne 44, no. 3 (1996): 203–30.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1997a</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 1997a</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. Anachoreza w pismach Ewagriusza z Pontu. Kraków: Tyniec - Wydawnictwo Benedyktynów, 1997. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1997b</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 1997b</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Pojecie apathei w pismach Ewagriusza z Pontu [The notion of apatheia in the writings of Evagrius Ponticus].” Studia Paradyskie 6–7 (1997): 105–33.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1997c</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 1997c</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Praktike jako wlaka ze zlymi mslami w nauce Ewagriusza z Pontu [Prakite as a fight with wrong thougths in the teaching of Evagrius Ponticus].” Vox Patrum 17 (1997): 177–86.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1997d</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior, Draczkowski, Palucki, and Szram 1997</name>
         <name>nieścior 1997d</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Rozeznawanie mysli (diakrisis) i spor z nimi (anthiresis) wedlug Ewagriusza z Pontu [The Discernement of thoughts (diakrisis) and the dispute with them (anthiresis) according to Evagrius Ponticus].”  In Droga doskonalenia chrzescijanskiego w epoce patrystycznej: Zagadnienia wybrane; praca zbiorowa, pp. 31–56. Lublin: Polihymnia, 1997. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1998</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior, Draczkowski, Palucki, and Szram 1998</name>
         <name>nieścior 1998</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Glos Klemensa Aleksandryjskiego i Ewagriusza z Pontu w starozytnej dyskusji o apathei [The voice of Clement and Evagrius in ancient discussion on apatheia].”  In Ojcowie Kosciola wobec filozofii i kultury klasycznej: Zagadnienia wybrane; Praca zbiorowa, pp. 41–69. Lublin: Polihymnia, 1998. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1999a</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior and Drabina 1999</name>
         <name>nieścior 1999a</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Mistyczne perspektywy apathei w nauce Ewagriusza z Pontu [The Mystical Perspective of Apathy in the teaching of Evagrius of Pontus].”  In Koscioly Wschodnie, pp. 65–83. Zeszyty naukowe Uniwersytetu Jagiellonskiego 1237. Kraków: Wydawn. Uniwersytetu Jagiellonskiego, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-1999b</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior, Pietras, and Obrycki 1999</name>
         <name>nieścior 1999b</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Pierwotny upadek umyslu w pismach Ewagriusza z Pontu [Primordial fall of the nous in the writings of Evagrius Ponticus].”  In Grzech pierworodny, pp. 67–85. Zródla Mysli Teologicznej 12. Kraków: Wydaw. WAM- Ksiaza Jezuici, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-2002a</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior, Podeszwa, and Szczerbinski 2002</name>
         <name>nieścior 2002a</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Czystosc serca i umyslu wedlug Ewagriusza z Pontu [The purity of heart cnd mind according to Evagrius Ponticus].”  In Ad sapientiam cordis: Ksiega pamiatkowa dedykowana ksiedzu profesorowi Ludwikowi Gladyszewskiemu w 70. rocznice urodzin, pp. 125–150. Gniezno: Prymasowskie Wyzsze Seminarium Duchowne, 2002. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-2002b</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior 2002</name>
         <name>nieścior 2002b</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Psalmy w procesie wewnetrznej ewangelizacji chrzescijanina: Metoda antyrretyczna Ewagriusza z Pontu [The Psalms in the interior process of Christian evangelization: The anthirrethical method of Evagrius Ponticus].” Verbum Vitae 2 (2002): 243–52.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-2005a</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 2005a</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Die Grundlagen der ethischen Beurteilung der Gedanken in der Lehre von Evagrios Pontikos.” Erbe und Auftrag 81 (2005): 97–119.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-2005b</IRI>
         <name>nieścior 2005b</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Sny u Ewagriusza z Pontu [Dreams in Evagrius Ponticus].” Zycie Duchowe 44 (2005): 21–27.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nieścior-2012</IRI>
         <name>Nieścior 2012</name>
         <desc>Nieścior, Leon. “Teologia i wiara według Ewagriusza z Pontu [Theology and Faith according to Evagrius Ponticus].” Teologia Patrystyczna 9 (2012): 73–93.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:nilus-1673</IRI>
         <name>Nilus and Suarez 1673</name>
         <name>nilus 1673</name>
         <desc>Nilus, of Ancyra. Τοῦ ἐν ἁγίοις πατρὸς ἡμῶν Νείλου Ἡγουμένου λόγοι / Sancti patris nostri Nili Abbatis tractatus, seu opscula ex codicibus manuscriptis Vaticanis, Cassinensibus, Barberinis, &amp; Altaempsianis eruta. Rome: Typis Barberinis excudebat Michael Hercules, 1673. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:noah-1983</IRI>
         <name>Noah 1983</name>
         <desc>Noah, P. de Angelis. “La méditation de Barsanuphe sur la lettre êta.” Byzantion 53 (1983): 506–7.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:norris-1985</IRI>
         <name>Norris 1985</name>
         <desc>Norris, Frederick W. “The Authenticity of Gregory Nazianzen's Five Theological Orations.” Vigiliae Christianae 39, no. 4 (1985): 331–39.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:olaughlin-1987</IRI>
         <name>O'Laughlin 1987</name>
         <name>olaughlin 1987</name>
         <desc>O'Laughlin, Michael. “Origenism in the Desert: Anthropology and Integration in Evagrius Ponticus.” PhD dissertation. Harvard Divinity School, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:olaughlin-1988</IRI>
         <name>O'Laughlin, Kannengiesser, and Petersen 1988</name>
         <name>olaughlin 1988</name>
         <desc>O'Laughlin, Michael. “Elements of Fourth Century Origenism: The Anthropology of Evagrius Ponticus and Its Sources.”  In Origen of Alexandria: His World and His Legacy, pp. 357–373. Christianity and Judaism in Antiquity 1. Notre Dame, Ind.: University of Notre Dame Press, 1988. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:olaughlin-1992a</IRI>
         <name>O'Laughlin and Daly 1992</name>
         <name>olaughlin 1992a</name>
         <desc>O'Laughlin, Michael. “New Questions Concerning the Origenism of Evagrius.”  In Origeniana quinta: Historica, Text and Method, Biblica, Philosophica, Theologica, Origenism and Later developments; Papers of the 5th International Origen Congress, Boston College, 14–18 August 1989, pp. 528–34. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 105. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:olaughlin-1992b</IRI>
         <name>O'Laughlin 1992</name>
         <name>olaughlin 1992b</name>
         <desc>O'Laughlin, Michael. “The Bible, Demons and the Desert: Evaluating the Antirrheticus of Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Monastica 34, no. 2 (1992): 201–15.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:olaughlin-1997</IRI>
         <name>O'Laughlin 1997</name>
         <name>olaughlin 1997</name>
         <desc>O'Laughlin, Michael. “Evagrius Ponticus in Spiritual Perspective.” Studia Patristica 30 (1997): 224–230.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:olaughlin-1999</IRI>
         <name>O'Laughlin, Bienert, and Kühneweg 1999</name>
         <name>olaughlin 1999</name>
         <desc>O'Laughlin, Michael. “Closing the Gap between Antony and Evagrius.”  In Origeniana septima: Origenes in den Auseinandersetzungen des 4. Jahrhunderts, pp. 345–54. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 137. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:orlandi-1982</IRI>
         <name>Orlandi 1982</name>
         <desc>Orlandi, Tito. “A Catechesis Against Apocryphal Texts by Shenute and the Gnostic Texts of Nag Hammadi.” Harvard Theological Review 75 (1982): 85–95.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:otto-1974</IRI>
         <name>Otto 1974</name>
         <desc>Otto, Stephan. “Esoterik und individualistische Gnosis: Der mönchische Platonismus des Euagrios Pontikos.”  In Die Antike im Umbruch: Politisches Denken zwischen hellenistischer Tradition und christlicher Offenbarung bis zur Reichstheologie Justinians, pp. 65–81. Munich: Lit Verlag, 1974. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ousley-1979</IRI>
         <name>Ousley 1979</name>
         <desc>Ousley, David Alan. “Evagrius' Theology of Prayer and the Spiritual Life.” PhD dissertation. University of Chicago, 1979. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:palladius-1918</IRI>
         <name>Palladius of Helenopolis and Clarke 1918</name>
         <name>palladius 1918</name>
         <desc>Palladius of Helenopolis. The Lausiac History of Palladius. Translated by W. K. Lowther Clarke. London: Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, 1918. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-85589-360-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:palladius-1994</IRI>
         <name>Palladius of Helenopolis, de Vogüé, and Bunge 1994</name>
         <name>palladius 1994</name>
         <desc>Palladius of Helenopolis. Quatre ermites égyptiens: D'après les fragments coptes de l'Histoire lausiaque. Translated by Adalbert de Vogüé. Spiritualité orientale 60. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: Abbaye de Bellefontaine, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:paramelle-1975</IRI>
         <name>Paramelle 1975-1976</name>
         <name>paramelle 1975</name>
         <desc>Paramelle, J. “Chapitres des disciples d'Évagre dans un manuscrit grec du Musée Bénaki d'Athènes.” Parole de l'Orient 6–7 (1975–1976): 101–113.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:paramelle-1979</IRI>
         <name>Paramelle 1979-1980</name>
         <name>paramelle 1979</name>
         <desc>Paramelle, J. “Les chapitres des disciples d'Évagre.” Annuaire de l'école pratique des hautes études, Ve section, Sciences Religieuses 88 (1979–1980): 348–85.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:parmentier-1985</IRI>
         <name>Parmentier 1985</name>
         <desc>Parmentier, M. “Evagrius of Pontus' Letter to Melania.” Bijdragen 46 (1985): 2–38.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-87907-696-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:parmentier-kitchen-2004</IRI>
         <name>Parmentier and Kitchen 2004</name>
         <name>parmentier kitchen 2004</name>
         <desc>Parmentier, M. F. G. and Kitchen, Robert A. The Book of Steps: The Syriac Liber Graduum. Cistercian Studies Series 196. Kalamazoo, Mich.: Cistercian Publications, 2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:parys-1981</IRI>
         <name>Parys 1981</name>
         <desc>Parys, Michel Van. “La lettre de Saint Arsène.” Irénikon 54, no. 1 (1981): 62–86.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:patrascu-2010</IRI>
         <name>Patrascu 2010</name>
         <desc>Patrascu, Horia. “Acedia—The Anchoretic Bovarism: Gustave Flaubert and Evagrius Ponticus.” “”  (2010): 390–403.40.249</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:paša-2010</IRI>
         <name>Paša 2010</name>
         <desc>Paša, Željko. “The Influence of Evagrius Ponticus on the Thought of Maximus the Confessor.” Licentiate. Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 2010. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:penati-benardini-2000a</IRI>
         <name>penati benardini 2000a</name>
         <desc>Penati Bernardini, A. “In margine alla definizione della Trinità: Un confronto tra gli scritti trinitari di Gregorio di Nissa e l'Epistula fidei di Evagrio Pontico.”  In L'epistula fidei di Evagrio Pontico: Temi, contesti, sviluppi; Atti del III convegno del gruppo italiano di ricerca su "Origene e la tradizione alessandrina". Edited by Paolo Bettiolo, pp. 145–152. Studia Ephemeridis Augustinianum 72. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:penati-benardini-2000b</IRI>
         <name>penati benardini 2000b</name>
         <desc>Penati Bernardini, A. “La γνῶσις χριστοῦ di Evagrio Pontico.”  In L'epistula fidei di Evagrio Pontico: Temi, contesti, sviluppi; Atti del III convegno del gruppo italiano di ricerca su "Origene e la tradizione alessandrina". Edited by Paolo Bettiolo, pp. 153–182. Studia Ephemeridis Augustinianum 72. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:perczel-1999a</IRI>
         <name>perczel 1999a</name>
         <desc>Perczel, István. “Mankind's Common Intellectual Substance: A Study in the Letters of Saint Antony and his Life by Saint Athanasius.”  In The Man of Many Devices, Who Wandered Full Many Ways: Festschrift in Honor of Janos M. Bak, pp. 197–213. [n.p.]: Central Europen University  Press, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:perczel-1999b</IRI>
         <name>perczel 1999b</name>
         <desc>Perczel, István. “Une théologie de la lumière: Denys l'Aréopagite et Évagre le Pontique.” Revue des Études Augustiniennes 45, no. 1 (1999): 79–120.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:perczel-2004</IRI>
         <name>Perczel, Schwartz, and Krech 2004</name>
         <name>perczel 2004</name>
         <desc>Perczel, István. “A Philosophical Myth in the Service of Christian Apologetics? Manichees and Origenists in the Sixth Century.”  In Religious Apologetics – Philosophical Argumentation. Edited by Yosset Schwartz and Volkhard Krech, pp. 205–236. Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2010a</IRI>
         <name>Peretó Rivas 2010</name>
         <name>peretó rivas 2010a</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “El itinerario medieval de la Acedia.” Intus – Legere: Historia 4, no. 1 (2010): 33–48.unirioja.es</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2011a</IRI>
         <name>peretó rivas 2011a</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “Acedia y depresión: Aportes para una reconstrucción histórica.” Revista de Humanidades Médicas &amp; Estudios Sociales de la Ciencia y la Tecnología 3, no. 1 (2011): .ea-journal.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2011b</IRI>
         <name>peretó rivas 2011b</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “La acedia y el transitus monástico en el siglo XII.” Teología Espiritual (Facultad de Teología San Vicente Ferrer - Valencia) 55, no. 165 (2011): 313–324.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2011c</IRI>
         <name>peretó rivas 2011c</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “Las mutaciones de la acedia: De la Patrística a la Edad Media.” Studium 27 (2011): 159–173.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2012a</IRI>
         <name>peretó rivas 2012a</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “Acedia y trabajo: El justo equilibrio.” “”  (2012): 333–344.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2012b</IRI>
         <name>peretó rivas 2012b</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “Evagrio Póntico y la exclaustración de la acedia.” Carthaginensia (Instituto Teológico de Murcia) 28, no. 53 (2012): 23–35.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2013a</IRI>
         <name>peretó rivas 2013a</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “La acedia y Evagrio Póntico: Entre ángeles y demonios.” Studia Patristica 67 (2013): .</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2013b</IRI>
         <name>peretó rivas 2013b</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “Las doctrinas secretas en la obra de Evagrio Póntico.” Mediaevalia: Textos e estudos 32 (2013): 15–28.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2014</IRI>
         <name>Peretó Rivas 2014</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “La acedia como causa de la caída del nous en Orígenes y Evagrio Póntico.” Teología y Vida 55, no. 4 (2014): 581–593.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2015a</IRI>
         <name>Peretó Rivas and Muñoz 2015</name>
         <name>peretó rivas 2015a</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “El concepto de acedia en Evagrio Póntico.”  In El cristianismo frente a los problemas perennes de la filosofía occidental. Edited by Carlos Muñoz, pp. 101–114. Mendoza: [n.p.], 2015. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2015b</IRI>
         <name>Peretó Rivas 2015</name>
         <name>peretó rivas 2015b</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “La Kephálaia gnóstica de Evagrio Póntico. Sus dos versiones y la discusión contemporánea.” Stylos 24 (2015): 193–201.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-2017</IRI>
         <name>Peretó Rivas 2017</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén. “Dreams in Evagrius Ponticus' Life and Teaching.” Vox Patrum 37 (2017): 523–542.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peretó-rivas-muñoz-2013</IRI>
         <name>Peretó Rivas, Muñoz, Muñoz Jiménez, Cañizares, and Martín Puente 2013</name>
         <name>peretó rivas muñoz 2013</name>
         <desc>Peretó Rivas, Rubén and Muñoz, Carlos. “La compilación como práctica terapéutica en Evagrio Póntico.”  In La compilación del saber en la Edad Media. Edited by María José Muñoz Jiménez, Patricia Cañizares, and Cristina Martín Puente, pp. 399–416. Textes et Études du Moyen Âge 69. Porto: Gabinete de Filosofia Medieval, Faculdade de Letras da Universidade do Porto, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:perrone-2009</IRI>
         <name>Perrone 2009</name>
         <desc>Perrone, Lorenzo. “"Dsaglebis gandeva locvis zhams" mlocvelis saxe demonebsa da angelozebs šoris: origenedan evagre pontoelamde.” Kristianul-arkeologiuri dziebani / Studies in Christian Archeology 2 (2009): 9–52.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:perrone-2011</IRI>
         <name>Perrone 2011</name>
         <desc>Perrone, Lorenzo. La preghiera secondo Origene: L'impossibilità donata. Letteratura Cristiana Antica. Nuova Serie 24. Brescia: Morcelliana, 2011. bib-bvb.de:8991</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peterson-1923</IRI>
         <name>Peterson 1923</name>
         <desc>Peterson, E. “Zu griechischen Asketikern. Part 1, Zu Euagrius Ponticus.” Byzantinisch-Neugriechische Jahrbücher 4 (1923): 5–8.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peterson-1926</IRI>
         <name>Peterson 1926</name>
         <desc>Peterson, E. “Zu griechischen Asketikern. Part 2, Noch einmal zu Euagrius Ponticus.” Byzantinisch-Neugriechische Jahrbücher 5 (1926): 412–14.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:peterson-1930</IRI>
         <name>Peterson 1930-1932</name>
         <name>peterson 1930</name>
         <desc>Peterson, E. “Zu griechischen Asketikern. Part 3, Zu Euagrius.” Byzantinisch-Neugriechische Jahrbücher 9 (1930–1932): 51–54.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:philokalia-1953</IRI>
         <name>Makarios, Nicodemus, and Gouillard 1953</name>
         <name>philokalia 1953</name>
         <desc>Makarios, Saint and Nicodemus, the Hagiorite. Petite Philocalie de la prière du coeur. Translated by Jean Gouillard. Documents Spirituels 5. Paris: Éditions des Cahiers du Sùd, 1953. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:philokalia-1957</IRI>
         <name>Philokalia 1957</name>
         <desc>Nicodemus the Hagiorite and Saint Makarios, Φιλοκαλία τῶν νηπτικῶν συνερανισθεῖσα
             παρὰ τῶν ἁγίων καὶ θεοφόρων πατέρων ἡμῶν ἐν ᾑ διὰ τῆς κατὰ τὴν Πρᾶξιν καὶ Θεωρίαν
             Ἠθικῆς Φιλοσοφίας ὁ νοῦς καθαίρεται, φωτίζεται, καὶ τελετοῦται, 3rd ed., 5 vols.
             (Athens: Ἀστήρ, 1957).</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-571-11377-X</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:philokalia-1979</IRI>
         <name>Nicodemus the Hagiorite, Makarios, Metropolitan of Corinth, Palmer, Sherrard, and Kallistos, Bishop of Diokleia 1979-</name>
         <name>philokalia 1979</name>
         <desc>Nicodemus the Hagiorite and Makarios, Metropolitan of Corinth. The Philokalia: The Complete Text. Translated by G. E. H. Palmer, Philip Sherrard, and Kallistos, Bishop of Diokleia. London: Faber and Faber, 1979–. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:philokalia-1982</IRI>
         <name>Nicodemus, Makarios, Artioli, and Lovato 1982-</name>
         <name>philokalia 1982</name>
         <desc>Nicodemus, the Hagiorite and Makarios, Saint. La Filocalia. Translated by M. Benedetta Artioli and M. Francesca Lovato. Torino: P. Gribaudi, 1982–. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2855899516</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:philokalia-1987</IRI>
         <name>Nicodemus, Regnault, and Touraille 1987</name>
         <name>philokalia 1987</name>
         <desc>Nicodemus, the Hagiorite. Philocalie des pères neptiques: Composée à partir des écrits des saints pères qui portaient dieu ..; Publiée pour la première fois par saint nicodème l'hagiorite à venise, en 1782. Translated by Lucien Regnault and Jacques Touraille. Bégrolles en Mauges, Maine-et-Loire: P. Boris Bobrinsky, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-220-03585-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:philokalia-1995</IRI>
         <name>Nicodemus, Makarios, and Touraille 1995-</name>
         <name>philokalia 1995</name>
         <desc>Nicodemus, the Hagiorite and Makarios, Saint. Philocalie des pères neptiques: Composée à partir des écrits des saints pères qui portaient Dieu, et dans laquelle, par une sagesse de vie, faite d'ascèse et de contemplation, l'intelligence est purifiée, illuminée et atteint la perfection. Translated by Jacques Touraille. Paris: Desclée de Brouwer, 1995–. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:1-884729-79-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:philokalia-2008</IRI>
         <name>Makarios, Nicodemus, and Cavarnos 2008-2009</name>
         <name>philokalia 2008</name>
         <desc>Makarios, Saint and Nicodemus, the Hagiorite. The Philokalia: Writings of Holy Mystic Fathers in Which Is Explained How the Mind Is Purified, Illumined, and Perfected Through Practical and Contemplative Ethical Philosophy. Translated by Constantine Cavarnos. Belmont, Mass.: Institute for Byzantine and Modern Greek Studies, 2008–2009. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:pilato-2014</IRI>
         <name>Pilato May 2014</name>
         <name>pilato 2014</name>
         <desc>Pilato, Michael. “Participating in Divine Simplicity: Apophatic Theology and Apatheia in the Thought of Evagrius Ponticus.” thesis. Eden Theological Seminary, May 2014. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:pitra-1876</IRI>
         <IRI>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/20553841</IRI>
         <name>Pitra 1876-1891</name>
         <name>pitra 1876</name>
         <desc>Pitra, J. B. Analecta sacra spicilegio Solesmensi parata. Paris: A. Jouby et Roger, 1876–1891. google.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:plested-2004</IRI>
         <name>Plested 2004</name>
         <desc>Plested, Marcus. “Macarius and Evagrius.”  In The Macarian Legacy: The Place of Macarius-Symeon in the Eastern Christian Tradition, pp. 59–71. Oxford Theological Monographs. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:prieur-1993</IRI>
         <name>Prieur 1993</name>
         <desc>Prieur, J. M. “From Prayer to Perfection.” Etudes Theologiques et Religieuses 68, no. 1 (1993): 142–43.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:puech-1972</IRI>
         <name>Puech 1972</name>
         <desc>Puech, H-Ch. “[Dans] Bulletin de la Société Ernest-Renan.” Revue de l'Histoire des Religions 181 (1972): 118–20.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:quasten-1950</IRI>
         <name>Quasten 1950-1986</name>
         <name>quasten 1950</name>
         <desc>Quasten, Johannes. Patrology. Westminster, Md.: Newman Press, 1950–1986. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:quecke-1989</IRI>
         <name>Quecke 1989</name>
         <desc>Quecke, Hans. “Auszüge aus Evagrius' Mönchsspiegel in koptischer Übersetzung.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 58, no. 4 (1989): 453–63.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:raasch-1970</IRI>
         <name>Raasch 1970</name>
         <desc>Raasch, Juana. “The Monastic Concept of Purity of Heart and its Sources. [Part 5] Symeon-Macarius, the School of Evagrius Ponticus, and the Apophthegmata Patrum.” Studia Monastica 12 (1970): 7–41.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rahner-1932</IRI>
         <name>Rahner 1932</name>
         <desc>Rahner, Karl. “Le début d'une doctrine des cinq sens spirituels chez Origène.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 13 (1932): 113–45.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rahner-1933</IRI>
         <name>Rahner 1933</name>
         <desc>Rahner, Karl. “Die geistliche Lehre des Evagrius Pontikus.” Zeitschrift für Aszese und Mystik 8 (1933): 21–38.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-2012</IRI>
         <name>Ramelli July 17, 2012</name>
         <name>ramelli 2012</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Ilaria L. E. “The Syriac version S2 of Evagrius’ Kephalaia Gnostica. Toward a New Edition, Translation, and Commentary.” Symposium Syriacum, Malta, July 17, 2012</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-2013a</IRI>
         <name>ramelli 2013a</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Ilaria L. E. “Harmony between Arkhē and Telos in Patristic Platonism and the Imagery of Astronomical Harmony Applied to Apokatastasis 1.” The International Journal of the Platonic Tradition 7, no. 1 (2013): 1–49.brillonline.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-2013b</IRI>
         <name>ramelli 2013b</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Ilaria L. E. “Origen's Apologists and Followers, the Cappadocians, Evagrius, the Antiochenes, and Fourth-Century Latin Origenians.”  In The Christian Doctrine of Apokatastasis: A Critical Assessment from the New Testament to Eriugena, pp. 279–658. Supplements to Vigiliae Christianae 120. Leiden and Boston: Brill, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-2013c</IRI>
         <name>ramelli 2013c</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Ilaria L. E. “Evagrius and Gregory: Nazianzen or Nyssen? Cappadocian (and Origenian) Influence on Evagrius.” Greek Roman and Byzantine Studies 53, no. 1 (2013): 117–137.duke.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-2013d</IRI>
         <name>ramelli 2013d</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Ilaria L. E. “A Rhetorical Device in Evagrius: Allegory, the Bible, and Apokatastasis.”  In The Purpose of Rhetoric in Late Antiquity: From Performance to Exegesis, pp. 55–69. Studien und Texte zu Antike und Christentum / Studies and Texts in Antiquity and Christianity 72. Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-2013e</IRI>
         <name>ramelli 2013e</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Ilaria L. E. “"Preexistence of Souls"? The Arche and Telos of Rational Creatures in Origen and Some Origenians.” Studia Patristica 56 (2013): 167–226.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:1-62837-041-6</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-1-62837-041-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-2015</IRI>
         <name>Ramelli 2015</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Ilaria L. E. Evagrius's Kephalaia Gnostica: A New Translation of the Unreformed Text from the Syriac. Writings from the Greco-Roman World. Atlanta: SBL Press, 2015. amazon.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-2017</IRI>
         <name>Ramelli, Tarrant, Layne, Baltzly, and Renaud 2017</name>
         <name>ramelli 2017</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Ilaria L. E. “Origen to Evagrius.”  In Brill's Companion to the Reception of Plato in Antiquity. Edited by Harold Tarrant, Danielle A. Layne, Dirk Baltzly, and François Renaud, pp. 271–291. Brill's companions to classical reception 13. Boston: Brill, 2017. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-1-59333-694-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramelli-konstan-2007</IRI>
         <name>Ramelli and Konstan 2007</name>
         <name>ramelli konstan 2007</name>
         <desc>Ramelli, Illaria and Konstan, David. Terms for Eternity: Aiônios and Aïdios in Classical and Christian Texts. [n.p.]: Gorgias Press, 2007. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ramfos</IRI>
         <name>Ramfos and Raffan n.p.</name>
         <name>ramfos</name>
         <desc>Ramfos, Stelios. “The Head and Corner Stone: Evagrius Ponticus.”  In Inconceivable Nothingness: The Philokalia and the Roots of Modern Greek Nihilism; An Essay in Philosophical Anthropology, pp. 62–126. n.p.: n.p, n.p. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rappe-2001</IRI>
         <name>Rappe and Too 2001</name>
         <name>rappe 2001</name>
         <desc>Rappe, Sarah. “The New Math: How to Add and to Subtract Pagan Elements in Christian Education.”  In Education in Greek and Roman Antiquity, pp. 405–432. Leiden: Brill, 2001. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:refoulé-1961a</IRI>
         <name>refoulé 1961a</name>
         <desc>Refoulé, François. “La christologie d'Évagre et l'Origénisme.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 27 (1961): 221–66.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:refoulé-1961b</IRI>
         <name>refoulé 1961b</name>
         <desc>Refoulé, François. “La date de la lettre à Évagre (P.G. 46, 1101–1108).” Recherches de Science Religieuse 49 (1961): 520–48.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:refoulé-1961c</IRI>
         <name>refoulé 1961c</name>
         <desc>Refoulé, François. “Rêves et vie spirituelle d'après Évagre le Pontique.” Supplément de la Vie Spirituelle 59 (1961): 470–516.bnf.fr</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:refoulé-1963a</IRI>
         <name>refoulé 1963a</name>
         <desc>Refoulé, François. “Évagre fut-il Origéniste.” Revue des Sciences Philosophiques et Théologiques 47 (1963): 398–402.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:refoulé-1963b</IRI>
         <name>refoulé 1963b</name>
         <desc>Refoulé, François. “Immortalité de l'âme et résurrection de la chair.” Revue de l'Histoire des Religions 163 (1963): 11–52.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:refoulé-1963c</IRI>
         <name>refoulé 1963c</name>
         <desc>Refoulé, François. “La mystique d'Évagre et l'Origénisme.” Supplément de la Vie Spirituelle 66 (1963): 453–63.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:regnault-1963</IRI>
         <IRI>http://lccn.loc.gov/67007974</IRI>
         <name>Dorotheus of Gaza, Regnault, and Préville 1963</name>
         <name>SC 92</name>
         <name>regnault 1963</name>
         <desc>Dorotheus of Gaza. Oeuvres spirituelles. Sources chrétiennes 92. Paris: Éditions du Cerf, 1963. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-85274-016-8</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:regnault-1976</IRI>
         <name>Regnault 1976</name>
         <desc>Regnault, Lucien. Les Sentences des Pères du désert: Troisième recueil &amp; tables. Sablé-sur-Sarthe: Abbaye Saint-Pierre de Solesmes, 1976. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-85274-112-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:regnault-1987</IRI>
         <name>Regnault 1987</name>
         <desc>Regnault, Lucien. Les Pères du désert: À travers leurs apophtegmes. Sablé-sur-Sarthe: Abbaye Saint-Pierre de Solesmes, 1987. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-01-015832-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:regnault-1990</IRI>
         <name>Regnault 1990</name>
         <desc>Regnault, Lucien. La vie quotidienne des pères du désert en Egypte au IVe siècle. Paris: Hachette, 1990. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:1879007347</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:regnault-1999</IRI>
         <name>Regnault 1999</name>
         <desc>Regnault, Lucien. The Day-to-Day Life of the Desert Fathers in Fourth-Century Egypt. Petersham, Mass.: St. Bede's Publications, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:regnault-dion-oury-1966</IRI>
         <name>Regnault, Dion, and Oury 1966</name>
         <name>regnault dion oury 1966</name>
         <desc>Regnault, Lucien, Dion, Jean, and Oury, Guy Marie. Les Sentences des Pères du désert, les apophtegmes des Pères (recension de Pélage et Jean). Solesmes: Abbaye Saint-Pierre de Solesmes, 1966. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-1-84227-431-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rich-2007</IRI>
         <name>Rich 2007</name>
         <desc>Rich, Antony D. Discernment in the Desert Fathers: Diákrisis in the Life and Thought of Early Egyptian Monasticism. Studies in Christian History and Thought. Milton Keynes: Paternoster, 2007. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rich-2010</IRI>
         <name>Rich 2010</name>
         <desc>Rich, Antony D. “Discerning Evagrius Ponticus Discerning: Διάκρισις in the Works   of Evagrius.” Studia Patristica 47 (2010): 203–208.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:robinette-2012</IRI>
         <name>Robinette, Pfeil, and Winwright 2012</name>
         <name>robinette 2012</name>
         <desc>Robinette, Brian. “Deceit, Desire, and the Desert: René Girard’s Mimetic Theory in Conversation with Early Christian Monastic Practice.”  In Violence, Transformation, and the Sacred: "They Shall Be Called Children of God". Edited by Margaret R. Pfeil and Tobias L. Winwright. The annual publication of the College Theology Society 57. Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 2012. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rondeau-1960</IRI>
         <name>Rondeau 1960</name>
         <desc>Rondeau, Marie-Josèphe. “Le commentaire sur les Psaumes d'Évagre le Pontique.” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 26 (1960): 307–48.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rondeau-1982</IRI>
         <name>Rondeau 1982-1985</name>
         <name>rondeau 1982</name>
         <desc>Rondeau, Marie-Josèphe. Les commentaires patristiques du Psautier: IIIe-Ve siècles. Orientalia Christiana analecta 219–220. Rome: Pont. Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1982–1985. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rondeau-2021</IRI>
         <name>Rondeau 2021</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Scholies aux Psaumes. Edited by Marie-Josèphe Rondeau, Paul Géhin, and Matthieu Cassin. 2 vols. Sources chrétiennes 614-615. Paris: Les Éditions du Cerf, 2021.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rondeau-2021a</IRI>
         <name>Rondeau 2021a</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Scholies aux Psaumes I, Psaumes 1-70. Edited by Marie-Josèphe Rondeau, Paul Géhin, and Matthieu Cassin. Sources chrétiennes 614. Paris: Les Éditions du Cerf, 2021.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rondeau-2021b</IRI>
         <name>Rondeau 2021b</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Scholies aux Psaumes II, Psaumes 71-150. Edited by Marie-Josèphe Rondeau, Paul Géhin, and Matthieu Cassin. Sources chrétiennes 615. Paris: Les Éditions du Cerf, 2021.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rozumna-2017</IRI>
         <name>Rozumna 2017</name>
         <desc>Rozumna, Yulia. “"Be Angry and Do Not Sin": Human Anger in Evagrius of Pontus and Gregory of Nyssa.” Studia Patristica 82 (2017): .academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rubenson-1993</IRI>
         <name>Rubenson, Abramowski, Brennecke, Grasmück, and Markschies 1993</name>
         <name>rubenson 1993</name>
         <desc>Rubenson, Samuel. “Evagrios Pontikos und die Theologie der Wüste.”  In Logos: Festschrift für Luise Abramowski zum 8. Juli 1993, pp. 384–401. Beihefte zur Zeitschrift für die neutestamentliche Wissenschaft und die Kunde der älteren Kirche 67. Berlin: W. de Gruyter, 1993. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:rydell-johnsén-2010</IRI>
         <name>Rydell Johnsén, Stenqvist, and Lindstedt Cronberg 2010</name>
         <name>rydell johnsén 2010</name>
         <desc>Rydell Johnsén, Henrik. “Dödssyndernas genealogi: Evagrios Pontikos åtta onda grundtankar och det antika arvet [The Genealogy of the Cardinal Sins: The Eight Thoughts of Evagrius Ponticus and the Heritage from Antiquity].”  In Dygder och laster: Förmoderna perspektiv på tillvaron. Edited by Catharina Stenqvist and Marie Lindstedt Cronberg, pp. 23–38. Lund: Nordic Academic Press, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:samir-1992</IRI>
         <name>Samir, Rassart-Debergh, and Ries 1992</name>
         <name>samir 1992</name>
         <desc>Samir, Khalil. “Évagre le Pontique dans la tradition arabo-copte.”  In Actes du IVe Congrès copte: Louvain-la-Neuve, 5–10 septembre 1988. Edited by Marguerite Rassart-Debergh and Julien Ries, pp. 125–153. Publications de l'Institut orientaliste de Louvain 40. Louvain-la-Neue: Université catholique de Louvain, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:samuel-1986</IRI>
         <name>Samuel 1986</name>
         <desc>Samuel, Bishop. Mayāmir Mār Ūghrīs. Cairo: al-Naʿām li-al-Ṭibāʿah wa al-Tawrīdāt, 1986. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:sargisean-1907</IRI>
         <name>Evagrius Ponticus and Sargisean 1907</name>
         <name>sargisean 1907</name>
         <desc>Evagrius Ponticus. Varkʻ ew matenagrutʻiwnkʻ: Tʻargmanealkʻ i hunē i hay barbaṛ i E. daru. Venice: S. Ghazar, 1907. archive.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:schenke-1984</IRI>
         <name>Schenke and Nagel 1984</name>
         <name>schenke 1984</name>
         <desc>Schenke, H.-M. “Ein koptischer Evagrius.”  In Graeco-Coptica: Griechen und Kopten im byzantinischen Ägypten, pp. 219–230. Wissenschaftliche Beiträge der Martin-Luther-Universität Halle- Wittenberg. Reihe I 29. Halle (Saale): Martin-Luther-Universität [Abt. Wissenschaftlichspublizistik], 1984. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:schenke-1989</IRI>
         <name>Schenke 1989</name>
         <desc>Schenke, H-M. “Das Berliner Evagrius-Ostrakon (P. Berol. 14700).” Zeitschrift für ägyptische Sprache und Altertumskunde 116 (1989): 90–107.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:schuster-1902</IRI>
         <name>Schuster 1902</name>
         <desc>Schuster, D Ildefonso. “Della basilica di San Martino e di alcuni Ricordi Farfensi.” Nuovo bullettino di archeologia cristiana 8 (1902): 47–54.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:scully-2009</IRI>
         <name>Scully 2009</name>
         <desc>Scully, Jason. “The Transmission of Evagrian Theological Concepts into East Syrian Christianity: A Comparison of Evagrius and Sahdona on Contemplation and Anthropology.” Greek Orthodox Theological Review 54, no. 1–4 (2009): 77–96.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:scully-2011</IRI>
         <name>Scully 2011</name>
         <desc>Scully, Jason. “Angelic Pneumatology in the Egyptian Desert: The Role of the Angels and the Holy Spirit in Evagrian Asceticism.” Journal of Early Christian Studies 19, no. 2 (2011): 287–305.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-8006-2765-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:shaw-1998</IRI>
         <name>Shaw 1998</name>
         <desc>Shaw, Teresa M. The Burden of the Flesh: Fasting and Sexuality in Early Christianity. Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 1998. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:sheridan-2009</IRI>
         <name>Sheridan OSB 2009</name>
         <name>sheridan 2009</name>
         <desc>Sheridan OSB, Mark. “Mapping the Intellectual Genome of Early Christian Monasticism.”  In Church, Society and Monasticism: Acts of the International Symposium, Rome, May 31–June 3, 2006, pp. 313–340. Studia Anselmiana. Rome: Centro studi S. Anselmo, 2009. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-8306-7558-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:sheridan-2012</IRI>
         <name>Sheridan OSB 2012</name>
         <name>sheridan 2012</name>
         <desc>Sheridan OSB, Mark. From the Nile to the Rhone and Beyond; Studies in early monastic literature and scriptural interpretation. Studia Anselmiana. [n.p.]: Pontificio Ateneo Sant'Anselmo, 2012. google.it</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:sidorov-1994</IRI>
         <name>Sidorov 1994</name>
         <desc>Sidorov, A. I. “Евагрий Понтийский: жизнь, литературная деятельность и место в истории христианского богословия.”  In Творения аввы Евагрия, pp. 5–75. Moscow: Martis, 1994. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:simonetti-2000</IRI>
         <name>Simonetti and Bettiolo 2000</name>
         <name>simonetti 2000</name>
         <desc>Simonetti, M. “Dibattito trinitario e tensioni ecclesiali in Cappadecia e Ponto dal 360 al 380.”  In L'epistula fidei di Evagrio Pontico: Temi, contesti, sviluppi; Atti del III convegno del gruppo italiano di ricerca su "Origene e la tradizione alessandrina". Edited by Paolo Bettiolo, pp. 7–24. Studia Ephemeridis Augustinianum 72. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:sims-williams-1985</IRI>
         <name>Sims-Williams 1985</name>
         <desc>Sims-Williams, Nicholas. The Christian Sogdian Manuscript C2. Schriften zur Geschichte und Kultur des alten Orients. Berliner Turfantexte 12. Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 1985. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:1-59473-103-9</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:smith-2006</IRI>
         <name>Smith 2006</name>
         <desc>Smith, Allyne. Philokalia: The Eastern Christian Spiritual Texts: Selections Annotated &amp; Explained. SkyLight illuminations. Woodstock, Vt.: SkyLight Paths Pub, 2006. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:smither-2011</IRI>
         <name>Smither October 2011</name>
         <name>smither 2011</name>
         <desc>Smither, Edward. “Lessons from a Tentmaking Ascetic in the Egyptian Desert: The Case of Evagrius  of Pontus.” Missiology: An International Review 39, no. no. 4 (October 2011): 485–496.liberty.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-204-08170-1</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-204-08170-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:socrates-2006</IRI>
         <name>Socrates, Périchon, and Maraval 2006</name>
         <name>SC 505</name>
         <name>socrates 2006</name>
         <desc>Socrates. Histoire ecclésiastique. Livres IV-VI. Sources chrétiennes 505. Paris: Éditions du Cerf, 2006. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:somos-1999</IRI>
         <name>Somos, Bienert, and Kühneweg 1999</name>
         <name>somos 1999</name>
         <desc>Somos, Robert. “Origen, Evagrius Ponticus and the Ideal of Impassibility.”  In Origeniana septima: Origenes in den Auseinandersetzungen des 4. Jahrhunderts, pp. 365–73. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 137. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:sorabji-2000</IRI>
         <name>Sorabji 2000</name>
         <desc>Sorabji, Richard. “From First Movements to the Seven Cardinal Sins Evagrius.”  In Emotion and Peace of Mind, pp. 357–371. [n.p.]: Oxford University Press, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-204-07918-9</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-204-07918-1</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:sozomen-495</IRI>
         <name>Sozomen, Bidez, Festugière, Grillet, and Sabbah 2005</name>
         <name>SC 495</name>
         <name>sozomen 495</name>
         <desc>Sozomen. Histoire ecclésiastique: Livres V-VI. Sources chrétiennes 495. Paris: Éditions du Cerf, 2005. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:spanu-2015</IRI>
         <name>Spanu 2015</name>
         <desc>Spanu, Nicola. “The Method of Unceasing Prayer in Evagrius Ponticus and John Cassian.” E-Patrologos 1–2 (2015): 46–59.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-631-60314-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:sperber-hartmann-2011</IRI>
         <name>Sperber-Hartmann 2011</name>
         <desc>Sperber-Hartmann, Doris. Das Gebet als Aufstieg zu Gott: Untersuchungen zur Schrift de oratione des Evagrius Ponticus. Early Christianity in the Context of Antiquity 10. Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:spies-1932</IRI>
         <name>Spies 1932</name>
         <desc>Spies, Otto. “Die äthiopische Überlieferung der Abhandlung des Evagrius Peri okto logismon.” Oriens Christianus 29 (1932): 203–28.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:spiteris-1997</IRI>
         <name>Spiteris 1997</name>
         <desc>Spiteris, Yannis. “La Conoscenza 'Esperienziale' di Dio et la teologia nella prospettiva orientale.” Antonianum 72 (1997): 365–426.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:spörri-1964</IRI>
         <name>Spörri, Gärtner, Sontheimer, and Ziegler 1964-1975</name>
         <name>spörri 1964</name>
         <desc>Spörri, W. “Gnome.”  In Der Kleine Pauly: Lexikon der Antike, pp. 822–829. Munich: Druckenmüller, 1964–1975. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stadler-1994</IRI>
         <name>Stadler 1994</name>
         <desc>Stadler, Karin. “Méditation crétienne et techniques de méditation orientale.” Esprit et Vie. L'ami du Clergé 104 (1994): 593–608.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stefaniw-2007</IRI>
         <name>Stefaniw 2007</name>
         <desc>Stefaniw, Blossom. “Evagrius Ponticus on Image and Material.” Cistercian Studies Quarterly 42, no. 2 (2007): 125–35.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-631-60267-6</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-631-60267-7</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stefaniw-2010a</IRI>
         <name>stefaniw 2010a</name>
         <desc>Stefaniw, Blossom. Mind, Text, and Commentary: Noetic Exegesis in Origen of Alexandria, Didymus the Blind, and Evagrius Ponticus. Early Christianity in the Context of Antiquity 6. Frankfurt am Main: Lang, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stefaniw-2010b</IRI>
         <name>stefaniw 2010b</name>
         <desc>Stefaniw, Blossom. “Exegetical Curricula in Origen, Didymus, and Evagrius: Pedagogical Agenda and the Case for Neoplatonist Influence.” Studia Patristica 44 (2010): 281–294.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stefaniw-2016</IRI>
         <name>Stefaniw 2016</name>
         <desc>Stefaniw, Blossom. “Evagrius and Authority.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 96–127. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-585-22093-X</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-1998</IRI>
         <name>Stewart 1998</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. Cassian the Monk. Oxford Studies in Historical Theology. New York: Oxford University Press, 1998. netlibrary.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-2000</IRI>
         <name>Stewart and Valantasis 2000</name>
         <name>stewart 2000</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. “Evagrius on Prayer and Anger.”  In Religions of Late Antiquity in Practice. Edited by Richard Valantasis, pp. 71–80. Princeton Readings in Religions. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 2000. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-2001a</IRI>
         <name>Stewart 2001</name>
         <name>stewart 2001a</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. “Imageless Prayer and the Theological Vision of Evagrius Ponticus.” Journal of Early Christian Studies 9, no. 2 (2001): 173–204.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-2001b</IRI>
         <name>Stewart 2011</name>
         <name>stewart 2001b</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. “Evagrius Ponticus and the Eastern Monastic Tradition on the Intellect and the Passions.” “”  (2011): 263–275.wiley.comacademia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-2003a</IRI>
         <name>Stewart, Behr, Louth, and Conomos 2003</name>
         <name>stewart 2003a</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. “Evagrius Ponticus on Monastic Pedagogy.”  In Abba: The Tradition of Orthodoxy in the West; Festschrift for Bishop Kallistos (Ware) of Diokleia, pp. 241–271. Crestwood, N.Y.: St. Vladimir's Seminary Press, 2003. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-2003b</IRI>
         <name>Stewart, Bădiliță, and Jakab 2003</name>
         <name>stewart 2003b</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. “John Cassian’s Schema of Eight Principal Faults and His Debt to Origen and Evagrius.”  In Jean Cassien entre l'orient et l'occident: Actes du colloque international organisé par le New Europe College en collaboration avec la Ludwig Boltzman Gesellschaft, Bucarest, 27–28 septembre 2001. Edited by Cristian Bădiliță and Attila Jakab, pp. 205–219. Paris: Beauchesne, 2003. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-2008</IRI>
         <name>Stewart and Hammerling 2008</name>
         <name>stewart 2008</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. “Imageless Prayer and the Theological Vision of Evagrius Ponticus.”  In A History of Prayer: The First to the Fifteenth Century. Edited by Roy Hammerling, pp. 137–166. Leiden: Brill, 2008. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-2010</IRI>
         <name>Stewart 2010</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. “Monastic Attitudes Toward Philosophy and Philosophers.” Studia Patristica 44 (2010): 321–327.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stewart-2016</IRI>
         <name>Stewart 2016</name>
         <desc>Stewart, Columba. “Evagrius beyond Byzantium: The Latin and Syriac Reception.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 206–235. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:2-87723-301-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:stone-1997</IRI>
         <name>Stone 1997</name>
         <desc>Stone, Nira. The Kaffa Lives of the Desert Fathers: A Study in Armenian Manuscript Illumination. Corpus scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 566. Louvain: Peeters, 1997. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tarchnisvili-1958</IRI>
         <name>Tarchnisvili 1958</name>
         <desc>Tarchnisvili, Michael. “Il monachismo Georgiano nelle sue origini e nei suoi primi sviluppi.” Orientalia Christiana Analecta 153 (1958): 307–19.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:theophanes-2006</IRI>
         <name>(Constantine) 2006</name>
         <name>theophanes 2006</name>
         <desc>(Constantine), Theophanes. The Evagrian Ascetical System. Mount Athos: Timios Prodromos, 2006. blogspot.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:theophanes-2008</IRI>
         <name>Theophanes (Constantine) 2008–</name>
         <name>theophanes 2008</name>
         <desc>Theophanes (Constantine). “To the Caesareans.” [n.p.]: [n.p.], 2008–. blogspot.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-8126-9211-X</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:thunberg-1995</IRI>
         <name>Thunberg and Allchin 1995</name>
         <name>thunberg 1995</name>
         <desc>Thunberg, Lars. Microcosm and Mediator: The Theological Anthropology of Maximus the Confessor. Chicago: Open Court, 1995. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tilby-2005</IRI>
         <name>Tilby, Sugirtharajah, and Harvey 2005</name>
         <name>tilby 2005</name>
         <desc>Tilby, Angela. “From Evil Thoughts to Deadly Sins: Evagrius of Pontus's Psychology of Sin.”  In Wilderness: Essays in Honour of Frances Young. Library of New Testament Studies 295. London: T &amp; T Clark International, 2005. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-0-281-05632-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tilby-2009</IRI>
         <name>Tilby 2009</name>
         <desc>Tilby, Angela. The Seven Deadly Sins: Their Origin in the Spiritual Teaching of Evagrius the Hermit. London: Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, 2009. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-8370-9511-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tischendorf-1860</IRI>
         <name>Tischendorf and Origen 1860</name>
         <name>tischendorf 1860</name>
         <desc>Tischendorf, Constantin von and Origen. Notitia editionis codicis bibliorum Sinaitici auspiciis Imperatoris Alexandri II. susceptae: Accedit catalogus codicum nuper ex oriente Petropolin perlatorum; Item Origenis Scholia in Proverbia Salomonis; Partim nunc primum partim secundum atque emendatius edita. ATLA Historical Monographs Collection, Series 1 (13th Century to 1893). Leipzig: F.A. Brockhaus, 1860. harvard.eduarchive.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0524051429</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tischendorf-1960</IRI>
         <name>Diekamp 1899</name>
         <name>tischendorf 1960</name>
         <desc>Diekamp, Franz. Die Origenistischen Streitigkeiten im sechsten Jahrhundert und das fünfte allgemeine Concil. ATLA Historical Monographs Collection. Series 2 (1894–1923). Münster i. W.: Aschendorff, 1899. harvard.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tiso-2005</IRI>
         <name>Tiso 2005</name>
         <desc>Tiso, Francis. “Evagrius of Pontus and Buddhist Abhidharma.” Religion East &amp; West 5 (2005): 41–72.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2010</IRI>
         <name>Tobon 2010</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “The Health of the Soul: Ἀπάθεια in Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Patristica 47 (2010): 187–202.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2011a</IRI>
         <name>tobon 2011a</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “Apatheia in the Teachings of Evagrius Ponticus.” thesis. University College London, 2011. ac.uk</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2011b</IRI>
         <name>Tobon, Kaczmarek, and Pietras 2011</name>
         <name>tobon 2011b</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “Evagrius as Writer: The Example of Eulogios 2's Discussion of Xeniteia.”  In Origeniana Decima: Origen as Writer; Papers of the 10th International Origen Congress, University School of Philosophy and Education "ignatianum", Kraków, Poland, 31 August-4 September 2009. Edited by Sylwia Kaczmarek and Henryk Pietras, pp. 765–778. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 244. Leuven: Peeters, 2011. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2011c</IRI>
         <name>tobon 2011c</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “Letting our Light Shine into the Heavens: The Spirituality of Evagrius.”  In Ex Corde: Franciscan Studies in Theology, pp. 101–121. Canterbury: Franciscan International Study Centre, 2011. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2013a</IRI>
         <name>tobon 2013a</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “Evagrius Ponticus on Contemplation: Introduction.” Studia Patristica 57 (2013): .</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2013b</IRI>
         <name>tobon 2013b</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “From Evagrian Prayer to Centering Prayer.”  In Proceedings of the Colloquium Origenianum Undecimum: Origen and Origenism in the History of Western Thought. Leuven: Peeters, 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2013c</IRI>
         <name>tobon 2013c</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “Raising Body and Soul to the Order of the Nous: Anthropology and Contemplation in Evagrius Ponticus.” Studia Patristica 57 (2013): 51–74.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2014</IRI>
         <name>Tobon 2014</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “Words Spoken in Silence: the "Missing Chapters" of Evagrius’ Kephalaia Gnostika.” Studia Patristica 72 (2014): .academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2017</IRI>
         <name>Tobon 2017</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. “Two Poor Ones in the Desert: Vestiges of Evagrius in Bonaventure&amp;#39;s Itinerarium.” Studii Franciscane: Revista Institutuli Teologic Romano-Catolic Franciscan 17 (2017): .academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tobon-2020</IRI>
         <name>Tobon 2020</name>
         <desc>Tobon, Monica. Apatheia and Anthropology in Evagrius of Pontus: Restoring the Image of God. [n.p.]: Routledge, 2020. academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:toda-2001</IRI>
         <name>Toda 2001</name>
         <desc>Toda, Satoshi. “Les Apophthegmata patrum et Évagre le Pontique.” Mediterranean World 16 (2001): 77–87.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tondello-2014</IRI>
         <name>Tondello 2014</name>
         <desc>Tondello, M. “Babai il grande e il santo Evagrio.” Adamantius 20 (2014): 389–395.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:torevell-2012</IRI>
         <name>Torevell, Schmack, Thompson, and Torevell 2012</name>
         <name>torevell 2012</name>
         <desc>Torevell, David. “Like a Jar of Wine Left in Its Place for a While . . . Clear, Settled and Perfumed”: Evagrius of Pontus and the Purifying Engagement of Stillness.”  In Engaging Religious Education. Edited by Joy Schmack, Matthew Thompson, and David Torevell, pp. 171–184. Liverpool Hope University Studies in Ethics. Newcastle: Cambridge Scholars, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:1-60899-066-4</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-1-60899-066-5</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tsakiridis-2010</IRI>
         <name>Tsakiridis 2010</name>
         <desc>Tsakiridis, George. Evagrius Ponticus and Cognitive Science: A Look at Moral Evil and the Thoughts. Eugene, Or.: Wipf and Stock, 2010. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tsirpanlis-1987</IRI>
         <name>Tsirpanlis 1987</name>
         <desc>Tsirpanlis, Constantine N. “The Unity of Mankind and Ecclesial Koinonia in Early Ascetic Theology.” Patristic and Byzantine Review 6.3 (1987): 173–98.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tsirpanlis-1988</IRI>
         <name>Tsirpanlis 1988</name>
         <desc>Tsirpanlis, Constantine N. “Ο εσωτερικός πόλεμος στην ασκητική εμπείρια του τετάρτου αιώνα: Αγίου Μακαρίου του Αιγύπτου και Ευαγρίου του Ποντικού.” Patristic and Byzantine Review 7, no. 2–3 (1988): 149–83.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-87243-136-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tugwell-1985</IRI>
         <name>Tugwell 1985</name>
         <desc>Tugwell, Simon. Ways of Imperfection: An Exploration of Christian Spirituality. Springfield, Ill.: Templegate, 1985. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tugwell-1986</IRI>
         <name>Tugwell, Jones, Wainwright, and Yarnold 1986</name>
         <name>tugwell 1986</name>
         <desc>Tugwell, Simon. “Evagrius and Macarius.”  In The Study of Spirituality, pp. 168–175. New York: Oxford University Press, 1986. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:turner-1904</IRI>
         <name>Turner 1904</name>
         <desc>Turner, Cuthbert Hamilton. “The Lausiac History of Palladius.” The Journal of Theological Studies 6 (1904): 321–55.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:turner-1975</IRI>
         <name>Turner 1975</name>
         <desc>Turner, Henry J M. “Evagrius Ponticus, Teacher of Prayer.” Eastern Churches Review 7, no. 2 (1975): 145–48.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9789004224414</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tzamalikos-2012a</IRI>
         <name>Cassian the Sabaite and Tzamalikos 2012</name>
         <name>tzamalikos 2012a</name>
         <desc>Cassian the Sabaite and Tzamalikos, Panagiōtēs. A Newly Discovered Greek Father: Cassian the Sabaite Eclipsed by John Cassian of Marseilles. Supplements to Vigiliae Christianae. Leiden and Boston: Brill, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:9789004224407</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:tzamalikos-2012b</IRI>
         <name>Tzamalikos 2012</name>
         <name>tzamalikos 2012b</name>
         <desc>Tzamalikos, Panagiōtēs. The Real Cassian Revisited: Monastic Life, Greek Paideia, and Origenism in the Sixth Century. Supplements to Vigiliae Christianae. Leiden and Boston: Brill, 2012. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:utheman-1999</IRI>
         <name>Utheman, Bienert, and Kühneweg 1999</name>
         <name>utheman 1999</name>
         <desc>Utheman, Karl-Heinz. “Protologie und Eschatologie: Zur Rezeption des Origenes im 4. Jahrhundert vor dem Ausbruch der ersten origenistischen Kontroverse.”  In Origeniana septima: Origenes in den Auseinandersetzungen des 4. Jahrhunderts, pp. 399–458. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 137. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vadakkekara-1980</IRI>
         <name>Vadakkekara 1980</name>
         <desc>Vadakkekara, C. M. “Evagrius on Prayer.”  In Prayer and Contemplation, pp. 27–55. Studies in Christian and Hindu Spirituality 1. Bangalore: Asirvanam Benedictine Monastery, 1980. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:van-dam-1995</IRI>
         <name>Van Dam 1995</name>
         <desc>Van Dam, Raymond. “Self-Representation in the Will of Gregory of Nazianzus.” Journal of Theological Studies 46 (1995): 118–48.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:van-den-ven-1908</IRI>
         <name>van den Ven 1908</name>
         <desc>van den Ven, P. “Un opuscule inédit attribué à S. Nil.” Mémoires littéraires, philologiques et archéologiques 2 (1908): 73–81.archive.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vasquez-1982</IRI>
         <name>Vasquez 1982</name>
         <desc>Vasquez, Michel F. “The Gnosis of Space and Time in Evagrius of Ponticus: A Preliminary Investigation.” thesis. Graduate Theological Union, 1982. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vasquez-2011</IRI>
         <name>Vasquez 2011</name>
         <desc>Vasquez, Michel F. “Evagrius and the Naked Nous.” From Bodhgaya to the Cuyahoga 1 (2011): 49–73.fbttc.org</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:viller-1930</IRI>
         <name>Viller 1930</name>
         <desc>Viller, Marcel. “Aux sources de la spiritualité de S. Maxime: Les oeuvres d'Évagre le Pontique.” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 11 (1930): 156–84; 239–68; 331–36.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:viller-1942</IRI>
         <name>Viller 1942</name>
         <desc>Viller, Marcel. “Autour de la spiritualité Byzantine.” Bulletin de Littérature Ecclésiastique 43 (1942): 169–79.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-451-21463-6</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:viller-1990</IRI>
         <name>Viller, Rahner, and Neufeld 1990</name>
         <name>viller 1990</name>
         <desc>Viller, Marcel. Aszese und Mystik in der Väterzeit: Ein Abriss der frühchristlichen Spiritualität. Freiburg im Breisgau: Herder, 1990. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:villeux-1986</IRI>
         <name>Villeux, Goehring, and Pearson 1986</name>
         <name>villeux 1986</name>
         <desc>Villeux, A. “Monasticism and Gnosis in Egypt.”  In The Roots of Egyptian Christianity, pp. 271–306. Studies in Antiquity and Christianity. Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1986. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-2-87296-006-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vittis-1997</IRI>
         <name>Vittis and Evagrius 1997</name>
         <name>vittis 1997</name>
         <desc>Vittis, Eusebios N. and Evagrius. "Aux cimes de l'intelligible..": "le Traité de la prière" de Saint Nil l'Ascète = Titre grec, "Eis ypsos moēton.." : "Logos peri proseuchēs" tou 'Agiou Neilou tou' Askētou. [n.p.]: [n.p.], 1997. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vivian-2000</IRI>
         <name>Vivian 2000</name>
         <desc>Vivian, Tim. “Coptic Palladiana II: The Life of Evagrius (Lausiac History 38).” Coptic Church Review 21, no. 1 (2000): 8–23.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0881412562</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vivian-2004</IRI>
         <name>Vivian and Greer 2004</name>
         <name>vivian 2004</name>
         <desc>Vivian, Tim. Four Desert Fathers: Pambo, Evagrius, Macarius of Egypt, and Macarius of Alexandria: Coptic Texts Relating to the Lausiac History of Palladius. Popular Patristics. Crestwood, N.Y.: St Vladimir's Seminary Press, 2004. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vogüé-1973</IRI>
         <name>Vogüé 1973</name>
         <desc>Vogüé, Adalbert de. “L'anecdote Pachômienne du 'Vaticanus Graecus' 2091. Son origine et ses sources.” Revue d'Histoire de la Spiritualité 49 (1973): 401–19.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vogüé-1984</IRI>
         <name>Vogüé 1984</name>
         <desc>Vogüé, Adalbert de. “La lecture du matin dans les sentences d'Évagre et le de Virginitate attribué à Saint Athanase.” Studia Monastica 26, no. 1 (1984): 7–11.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vogüé-1985a</IRI>
         <name>vogüé 1985a</name>
         <desc>Vogüé, Adalbert de. “Les sources des quatre premiers Livres des Institutions de Jean Cassien: Introduction aux recherches sur les anciennes règles monastiques latines.” Studia Monastica 27 (1985): 241–311.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vogüé-1985b</IRI>
         <name>vogüé 1985b</name>
         <desc>Vogüé, Adalbert de. “Un morceau célèbre de Cassien parmi des extraits d'Évagre.” Studia Monastica 27 (1985): 7–12.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vogüé-1989</IRI>
         <name>Vogüé 1989</name>
         <desc>Vogüé, Adalbert de. “Psalmodier n'est pas prier.” Ecclesia Orans 6 (1989): 7–32.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:von-ivanka-1954</IRI>
         <name>von Ivanka 1954</name>
         <desc>von Ivanka, Endre. “KEPHALAIA: Eine byzantinische Literaturform und ihre antiken Wurzeln.” Byzantine Zeitschrift 47 (1954): 285–91.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vázquez-2013</IRI>
         <name>Vázquez 2013</name>
         <desc>Vázquez, Santiago Hernán. “La curación por la palabra: De Platón al primer monacato cristiano.” Cauriensia (Universidad de Extremadura - España) 8 (2013): 459–472.academia.edu</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vázquez-2014</IRI>
         <name>Vázquez 2014</name>
         <desc>Vázquez, Santiago Hernán. “La acedia en Evagrio Póntico y la existencia impropia de Heidegger: Algunas Coincidencias Fenomenológicas Significativas.”  In “Senderos medievales, pasos contemporáneos”. IX Jornadas Nacionales de Filosofía Medieval (CONICET) Buenos Aires, 22 al 24 de abril de 2014. [n.p.]: [n.p.], 2014. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vázquez-2015a</IRI>
         <name>Vázquez and Muñoz 2015</name>
         <name>vázquez 2015a</name>
         <desc>Vázquez, Santiago H. “Acedia y depresión: Manifestaciones fenomenológicas y dinamismo psicológico.”  In El cristianismo frente a los problemas perennes de la filosofía occidental. Edited by Carlos Muñoz. Mendoza: [n.p.], 2015. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vázquez-2015b</IRI>
         <name>Vázquez 2015</name>
         <name>vázquez 2015b</name>
         <desc>Vázquez, Santiago Hernán. “Las implicancias psicopatológicas de la acedia en Evagrio Póntico.” “”  (2015): 679–703.scielo.br</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vázquez-2016</IRI>
         <name>Vázquez 2016</name>
         <desc>Vázquez, Santiago Hernán. “Convergencias fenomenológicas y articulaciones conceptuales entre la acedia evagriana y la caída heideggeriana.” “”  (2016): 197–214.oei.es</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:vögtle-1941</IRI>
         <name>Vögtle 1941</name>
         <desc>Vögtle, Anton. “Woher stammt das Schema der Hauptsünden?.” Theologische Quartalschrift 122 (1941): 217–37.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-87907-959-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ward-1984</IRI>
         <name>Ward 1984</name>
         <desc>The Sayings of the Desert Fathers: The Alphabetical Collection. Translated by Benedicta Ward. Cistercian Studies Series 59. Kalamazoo, Mich.: Cistercian Publications, 1984. evagriusponticus.net</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ware-1999</IRI>
         <name>Ware, Waller, and Ward 1999</name>
         <name>ware 1999</name>
         <desc>Ware, Kallistos. “Prayer in Evagrius of Pontus and the Macarian Homilies.”  In An Introduction to Christian Spirituality, pp. 14–30. London: Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, 1999. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ware-dempf-1985</IRI>
         <name>Ware and Dempf 1985</name>
         <name>ware dempf 1985</name>
         <desc>Ware, Kallistos and Dempf, Alois. “Nous and Noesis in Plato, Aristotle and Evagrius of Pontus: Evagrios Pontikos als Metaphysiker und Mystiker.” Diotima 13 (1985): 158–63.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:wathen-1976</IRI>
         <name>Wathen 1976</name>
         <desc>Wathen, Ambrose. “Methodological Considerations of the Sources of the Regula Benedicti as Instruments of Historical Interpretations.” Regulae Benedicti Studia. Annuarium Internationale 5 (1976): 101–17.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:watson-2013</IRI>
         <name>Watson Feb 2013</name>
         <name>watson 2013</name>
         <desc>Watson, Tony. “Evagrius and the History of Mar Yaballahah: Preliminary Findings on a Virtue Tradition in the Church of the East.”  In From the Oxus River to the Chinese Shores; Studies on East Syriac Christianity in China and Central Asia, pp. 441–456. Munich: Lit Verlag, Feb 2013. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:watson-2016</IRI>
         <name>Watson 2016</name>
         <desc>Watson, Anthony J. “Evagrius East of the Euphrates.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 236–256. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:watt-1980</IRI>
         <name>Watt 1980</name>
         <desc>Watt, John W. “Philoxenus and the Old Syriac Version of Evagrius' Centuries.” Oriens Christianus 64 (1980): 65–81.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:watt-1982</IRI>
         <name>Watt 1982</name>
         <desc>Watt, John W. “The Syriac Adapter of Evagrius' Centuries.” Studia Patristica 17.3 (1982): 1388–95.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:way-1951</IRI>
         <name>Basil of Caesarea and Way 1951</name>
         <name>way 1951</name>
         <desc>Basil of Caesarea and Way, Agnes Clare. Letters. Fathers of the Church 13. Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of America Press, 1951. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:weijenborg-1969</IRI>
         <name>Weijenborg 1969</name>
         <desc>Weijenborg, Reinoud. “Is Evagrius Ponticus the Author of the Longer Recension of the Ignatian Letters?.” Antonianum 44 (1969): 339–47.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:weijenborg-1973</IRI>
         <name>Weijenborg 1973</name>
         <desc>Weijenborg, R. “L’origine evagriana dei “Discorsi Teologici III, IV, V (Discorsi XXIX, XXX, XXXI)”, attríbuiti a Gregorio di Nazianzo.” Augustinianum 13, no. 3 (1973): 551–565.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:weijenborg-1981</IRI>
         <name>Weijenborg, Treu, Paschke, Dummer, and Irmscher 1981</name>
         <name>weijenborg 1981</name>
         <desc>Weijenborg, Reinoud. “Überlieferungsgeschichtliche Bemerkungen zu der Justin dem Märtyrer zugeschriebenen Apologia Secunda.”  In Überlieferungsgeschichtliche Untersuchungen, pp. 593–603. Texte und Untersuchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 125. Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 1981. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:0-691-03940-2</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:weitzmann-1979</IRI>
         <name>Weitzmann 1979</name>
         <desc>Weitzmann, Kurt. The Miniatures of the Sacra Parallela, Parisinus Graecus 923. Studies in manuscript illumination 8. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1979. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:3-0343-1789-1</IRI>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-3-0343-1789-4</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:wellington-2014</IRI>
         <name>Wellington July 18, 2014</name>
         <name>wellington 2014</name>
         <desc>Wellington, James F. Christe Eleison! The Invocation of Christ in Eastern Monastic Psalmody c.350–450. Studies in Eastern Orthodoxy Book 2. Bern, Switerland: Peter Lang, July 18, 2014. amazon.com</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:wenzel-1963</IRI>
         <name>Wenzel 1963</name>
         <desc>Wenzel, Siegfried. “Akedía: Additions to Lampe's Patristic Greek Lexicon.” Vigiliae Christianae 17 (1963): 173–76.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:wilmart-1911</IRI>
         <name>Wilmart 1911</name>
         <desc>Wilmart, André. “Les versions latines des sentences d'Évagre pour les vierges.” Revue Bénédictine 28 (1911): 143–53.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:wilmart-1922</IRI>
         <name>Wilmart 1922</name>
         <desc>Wilmart, André. “[No title].” Revue d'Ascétique et de Mystique 3 (1922): 413 n. 11.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>urn:isbn:978-1-84384-287-3</IRI>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:wilson-2011</IRI>
         <name>Wilson 2011</name>
         <desc>Wilson, N. G. A Descriptive Catalogue of the Greek Manuscripts at Corpus Christi College, Oxford. Cambridge: DSBrewer, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:wiltse-palmer-2011</IRI>
         <name>Wiltse and Palmer 2011</name>
         <name>wiltse palmer 2011</name>
         <desc>Wiltse, Virginia and Palmer, Helen. “Hidden in Plain Sight: Observations on the Origins of the Enneagram.” IEA Enneagram Journal  (2011): .got.net</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:wolf-1722</IRI>
         <IRI>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/7907597</IRI>
         <name>Wolf 1722-1724</name>
         <name>wolf 1722</name>
         <desc>Wolf, Johann Christoph. Anecdota graeca sacra et profana: Ex codicibus manu exaratis nunc primum in lucem edita, versione Latina donata et notis illustrata. Hamburg: Apud Theodorum Christophorum Felginer, 1722–1724. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:young-1992</IRI>
         <name>Young and Daly 1992</name>
         <name>young 1992</name>
         <desc>Young, Robin Darling. “The Armenian Adaptation of Evagrius' Kephalaia Gnostica.”  In Origeniana quinta: Historica, Text and Method, Biblica, Philosophica, Theologica, Origenism and Later developments: Papers of the 5th International Origen Congress, Boston College, 14–18 August 1989, pp. 535–41. Bibliotheca Ephemeridum theologicarum Lovaniensium 105. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1992. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:young-1997</IRI>
         <name>Young 1997</name>
         <desc>Young, Robin Darling. “Theologia in the Early Church.” Communio (US) 24 (1997): 681–90.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:young-2001</IRI>
         <name>Young 2001</name>
         <desc>Young, Robin Darling. “Evagrius the Iconographer: Monastic Pedagogy in the Gnostikos.” Journal of Early Christian Studies 1 (2001): 53–71.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:young-2007</IRI>
         <name>Young, Goehring, and Timbie 2007</name>
         <name>young 2007</name>
         <desc>Young, Robin Darling. “Cannibalism and Other Family Woes in Letter 55 of Evagrius of Pontus.”  In The World of Early Egyptian Christianity: Language, Literature, and Social Context; Essays in Honor of David W. Johnson, pp. 130–139. CUA Studies in Early Christianity. Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of America Press, 2007. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:young-2011</IRI>
         <name>Young, Blanchard, and Young 2011</name>
         <name>young 2011</name>
         <desc>Young, Robin Darling. “The Influence of Evagrius of Pontus on the Early Monastic Thought of Philoxenos of Mabbug.”  In To Train His Soul in Books: Syriac Asceticism in Early Christianity. Edited by Monica J Blanchard and Robin Darling Young, pp. 157–175. CUA studies in early Christianity. Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of America Press, 2011. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:young-2013</IRI>
         <name>Young 2013</name>
         <desc>Young, Robin Darling. “The Path to Contemplation in Evagrius’ Letters.” Studia Patristica 57 (2013): 75–86.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:young-2016</IRI>
         <name>Young 2016</name>
         <desc>Young, Robin Darling. “The Role of Letters in the Works of Evagrius.”  In Evagrius and His Legacy. Edited by Joel Kalvesmaki and Robin Darling Young, pp. 154–174. South Bend: University of Notre Dame Press, 2016. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:zigmund-cerbu-1959</IRI>
         <name>Zigmund-Cerbu 1959</name>
         <desc>Zigmund-Cerbu, A. “La préface du De Oratione d'Évagre.” Acta Philologica 2 (1959): 251–257.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:zizioulas-1985</IRI>
         <name>Zizioulas, McGinn, Meyendorff, and Leclercq 1985</name>
         <name>zizioulas 1985</name>
         <desc>Zizioulas, John D. “The Early Christian Community.”  In Christian Spirituality: Origins to the Twelfth Century, pp. 23–43. World spirituality 16. New York: Crossroad, 1985. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:zöckler-1893</IRI>
         <name>Zöckler 1893</name>
         <desc>Zöckler, Otto. Evagrius Pontikus: Seine Stellung in der altchristlichen Literatur- und Dogmengeschichte. Biblische und kirchenhistorische Studien 4. Munich: C. H. Beck, 1893. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:òmurchú-1983</IRI>
         <name>ÒMurchú 1983-1984</name>
         <name>òmurchú 1983</name>
         <desc>ÒMurchú, Diarmuid. “Early Christian Ascetism and its Relevance Today.” The Irish Theological Quarterly 50 (1983–1984): 83–117.</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:đakovac-2014</IRI>
         <name>Đjakovac 2014</name>
         <name>đakovac 2014</name>
         <desc>Đjakovac, Aleksandar. “Теолошке основе аскетске традиције Евагрија Понтијског (Theological Basis of Ascetic Tradition of Evagrius Ponticus).” Зборник Матице српске за друштвене науке 149, no. 4 (2014): 949–957.academia.edunb.rs</desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:ḳaṭraya-draguet-1972</IRI>
         <name>Ḳaṭraya and Draguet 1972</name>
         <name>ḳaṭraya draguet 1972</name>
         <desc>Ḳaṭraya, Dadishoʻ and Draguet, René. Commentaire du livre d'abba Isaïe (logoi I-XV). Corpus scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium. Scriptores Syri 144–145. 326–327. Louvain,: Secrétariat du CSCO, 1972. </desc>
      </item>
      <item>
         <IRI>tag:evagriusponticus.net,2012:scriptum:聡-1998</IRI>
         <name>聡 1998</name>
         <desc>聡, 戸田. “『師父たちの金言』とポントスのエウアグリオス.” (1998): 213–228.ac.jp</desc>
      </item>
   </body>
</TAN-voc>