<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TAN-T xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns" TAN-version="2021" id="tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:transcription:cpg2437.57:eng:2014:kalvesmaki">
   <head>
      <name>Kalvesmaki's translation of Letter 57 by Evagrius Ponticus</name>
      <master-location href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Arithmeticus/TAN-Evagrius/master/cpg2437/cpg2437.57.eng.2014.kalvesmaki.xml"/>
      <license which="by_4.0" licensor="kalvesmaki"/>
      <work which="Epistulae"/>
      <vocabulary>
         <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-key:evagrius</IRI>
         <name>General keywords associated with the TAN collection for Evagrius of Pontus</name>
         <location href="../TAN-voc/evagrius.TAN-voc.xml" accessed-when="2017-12-16-05:00"/>
      </vocabulary>
      <source which="Kalvesmaki 2014"/>
      <model which="cpg2437 grc Géhin" accessed-when="2025-12-22"/>

      <adjustments>
         <normalization which="no hyphens"/>
      </adjustments>
      <vocabulary-key>

         <person xml:id="kalvesmaki" which="Joel Kalvesmaki"/>
      </vocabulary-key>

      <file-resp who="kalvesmaki"/>
      <resp roles="editor" who="kalvesmaki"/>
      <change when="2025-12-22" who="kalvesmaki">Adjusted to new Géhin's 2025 reference system.</change>
      <change when="2020-09-21" who="kalvesmaki">Started file</change>
      <to-do></to-do>
   </head>
   <body xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="57" type="letter">
         <div n="1" type="section">Since you are mortal, you should not be very disheartened
            concerning the falling asleep of our revered father. “For we are proceeding to meet him,
            but he is not returning to us.” My desire, then, concerning all I have is this: I
            pledged a vow before God when I entered the rank of monks that after the death of my
            father nothing on the earth would be left for me, but I would spend it all as alms for
            the Lord. According to your word, then, you wrote to us in the time when
            sadness was burning you. But I, though also in lamentation, was called upon for this
            letter, and I was compelled to write these things that I received from you. </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">God, who
            comforts the downtrodden, also comforts us, by his suddenly granting us knowledge . . .
            (a) . . . of both death and life; (b) . . . of the body—which is our vessel—and of the
            rational soul; (c) . . . of why souls are bound by bodies and yet [the body] is
            perishable; (d) . . . of what reason angels and demons come to our realm; We, certainly,
            do not go to their realms, for neither are we able to bind further the angels to God,
            nor do we intend the spirits to be more foul. For neither do we attain to such great
            knowledge, nor are we left to such ignorance. (e) . . . also of how our fathers are our fathers only with
            regard to the body, but God is the Father of the soul. In the same way the sickness of
            the son disheartens the father, so also the disorder of the soul disheartens God. A
            father, at the sickness of his son, summons a physician. But from heaven God sends for
            the physician of our souls so that he might entice and draw men from wickedness to
            virtue and from ignorance to the knowledge of God. (f) . . . also of how he granted to the angels a habitation—the
            Upper Jerusalem (just as it is written, “You approached Mount Zion, and the city of the
            living God, the heavenly Jerusalem and the multitude of angels.”)—whereas he bound the
            demons in chains of darkness and committed them to the lowest parts of the earth so that
            they might be kept for the Judgment. But he placed us in this realm and joined us with
            laboring bodies, as it is written, “The heaven of heavens are the Lord’s, but the earth
            he gave to men,” so that, when we enact mercies, mercies might come to us, and that we
            might become co-inheritors with the angels, with whom, I believe, is our revered father,
            for he was merciful. Those who received mercies from him and sold him oil are
            witnesses.</div>
         <div n="3" type="section">These words of beginning knowledge emerged as lamentation touched
            me, and they transformed my distress. But you, O holy one, did well. You refreshed the
            blessed one in his life and, as he slept, you reverenced him within his holy grave,
            where our father Abraham and his sons sleep. And I shall confess [your deeds] before my
            Lord and before the holy angels, who will lead you and set you before the judgment seat
            of Christ our Savior.</div>
      </div>
   </body>
</TAN-T>